<front-matter>
<book-title>
<title>Grinstead and Snell's Introduction to Probability</title>
<subtitle></subtitle>The CHANCE Project<sup>1</sup></subtitle>
<releas-date>Version dated 4 July 2006</releas-date>
</book-title>
<contents-preface>
<sec id="content">
<label>Content</label>
<title>Preface</title>
<target type="page" id="2">2</target>
<label>1</label>
<title>Discrete Probability Distributions 1</title>
<subtitle>1.1	Simulation of Discrete Probabilities</subtitle>
<subtitle>1.2	Discrete Probability Distributions</subtitle>
<label>2</label>
<title>Continuous Probability Densities 41</title>
<subtitle>2.1	Simulation of Continuous Probabilities</subtitle>
<subtitle>2.2	Continuous Density Functions</subtitle>
<label>3</label>
<title>Combinatorics</title>
<subtitle>3.1	Permutations</subtitle>
<subtitle>3.2	Combinations</subtitle>
<subtitle>3.3	Card Shuffling</subtitle>
<label>4</label>
<title>Conditional Probability</title>
<subtitle>4.1	Discrete Conditional Probability</subtitle>
<subtitle>4.2	Continuous Conditional Probability</subtitle>
<subtitle>4.3	Paradoxes .</subtitle>
<label>5</label>
<title>	Distributions and Densities</title>
<subtitle>5.1	Important Distributions</subtitle>
<subtitle>5.2	Important Densities</subtitle>
<label>6</label>
<title>Expected Value and Variance</title>
<subtitle>6.1	Expected Value</subtitle>
<subtitle>6.2	Variance of Discrete Random Variables</subtitle>
<subtitle>6.3	Continuous Random Variables</subtitle>
<label>7.</label>
<title>Sums of Random Variables</title>
<subtitle>7.1	Sums of Discrete Random Variables</subtitle>
<subtitle>7.2	Sums of Continuous Random Variables</subtitle>
<label>8.</label>
<title>Law of Large Numbers</title>
<subtitle>8.1	Discrete Random Variables</subtitle>
<subtitle>8.2	Continuous Random Variables</subtitle>
<label>9.</label>
<title>	Central Limit Theorem</title>
<subtitle>9.1	Bernoulli Trials</subtitle>
<subtitle>9.2	Discrete Independent Trials</subtitle>
<subtitle>9.3	Continuous Independent Trials</subtitle>
<label>10</label>
<title>	Generating Functions</title>
<subtitle>10.1	Discrete Distributions</subtitle>
<subtitle>10.2	Branching Processes</subtitle>
<subtitle>10.3	Continuous Densities</subtitle>
<label>11</label>
<title>	Markov Chains</title>
<subtitle>11.1	Introduction</subtitle>
<subtitle>11.2	Absorbing Markov Chains</subtitle>
<subtitle>11.3	Ergodic Markov Chains</subtitle>
<subtitle>11.4	Fundamental Limit Theorem</subtitle>
<subtitle>11.5	Mean First Passage Time</subtitle>
<label>12</label>
<title>	Central Limit Theorem</title>
<subtitle>12.1	Random Walks in Euclidean Space</subtitle>
<subtitle>12.2	Gambler's Ruin</subtitle>
<subtitle>12.3	Arc Sine Laws</subtitle>
<p>Appendices</p>
<p>Index</p>
</sec>
<sec id="preface">
<p>Probability theory began in seventeenth century France when the two great French mathematicians, Blaise Pascal and Pierre de Fermat, corresponded over two problems from games of chance. Problems like those Pascal and Fermat solved continued to influence such early researchers as Huygens, Bernoulli, and DeMoivre in establishing a mathematical theory of probability. Today, probability theory is a wellestablished branch of mathematics that finds applications in every area of scholarly activity from music to physics, and in daily experience from weather prediction to predicting the risks of new medical treatments.</p>
<p role="indent">This text is designed for an introductory probability course taken by sophomores, juniors, and seniors in mathematics, the physical and social sciences, engineering, and computer science. It presents a thorough treatment of probability ideas and techniques necessary for a firm understanding of the subject. The text can be used in a variety of course lengths, levels, and areas of emphasis.</p>
<p role="indent">For use in a standard one-term course, in which both discrete and continuous probability is covered, students should have taken as a prerequisite two terms of calculus, including an introduction to multiple integrals. In order to cover Chapter 11, which contains material on Markov chains, some knowledge of matrix theory is necessary.</p>
<p role="indent">The text can also be used in a discrete probability course. The material has been organized in such a way that the discrete and continuous probability discussions are presented in a separate, but parallel, manner. This organization dispels an overly rigorous or formal view of probability and offers some strong pedagogical value in that the discrete discussions can sometimes serve to motivate the more abstract continuous probability discussions. For use in a discrete probability course, students should have taken one term of calculus as a prerequisite.</p>
<p role="indent">Very little computing background is assumed or necessary in order to obtain full benefits from the use of the computing material and examples in the text. All of the programs that are used in the text have been written in each of the languages TrueBASIC, Maple, and Mathematica.</p>
<p role="indent">This book is distributed on the Web as part of the Chance Project, which is devoted to providing materials for beginning courses in probability and statistics. The computer programs, solutions to the odd-numbered exercises, and current errata are also available at this site. Instructors may obtain all of the solutions by writing to either of the authors, at jlsnell@dartmouth.edu and cgrinst1@swarthmore.edu.</p>
<sec id="FEATURES">
<title>FEATURES</title>
<p role="indent">Level of rigor and emphasis: Probability is a wonderfully intuitive and applicable field of mathematics. We have tried not to spoil its beauty by presenting too much formal mathematics. Rather, we have tried to develop the key ideas in a somewhat leisurely style, to provide a variety of interesting applications to probability, and to show some of the nonintuitive examples that make probability such a lively subject.</p>
<p role="indent">Exercises: There are over 600 exercises in the text providing plenty of opportunity for practicing skills and developing a sound understanding of the ideas. In the exercise sets are routine exercises to be done with and without the use of a computer and more theoretical exercises to improve the understanding of basic concepts. More difficult exercises are indicated by an asterisk. A solution manual for all of the exercises is available to instructors.</p>
<p role="indent">Historical remarks: Introductory probability is a subject in which the fundamental ideas are still closely tied to those of the founders of the subject. For this reason, there are numerous historical comments in the text, especially as they deal with the development of discrete probability.</p>
<p role="indent">Pedagogical use of computer programs: Probability theory makes predictions about experiments whose outcomes depend upon chance. Consequently, it lends itself beautifully to the use of computers as a mathematical tool to simulate and analyze chance experiments.</p>
<p role="indent">In the text the computer is utilized in several ways. First, it provides a laboratory where chance experiments can be simulated and the students can get a feeling for the variety of such experiments. This use of the computer in probability has been already beautifully illustrated by William Feller in the second edition of his famous text An Introduction to Probability Theory and Its Applications (New York: Wiley, 1950). In the preface, Feller wrote about his treatment of fluctuation in coin tossing: "The results are so amazing and so at variance with common intuition that even sophisticated colleagues doubted that coins actually misbehave as theory predicts. The record of a simulated experiment is therefore included."</p>
<p role="indent">In addition to providing a laboratory for the student, the computer is a powerful aid in understanding basic results of probability theory. For example, the graphical illustration of the approximation of the standardized binomial distributions to the normal curve is a more convincing demonstration of the Central Limit Theorem than many of the formal proofs of this fundamental result</p>
<p role="indent">Finally, the computer allows the student to solve problems that do not lend themselves to closed-form formulas such as waiting times in queues. Indeed, the introduction of the computer changes the way in which we look at many problems in probability. For example, being able to calculate exact binomial probabilities for experiments up to 1000 trials changes the way we view the normal and Poisson approximations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ACKNOWLEDGMENTS">
<title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
<p role="indent">Anyone writing a probability text today owes a greatdebt to William Feller, who taught us all how to make probability come alive as a subject matter. If you PREFACE find an example, an application, or an exercise that you really like, it probably had its origin in Feller's classic text, An Introduction to Probability Theory and ItsApplications.</p>
<p role="indent">We are indebted to many people for their help in this undertaking. The approach to Markov Chains presented in the book was developed by John Kemeny and the second author. Reese Prosser was a silent co-author for the material on continuous probability in an earlier version of this book. Mark Kernighan contributed 40 pages of comments on the earlier edition. Many of these comments were very thoughtprovoking; in addition, they provided a student's perspective on the book. Most of the major changes in this version of the book have their genesis in these notes.</p>
<p role="indent">Finally, we thank the American Mathematical Society, and in particular Sergei Gelfand and John Ewing, for their interest in this book; their help in its production; and their willingness to make the work freely redistributable.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</contents-preface>
</front-matter>
<body>
<chapter id="chap1">
<label>Chapter 1</label>
<title>Discrete Probability Distributions</title>
<sec id="sec_1_1">
<label>1.1</label>
<title>Simulation of Discrete Probabilities</title>
<sec id="sec_Probability">
<title>Probability</title>
<p role="noindent">In this chapter, we shall first consider chance experiments with a finite number ofpossible outcomes &#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>, &#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>, . . . , &#x03C9;<sub>n</sub>. For example, we roll a die and the possibleoutcomes are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 corresponding to the side that turns up. We toss a coinwith possible outcomes H (heads) and T (tails).</p>
<p role="indent">It is frequently useful to be able to refer to an outcome of an experiment. Forexample, we might want to write the mathematical expression which gives the sumof four rolls of a die. To do this, we could let<i>X</i><sub>i</sub>,<i>i</i> = 1, 2, 3, 4, represent the valuesof the outcomes of the four rolls, and then we could write the expression</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>3</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>4</mn></msub>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">for the sum of the four rolls. The<i>X</i><sub>i</sub>&#x2019;s are called<i>random variables</i>. A random variable is simply an expression whose value is the outcome of a particular experiment.Just as in the case of other types of variables in mathematics, random variables cantake on different values.</p>
<p role="indent">Let<i>X</i> be the random variable which represents the roll of one die. We shallassign probabilities to the possible outcomes of this experiment. We do this byassigning to each outcome &#x03C9;<sub>j</sub> a nonnegative number<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>j</sub>) in such a way that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>&#x03C9;</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>&#x03C9;</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>&#x03C9;</mi><mn>6</mn></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The function<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>j</sub>) is called the<i>distribution function</i> of the random variable<i>X</i>.For the case of the roll of the die we would assign equal probabilities or probabilities1/6 to each of the outcomes. With this assignment of probabilities, one could write</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>2</mn>
<mn>3</mn>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_1">1</target>
<p role="indent">to mean that the probability is 2/3 that a roll of a die will have a value which doesnot exceed 4.</p>
<p role="indent">Let<i>Y</i> be the random variable which represents the toss of a coin. In this case,there are two possible outcomes, which we can label as H and T. Unless we havereason to suspect that the coin comes up one way more often than the other way,it is natural to assign the probability of 1/2 to each of the two outcomes.</p>
<p role="indent">In both of the above experiments, each outcome is assigned an equal probability.This would certainly not be the case in general. For example, if a drug is found tobe effective 30 percent of the time it is used, we might assign a probability .3 thatthe drug is effective the next time it is used and .7 that it is not effective. This lastexample illustrates the intuitive frequency concept of probability. That is, if we haveexperiment a large number of times we should expect that the fraction of times that<i>A</i> will occur is about<i>p</i>. To check intuitive ideas like this, we shall find it helpful tolook at some of these problems experimentally. We could, for example, toss a coina large number of times and see if the fraction of times heads turns up is about 1/2.We could also simulate this experiment on a computer.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec_Simulation">
<title>Simulation</title>
<p role="noindent">We want to be able to perform an experiment that corresponds to a given set ofprobabilities; for example,<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>) = 1/2,<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>) = 1/3, and<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>3</sub>) = 1/6. In thiscase, one could mark three faces of a six-sided die with an &#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>, two faces with an &#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>,and one face with an &#x03C9;<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p role="indent">In the general case we assume that<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>),<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>), . . . ,<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>n</sub>) are all rationalnumbers, with least common denominator<i>n</i>. If<i>n</i> &gt; 2, we can imagine a loncylindrical die with a cross-section that is a regular<i>n</i>-gon. If<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>j</sub>) =<i>n</i><sub>j</sub>/<i>n</i>, thenwe can label<i>n</i><sub>j</sub> of the long faces of the cylinder with an &#x03C9;<sub>j</sub>, and if one of the endfaces comes up, we can just roll the die again. If<i>n</i> = 2, a coin could be used toperform the experiment.</p>
<p role="indent">We will be particularly interested in repeating a chance experiment a large number of times. Although the cylindrical die would be a convenient way to carry outa few repetitions, it would be difficult to carry out a large number of experiments.Since the modern computer can do a large number of operations in a very shorttime, it is natural to turn to the computer for this task.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_RandomNumbers">
<title>Random Numbers</title>
<p role="noindent">We must first find a computer analog of rolling a die. This is done on the computerby means of a<i>random number generator</i>. Depending upon the particular softwarepackage, the computer can be asked for a real number between 0 and 1, or an integerin a given set of consecutive integers. In the first case, the real numbers are chosenin such a way that the probability that the number lies in any particular subintervalof this unit interval is equal to the length of the subinterval. In the second case,each integer has the same probability of being chosen.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_2">2</target>
<table-wrap id="table_1_1">
<label>Table 1.1</label>
<caption><p>Sample output of the program<bold>RandomNumbers</bold>.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Col 1</th>
<th>Col 2</th>
<th>Col 3</th>
<th>Col 4</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>.203309</td>
<td>.762057</td>
<td>.151121</td>
<td>.623868</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.932052</td>
<td>.415178</td>
<td>.716719</td>
<td>.967412</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.069664</td>
<td>.670982</td>
<td>.352320</td>
<td>.049723</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.750216</td>
<td>.784810</td>
<td>.089734</td>
<td>.966730</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.946708</td>
<td>.380365</td>
<td>.027381</td>
<td>.900794</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="indent">Let<i>X</i> be a random variable with distribution function<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;), where &#x03C9; is in theset {&#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>, &#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>, &#x03C9;<sub>3</sub>}, and<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>) = 1/2,<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>) = 1/3, and<i>m</i>(&#x03C9;<sub>3</sub>) = 1/6. If our computerpackage can return a random integer in the set {1, 2, ..., 6}, then we simply ask itto do so, and make 1, 2, and 3 correspond to &#x03C9;<sub>1</sub>, 4 and 5 correspond to &#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>, and 6correspond to &#x03C9;<sub>3</sub>. If our computer package returns a random real number<i>r</i> in theinterval (0, 1), then the expression</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x230A;</mo><mn>6</mn><mi>r</mi><mo>&#x230B;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">will be a random integer between 1 and 6. (The notation &#x230A;<i>x</i>&#x230B; means the greatestinteger not exceeding<i>x</i>, and is read &#x201C;floor of<i>x</i>.&#x201D;)</p>
<p role="indent">The method by which random real numbers are generated on a computer isdescribed in the historical discussion at the end of this section. The followingexample gives sample output of the program<bold>RandomNumbers</bold>.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_3">3</target>
<sec id="example1.1">
<label>Example 1.1</label>
<title>(Random Number Generation)</title>
<p role="noindent">The program<bold>RandomNumbers</bold>generates<i>n</i> random real numbers in the interval [0, 1], where<i>n</i> is chosen by theuser. When we ran the program with<i>n</i> = 20, we obtained the data shown inTable 1.1. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec id="example1.2">
<label>Example 1.2</label>
<title>(Coin Tossing)</title>
<p role="noindent">As we have noted, our intuition suggests that theprobability of obtaining a head on a single toss of a coin is 1/2. To have thecomputer toss a coin, we can ask it to pick a random real number in the interval[0, 1] and test to see if this number is less than 1/2. If so, we shall call the outcomeheads; if not we call it tails. Another way to proceed would be to ask the computerto pick a random integer from the set {0, 1}. The program<bold>CoinTosses</bold> carriesout the experiment of tossing a coin<i>n</i> times. Running this program, with<i>n</i> = 20,resulted in:</p>
<p role="noindent">THTTTHTTTTHTTTTTHHTT.</p>
<p role="indent">Note that in 20 tosses, we obtained 5 heads and 15 tails. Let us toss a coin<i>n</i>times, where<i>n</i> is much larger than 20, and see if we obtain a proportion of headscloser to our intuitive guess of 1/2. The program<bold>CoinTosses</bold> keeps track of thenumber of heads. When we ran this program with<i>n</i> = 1000, we obtained 494 heads.When we ran it with<i>n</i> = 10000, we obtained 5039 heads.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_4">4</target>
<p role="indent">We notice that when we tossed the coin 10,000 times, the proportion of headswas close to the &#x201C;true value&#x201D; .5 for obtaining a head when a coin is tossed. A mathematical model for this experiment is called<i>Bernoulli Trials</i> (see Chapter 3). The<i>Law of Large Numbers</i>, which we shall study later (see Chapter 8), will show thatin the Bernoulli Trials model, the proportion of heads should be near .5, consistentwith our intuitive idea of the frequency interpretation of probability.</p>
<p role="indent">Of course, our program could be easily modified to simulate coins for which theprobability of a head is<i>p</i>, where<i>p</i> is a real number between 0 and 1. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<p role="indent">In the case of coin tossing, we already knew the probability of the event occurringon each experiment. The real power of simulation comes from the ability to estimateprobabilities when they are not known ahead of time. This method has been used inthe recent discoveries of strategies that make the casino game of blackjack favorableto the player. We illustrate this idea in a simple situation in which we can computethe true probability and see how effective the simulation is.</p>
<sec id="example1.3">
<label>Example 1.3</label>
<title>(Dice Rolling)</title>
<p role="noindent">We consider a dice game that played an importantrole in the historical development of probability. The famous letters between Pascal and Fermat, which many believe started a serious study of probability, wereinstigated by a request for help from a French nobleman and gambler, Chevalierde M&#xe9;r&#xe9;. It is said that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; had been betting that, in four rolls of a die, atleast one six would turn up. He was winning consistently and, to get more peopleto play, he changed the game to bet that, in 24 rolls of two dice, a pair of sixeswould turn up. It is claimed that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; lost with 24 and felt that 25 rolls werenecessary to make the game favorable. It was<i>un grand scandale</i> that mathematicswas wrong.</p>
<p role="indent">We shall try to see if de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; is correct by simulating his various bets. Theprogram<bold>DeMere1</bold> simulates a large number of experiments, seeing, in each one,if a six turns up in four rolls of a die. When we ran this program for 1000 plays,a six came up in the first four rolls 48.6 percent of the time. When we ran it for10,000 plays this happened 51.98 percent of the time.</p>
<p role="indent">We note that the result of the second run suggests that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; was correctin believing that his bet with one die was favorable; however, if we had based ourconclusion on the first run, we would have decided that he was wrong. Accurateresults by simulation require a large number of experiments. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<p role="indent">The program<bold>DeMere2</bold> simulates de M&#xe9;r&#xe9;&#x2019;s second bet that a pair of sixeswill occur in<i>n</i> rolls of a pair of dice. The previous simulation shows that it isimportant to know how many trials we should simulate in order to expect a certaindegree of accuracy in our approximation. We shall see later that in these types ofexperiments, a rough rule of thumb is that, at least 95% of the time, the error doesnot exceed the reciprocal of the square root of the number of trials. Fortunately,for this dice game, it will be easy to compute the exact probabilities. We shallshow in the next section that for the first bet the probability that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; wins is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mn>4</mn>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.518</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_5">5</target>
<fig id="fig_1_1">
<label>Figure 1.1</label>
<caption><p>Peter&#x2019;s winnings in 40 plays of heads or tails.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1_1.jpg"/>
</fig>
<p role="indent">One can understand this calculation as follows: The probability that no 6 turnsup on the first toss is (5/6). The probability that no 6 turns up on either of thefirst two tosses is (5/6)<sup>2</sup>. Reasoning in the same way, the probability that no 6turns up on any of the first four tosses is (5/6)<sup>4</sup>. Thus, the probability of at leastone 6 in the first four tosses is
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mn>4</mn>
</msup>
</mrow>
</math>.
Similarly, for the second bet, with 24
rolls, the probability that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; wins is
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>35</mn><mn>36</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mn>24</mn>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.491</mn>
</mrow>
</math>,
and for 25 rolls it is
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>35</mn><mn>36</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mn>25</mn>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.506</mn>
</mrow>
</math>.</p>
<p role="indent">Using the rule of thumb mentioned above, it would require 27,000 rolls to have a reasonable chance to determine these probabilities with sufficient accuracy to assert that they lie on opposite sides of .5. It is interesting to ponder whether a gambler can detect such probabilities with the required accuracy from gambling experience. Some writers on the history of probability suggest that de M&#xe9;r&#xe9; was, in fact, just interested in these problems as intriguing probability problems.</p>
<sec id="example1.4">
<label>Example 1.4</label>
<title>(Heads or Tails)</title>
<p role="noindent">For our next example, we consider a problem wherethe exact answer is difficult to obtain but for which simulation easily gives thequalitative results. Peter and Paul play a game called<i>heads or tails</i>. In this game,a fair coin is tossed a sequence of times&#x2014;we choose 40. Each time a head comes upPeter wins 1 penny from Paul, and each time a tail comes up Peter loses 1 pennyto Paul. For example, if the results of the 40 tosses are</p>
<p role="noindent">THTHHHHTTHTHHTTHHTTTTHHHTHHTHHHTHHHTTTHH.</p>
<p role="indent">Peter&#x2019;s winnings may be graphed as in Figure 1.1.</p>
<p role="indent">Peter has won 6 pennies in this particular game. It is natural to ask for the probability that he will win<i>j</i> pennies; here<i>j</i> could be any even number from &#x2212;40to 40. It is reasonable to guess that the value of<i>j</i> with the highest probabilityis<i>j</i> = 0, since this occurs when the number of heads equals the number of tails.Similarly, we would guess that the values of<i>j</i> with the lowest probabilities are
<i>j</i> = &#x00B1;40.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_6">6</target>
<p role="indent">A second interesting question about this game is the following: How many times in the 40 tosses will Peter be in the lead? Looking at the graph of his winnings(Figure 1.1), we see that Peter is in the lead when his winnings are positive, butwe have to make some convention when his winnings are 0 if we want all tosses tocontribute to the number of times in the lead. We adopt the convention that, whenPeter&#x2019;s winnings are 0, he is in the lead if he was ahead at the previous toss andnot if he was behind at the previous toss. With this convention, Peter is in the lead34 times in our example. Again, our intuition might suggest that the most likelynumber of times to be in the lead is 1/2 of 40, or 20, and the least likely numbersare the extreme cases of 40 or 0.</p>
<p role="indent">It is easy to settle this by simulating the game a large number of times and keeping track of the number of times that Peter&#x2019;s final winnings are<i>j</i>, and the number of times that Peter ends up being in the lead by<i>k</i>. The proportions over all games then give estimates for the corresponding probabilities. The program<bold>HTSimulation</bold> carries out this simulation. Note that when there are an even number of tosses in the game, it is possible to be in the lead only an even number of times. We have simulated this game 10,000 times. The results are shown in Figures 1.2 and 1.3. These graphs, which we call<i>spike graphs</i>, were generated using the program<bold>Spikegraph</bold>. The vertical line, or spike, at position<i>x</i> on the horizontal axis, has a height equal to the proportion of outcomes which equal<i>x</i>. Our intuition about Peter&#x2019;s final winnings was quite correct, but our intuition about the number of times Peter was in the lead was completely wrong. The simulation suggests that the least likely number of times in the lead is 20 and the most likely is 0 or 40. This is indeed correct, and the explanation for it is suggested by playing the game of heads or tails with a large number of tosses and looking at a graph of Peter&#x2019;s winnings. In Figure 1.4 we show the results of a simulation of the game, for 1000 tosses and in Figure 1.5 for 10,000 tosses.</p>
<p role="indent">In the second example Peter was ahead most of the time. It is a remarkablefact, however, that, if play is continued long enough, Peter&#x2019;s winnings will continueto come back to 0, but there will be very long times between the times that thishappens. These and related results will be discussed in Chapter 12. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<p role="indent">In all of our examples so far, we have simulated equiprobable outcomes. We illustrate next an example where the outcomes are not equiprobable.</p>
<sec id="example1.5">
<label>Example 1.5</label>
<title>(Horse Races)</title>
<p role="noindent">Four horses (Acorn, Balky, Chestnut, and Dolby)have raced many times. It is estimated that Acorn wins 30 percent of the time,Balky 40 percent of the time, Chestnut 20 percent of the time, and Dolby 10 percentof the time.</p>
<p role="indent">We can have our computer carry out one race as follows: Choose a randomnumber<i>x</i>. If<i>x</i> &lt; .3 then we say that Acorn won. If .3 &#x2264;<i>x</i> &lt; .7 then Balky wins.If .7 &#x2264;<i>x</i> &lt; .9 then Chestnut wins. Finally, if .9 &#x2264;<i>x</i> then Dolby wins.</p>
<p role="indent">The program<bold>HorseRace</bold> uses this method to simulate the outcomes of<i>n</i> races.Running this program for<i>n</i> = 10 we found that Acorn won 40 percent of the time,Balky 20 percent of the time, Chestnut 10 percent of the time, and Dolby 30 percent</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_7">7</target>
<fig id="fig_1_2">
<label>Figure 1.2</label>
<caption><p>Distribution of winnings.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1_2.jpg"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig_1_3">
<label>Figure 1.3</label>
<caption><p>Distribution of number of times in the lead.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1_3.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_8">8</target>
<fig id="fig_1_4">
<label>Figure 1.4</label>
<caption><p>Peter&#x2019;s winnings in 1000 plays of heads or tails.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1_4.jpg"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig_1_5">
<label>Figure 1.5</label>
<caption><p>Peter&#x2019;s winnings in 10,000 plays of heads or tails.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1_5.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_9">9</target>
<p role="indent">of the me. A larger number of races would be necessary to have better agreementwith the past experience. Therefore we ran the program to simulate 1000 raceswith our our horses. Although very tired after all these races, they performed ia manner quite consistent with our estimates of their abilities. Acorn won 29.8percent of the time, Balky 39.4 percent, Chestnut 19.5 percent, and Dolby 11.3percent of the time.</p><p role="indent">The program<bold>GeneralSimulation</bold> uses this method to simulate repetitions ofan arbitrary experiment with a finite number of outcomes occurring with knownprobabilities. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_HistoricalRemarks">
<title>Historical Remarks</title>
<p role="noindent">Anyone who plays the same chance game over and over is really carrying out a simulation, and in this sense the process of simulation has been going on for centuries.As we have remarked, many of the early problems of probability might well havebeen suggested by gamblers&#x2019; experiences.</p>
<p role="indent">It is natural for anyone trying to understand probability theory to try simpleexperiments by tossing coins, rolling dice, and so forth. The naturalist Buffon tosseda coin 4040 times, resulting in 2048 heads and 1992 tails. He also estimated thenumber &#x03C0; by throwing needles on a ruled surface and recording how many timesthe needles crossed a line (see Section 2.1). The English biologist W. F. R. Weldon<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>recorded 26,306 throws of 12 dice, and the Swiss scientist Rudolf Wolf<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref> recorded100,000 throws of a single die without a computer. Such experiments are very time-consuming and may not accurately represent the chance phenomena being studied.For example, for the dice experiments of Weldon and Wolf, further analysis of therecorded data showed a suspected bias in the dice. The statistician Karl Pearsonanalyzed a large number of outcomes at certain roulette tables and suggested thatthe wheels were biased. He wrote in 1894:</p><p>Clearly, since the Casino does not serve the valuable end of huge laboratory for the preparation of probability statistics, it has no scientific<i>raison d&#x2019;&#x00EA;tre</i>. Men of science cannot have their most refined theoriesdisregarded in this shameless manner! The French Government must beurged by the hierarchy of science to close the gaming-saloons; it wouldbe, ofcourse, a graceful act to hand over the remaining resources of theCasino to the Acad&#xe9;mie des Sciences for the endowment of a laboratoryof orthodox probability; in particular, of the new branch of that study,the application of the theory of chance to the biological problems ofevolution, which is likely to occupy so much of men&#x2019;s thoughts in thenear future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref></p>
<p role="indent">However, these early experiments were suggestive and led to important discoveries in probability and statistics. They led Pearson to the<i>chi-squared test</i>, which</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_9b">9</target>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fry</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Probability and Its Engineering Uses</source>
<edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>Van Nostrand</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
<year>1965</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Czuber</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Wahrscheinlichkeitsrechnung</source>
<edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>Teubner</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
<year>1914</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Science and Monte Carlo</article-title>
<source>Fortnightly Review</source>
<volume>55</volume>
<year>1894</year>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<comment>cited in S. M. Stigler,<i>The History of Statistics</i> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1986)</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<target target-type="page" id="page_10">10</target>
<p role="indent">is of great importance in testing whether observed data fit a given probability distribution.</p>
<p role="indent">By the early 1900s it was clear that a better way to generate random numberswas needed. In 1927, L. H. C. Tippett published a list of 41,600 digits obtained byselecting numbers haphazardly from census reports. In 1955, RAND Corporationprinted a table of 1,000,000 random numbers generated from electronic noise. Theadvent of the high-speed computer raised the possibility of generating random numbers directly on the computer, and in the late 1940s John von Neumann suggestedthat this be done as follows: Suppose that you want a random sequence of four-digitnumbers. Choose any four-digit number, say 6235, to start. Square this numberto obtain 38,875,225. For the second number choose the middle four digits of thissquare (i.e., 8752). Do the same process starting with 8752 to get the third number,and so forth.</p>
<p role="indent">More modern methods involve the concept of modular arithmetic. If<i>a</i> is aninteger and<i>m</i> is a positive integer, then by<i>a</i> (mod<i>m</i>) we mean the remainderwhen<i>a</i> is divided by<i>m</i>. For example, 10 (mod 4) = 2, 8 (mod 2) = 0, and soforth. To generate a random sequence<i>X</i><sub>0</sub>,<i>X</i><sub>1</sub>,<i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . . of numbers choose a startingnumber<i>X</i><sub>0</sub> and then obtain the numbers<i>X</i><sub>n+1</sub> from<i>X</i><sub>n</sub> by the formula</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>(</mo>
<mi>a</mi><msub><mi>X</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>c</mi>
<mo>)</mo>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mi>m</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where<i>a</i>,<i>c</i>, and<i>m</i> are carefully chosen constants. The sequence<i>X</i><sub>0</sub>,<i>X</i><sub>1</sub>,<i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . .is then a sequence of integers between 0 and<i>m</i> &#x2212; 1. To obtain a sequence of realnumbers in [0, 1), we divide each<i>X</i><sub>j</sub> by<i>m</i>. The resulting sequence consists ofrational numbers of the form<i>j</i>/<i>m</i>, where 0 &#x2264;<i>j</i> &#x2264;<i>m</i> &#x2212; 1. Since<i>m</i> is usually avery large integer, we think of the numbers in the sequence as being random realnumbers in [0, 1).</p>
<p role="indent">For both von Neumann&#x2019;s squaring method and the modular arithmetic techniquethe sequence of numbers is actually completely determined by the first number.Thus, there is nothing really random about these sequences. However, they producenumbers that behave very much as theory would predict for random experiments.To obtain different sequences for different experiments the initial number<i>X</i><sub>0</sub> ischosen by some other procedure that might involve, for example, the time of day.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref></p>
<p role="indent">During the Second World War, physicists at the Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory needed to know, for purposes of shielding, how far neutrons travel throughvarious materials. This question was beyond the reach of theoretical calculations.Daniel McCracken, writing in the<i>Scientific American</i>, states:</p>
 
<p>The physicists had most of the necessary data: they knew the averagedistance a neutron of a given speed would travel in a given substancebefore it collided with an atomic nucleus, what the probabilities werethat the neutron would bounce off instead of being absorbed by thenucleus, how much energy the neutron was likely to lose after a given</p>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knuth</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>The Art of Computer Programming</source>
<volume>vol. II</volume>
<publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Reading</publisher-loc>
<year>1969</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<target target-type="page" id="page_11">11</target>
<p role="indent">collision and so on.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref></p>
<p role="indent">John von Neumann and Stanislas Ulam suggested that the problem be solvedby modeling the experiment by chance devices on a computer. Their work beingsecret, it was necessary to give it a code name. Von Neumann chose the name&#x201C;Monte Carlo.&#x201D; Since that time, this method of simulation has been called the<i>Monte Carlo Method</i>.</p>
<p role="indent">William Feller indicated the possibilities of using computer simulations to illustrate basic concepts in probability in his book<i>An Introduction to Probability Theoryand Its Applications</i>. In discussing the problem about the number of times in thelead in the game of &#x201C;heads or tails&#x201D; Feller writes:</p>
<p>The results concerning fluctuations in coin tossing show that widelyheld beliefs about the law of large numbers are fallacious. These resultsare so amazing and so at variance with common intuition that evensophisticated colleagues doubted that coins actually misbehave as theorypredicts. The record of a simulated experiment is therefore included.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref></p>
<p role="indent">Feller provides a plot showing the result of 10,000 plays of<i>heads or tails</i> similar tothat in Figure 1.5.</p>
<p role="indent">The martingale betting system described in Exercise 10 has a long and interesting history. Russell Barnhart pointed out to the authors that its use can be tracedback at least to 1754, when Casanova, writing in his memoirs,<i>History of My Life</i>,writes</p>
<p>She [Casanova&#x2019;s mistress] made me promise to go to the casino [theRidotto in Venice] for money to play in partnership with her. I wentthere and took all the gold I found, and, determinedly doubling mystakes according to the system known as the martingale, I won three orfour times a day during the rest of the Carnival. I never lost the sixthcard. If I had lost it, I should have been out of funds, which amountedto two thousand zecchini.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref></p>
<p role="indent">Even if there were no zeros on the roulette wheel so the game was perfectly fair,the martingale system, or any other system for that matter, cannot make the gameinto a favorable game. The idea that a fair game remains fair and unfair gamesremain unfair under gambling systems has been exploited by mathematicians toobtain important results in the study of probability. We will introduce the generalconcept of a martingale in Chapter 6.</p>
<p role="indent">The word<i>martingale</i> itself also has an interesting history. The origin of theword is obscure. A recent version of the<i>Oxford English Dictionary</i> gives examples</p>

<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCracken</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The Monte Carlo Method</article-title>
<source>Scientific American</source>
<volume>192</volume>
<year>1955</year>
<month>May</month>
<fpage>90</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feller</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Introduction to Probability Theory and its Applications</source>
<volume>vol. 1</volume>
<edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1968</year>
<fpage>xi</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Casanova</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>History of My Life</source>
<volume>vol. IV, Chap. 7</volume>
<person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name>
<surname>Trask</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<publisher-name>Harcourt-Brace</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1968</year>
<fpage>124</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</sec>
</sec>of its use in the early 1600s and says that its probable origin is the reference in Rabelais's Book One, Chapter 20:</p>

<p role="indent">Everything was done as planned, the only thing being that Gargantua doubted if they would be able to find, right away, breeches suitable to the old fellow's legs; he was doubtful, also, as to what cut would be most becoming to the orator-the martingale, which has a draw-bridge effect in the seat, to permit doing one's business more easily; the sailor-style, which affords more comfort for the kidneys; the Swiss, which is warmer on the belly; or the codfish-tail, which is cooler on the loins.</p>
<p role="indent">Dominic Luschnig noted an earlier occurrence of the word martingale. According to the French dictionary<i>Le Petit Robert</i>, the word comes from the Provençal word "martégal," which means "from Martigues." Martigues is a town west of Marseille. The dictionary gives the example of "chausses à la martingale" (which means Martigues-style breeches) and the date 1491.</p>
<p role="indent">In modern uses martingale has several different meanings, all related to<i>holding down</i>, in addition to the gambling use. For example, it is a strap on a horse's harness used to hold down the horse's head, and also part of a sailing rig used to hold down the bowsprit.</p>
<p role="indent">The Labouchere system described in Exercise 9 is named after Henry du Pre Labouchere (1831-1912), an English journalist and member of Parliament. Labouchere attributed the system to Condorcet (1743-1794) was a political leader during the time of the French revolution who was interested in applying probability theory to economics and politics. For example, he calculated the probability that a jury using majority vote will give a correct decision if each juror has the same probability of deciding correctly. His writings provide a wealth of ideas on how probability might be applied to human affairs.<sup>9</sup></p>
<sec id="exercises">
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol type="1">
<li>Modify the program<i>CoinTosses</i> to toss a coin n times and print out after every 100 tosses the proportion of heads minus 1/2. Do these numbers appear to approach 0 as n increases? Modify the program again to print out, every 100 times, both of the following quantities: the proportion of heads minus 1/2, and the number of heads minus half the number of tosses. Do these numbers appear to approach 0 as n increases?</li>
<li>Modify the program<i>CoinTosses</i> so that it tosses a coin n times and records whether or not the proportion of heads is within .1 of .5 (i.e., between .4 and .6). Have your program repeat this experiment 100 times. About how large must n be so that approximately 95 out of 100 times the proportion of heads is between .4 and .6?</li>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Putnam</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>The Portable Rabelais</source>
<publisher-name>Viking</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1946</year>
<comment>p. 113</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R2">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Condorcet</surname>
<given-names>M. de la Maguise de</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Essai sur l'Application de l'Analyse à la Probabilité des Décisions Rendues à la Pluralité des Voix</source>
<publisher-name>Imprimerie Royale</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
<year>1785</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<target target-type="page" id="page_13">13</target>
<ol>in the early 1600s, Galileo was asked to explain the fact that, although the number of triples of integers from 1 to 6 with sum 9 is the same as the number of such triples with sum 10, when three dice are rolled, a 9 seemed to come up less often than a 10-supposedly in the experience of gamblers.
<li>
<ol type="a">
(a) Write a program to simulate the roll of three dice a large number of times and keep track of the proportion of times that the sum is 9 and the proportion of times it is 10.
<li>
(b) Can you conclude from your simulations that the gamblers were correct?
</li>
</li></ol>
<li>
 In racquetball, a player continues to serve as long as she is winning; a point is scored only when a player is serving and wins the volley. The first player to win 21 points wins the game. Assume that you serve first and have a probability .6 of winning a volley when you serve and probability .5 when your opponent serves. Estimate, by simulation, the probability that you will win a game.
</li>
<li>
Consider the bet that all three dice will turn up sixes at least once in n rolls of three dice. Calculate f(n), the probability of at least one triple-six when three dice are rolled n times. Determine the smallest value of n necessary for a favorable bet that a triple-six will occur when three dice are rolled n times. DeMoivre would say it should be about 216 log 2 = 149.7 and so would answer 150-see Exercise 1.2.17. Do you agree with him?
</li>
<li>
 In Las Vegas, a roulette wheel has 38 slots numbered 0, 00, 1, 2, ., 36. The 0 and 00 slots are green and half of the remaining 36 slots are red and half are black. A croupier spins the wheel and throws in an ivory ball. If you bet 1 dollar on red, you win 1 dollar if the ball stops in a red slot and otherwise you lose 1 dollar. Write a program to find the total winnings for a player who makes 100 bets on red.
</li>
<li>
 Another form of bet for roulette is to bet that a specific number (say 17) will turn up. If the ball stops on your number, you get your dollar back plus 35 dollars. If not, you lose your dollar. Write a program that will plot your winnings when you make 500 plays of roulette at Las Vegas, first when you bet each time on red (see Exercise 6), and then for a second visit to Las Vegas when you make 500 plays betting each time on the number 17. What differences do you see in the graphs of your winnings on these two occasions?
</li>
<li>
 An astute student noticed that, in our simulation of the game of heads or tails (see Example 1.4), the proportion of times the player is always in the lead is very close to the proportion of times that the player's total winnings end up 0. Work out these probabilities by enumeration of all cases for two tosses and for four tosses, and see if you think that these probabilities are, in fact, the same.
</li>
<li>
 The<i>Labouchere system</i> for roulette is played as follows. Write down a list of numbers, usually 1, 2, 3, 4. Bet the sum of the first and last, 1 + 4 = 5, on
</li>

</sec>
<sec id="1.1_contd">
<target target-type="page" id="page_14">14</target>
<li>
red. If you win, delete the first and last numbers from your list. If you lose, add the amount that you last bet to the end of your list. Then use the new list and bet the sum of the first and last numbers (if there is only one number, bet that amount). Continue until your list becomes empty. Show that, if this happens, you win the sum, 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 = 10, of your original list. Simulate this system and see if you do always stop and, hence, always win. If so, why is this not a foolproof gambling system?
</li>
<li>
 Another well-known gambling system is the<i>martingale doubling system</i>. Suppose that you are betting on red to turn up in roulette. Every time you win, bet 1 dollar next time. Every time you lose, double your previous bet. Suppose that you use this system until you have won at least 5 dollars or you have lost more than 100 dollars. Write a program to simulate this and play it a number of times and see how you do. In his book<i>The Newcomes</i>, W. M. Thackeray remarks "You have not played as yet? Do not do so; above all avoid a martingale if you do."<sup>10</sup> Was this good advice?
</li>
<li>
 Modify the program<i>HTSimulation</i> so that it keeps track of the maximum of Peter's winnings in each game of 40 tosses. Have your program print out the proportion of times that your total winnings take on values 0, 2, 4, ., 40. Calculate the corresponding exact probabilities for games of two tosses and four tosses.
</li>
<li>
 In an upcoming national election for the President of the United States, a pollster plans to predict the winner of the popular vote by taking a random sample of 1000 voters and declaring that the winner will be the one obtaining the most votes in his sample. Suppose that 48 percent of the voters plan to vote for the Republican candidate and 52 percent plan to vote for the Democratic candidate. To get some idea of how reasonable the pollster's plan is, write a program to make this prediction by simulation. Repeat the simulation 100 times and see how many times the pollster's prediction would come true. Repeat your experiment, assuming now that 49 percent of the population plan to vote for the Republican candidate; first with a sample of 1000 and then with a sample of 3000. (The Gallup Poll uses about 3000.) (This idea is discussed further in Chapter 9, Section 9.1.)
</li>
<li>
<emphasis role="bold">13</i> The psychologist Tversky and his colleagues say that about four out of five people will answer (a) to the following question:
</li>
<li>
A certain town is served by two hospitals. In the larger hospital about 45 babies are born each day, and in the smaller hospital 15 babies are born each day. Although the overall proportion of boys is about 50 percent, the actual proportion at either hospital may be more or less than 50 percent on any day.
</li>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thackeray</surname>
<given-names>W. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>The Newcomes</source>
<publisher-name>Bradbury and Evans</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<year>1854-55</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>

<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="article">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKean</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Decisions, Decisions, Decisions</article-title>
<source>Discover</source>
<date-in-citation>June 1985</date-in-citation>
<comment>pp. 22-31</comment>
</element-citation>

<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKean</surname>
<given-names>Kevin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Discover Magazine</source>
<year>1987</year>
<comment>c1987 Family Media, Inc. Reprinted with permission</comment>
</element-citation>

<element-citation publication-type="book">
<source>Judgment Under Uncertainty: Heuristics and Biases</source>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
<year>1982</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>

</ref-list>

<sec id="1.1_contd2">

<label>1.1</label>
<title>SIMULATION OF DISCRETE PROBABILITIES</title>

<target target-type="page" id="page_15">15</target>

<li>
At the end of a year, which hospital will have the greater number of days on which more than 60 percent of the babies born were boys?
</li>
<li>(a) the large hospital</li>
<li>(b) the small hospital</li>
<li>(c) neither-the number of days will be about the same.</li>
<li>
Assume that the probability that a baby is a boy is .5 (actual estimates make this more like .513). Decide, by simulation, what the right answer is to the question. Can you suggest why so many people go wrong?
</li>
<li>
<emphasis role="bold">14</i> You are offered the following game. A fair coin will be tossed until the first time it comes up heads. If this occurs on the jth toss you are paid 2<sup>j</sup> dollars. You are sure to win at least 2 dollars so you should be willing to pay to play this game-but how much? Few people would pay as much as 10 dollars to play this game. See if you can decide, by simulation, a reasonable amount that you would be willing to pay, per game, if you will be allowed to make a large number of plays of the game. Does the amount that you would be willing to pay per game depend upon the number of plays that you will be allowed?
</li>
<li>
<emphasis role="bold">15</i> Tversky and his colleagues<sup>12</sup> studied the records of 48 of the Philadelphia 76ers basketball games in the 1980-81 season to see if a player had times when he was hot and every shot went in, and other times when he was cold and barely able to hit the backboard. The players estimated that they were about 25 percent more likely to make a shot after a hit than after a miss. In fact, the opposite was true-the 76ers were 6 percent more likely to score after a miss than after a hit. Tversky reports that the number of hot and cold streaks was about what one would expect by purely random effects. Assuming that a player has a fifty-fifty chance of making a shot and makes 20 shots a game, estimate by simulation the proportion of games in which the player will have a streak of 5 or more hits.
</li>
<li>
<emphasis role="bold">16</i> Estimate, by simulation, the average number of children there would be in a family if all people had children until they had a boy. Do the same if all people had children until they had at least one boy and at least one girl. How many more children would you expect to find under the second scheme than under the first in 100,000 families? (Assume that boys and girls are equally likely.)
</li>
<li>
<emphasis role="bold">17</i> Mathematicians have been known to get some of the best ideas while sitting in a café, riding on a bus, or strolling in the park. In the early 1900s the famous mathematician George Pólya lived in a hotel near the woods in Zurich. He liked to walk in the woods and think about mathematics. Pólya describes the following incident:
</li>
</sec>

<ref-list>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation>
<comment>Ibid.</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="1.1_fig">
<target target-type="page" id="page_16">16</target>
<label>CHAPTER 1</label>
<title>DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<fig id="fig1_6">
<graphic xlink:href="fig1_6a.jpg"/>
<caption>
<p>(a) Random walk in one dimension.</li>
</caption>

<graphic xlink:href="fig1_6b.jpg"/>
<caption>
<p>(b) Random walk in two dimensions.</li>
</caption>

<graphic xlink:href="fig1_6c.jpg"/>
<caption>
<p>(c) Random walk in three dimensions.</li>
</caption>

<caption>
<title>Figure 1.6: Random walk.</title>
</caption>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="1.1_contd3">
<label>1.1</label>
<title>SIMULATION OF DISCRETE PROBABILITIES</title>
<target target-type="page" id="page_17">17</target>
<li>
At the hotel there lived also some students with whom I usually took my meals and had friendly relations. On a certain day one of them expected the visit of his fiancée, what (sic) I knew, but I did not foresee that he and his fiancée would also set out for a stroll in the woods, and then suddenly I met them there. And then I met them the same morning repeatedly, I don't remember how many times, but certainly much too often and I felt embarrassed: It looked as if I was snooping around which was, I assure you, not the case.<sup>13</sup>
</li>
<li>
This set him to thinking about whether random walkers were destined to meet.
</li>
<li>
Pólya considered random walkers in one, two and three dimensions. In one dimension, he envisioned the walker on a very long street. At each intersection the walker flips a fair coin to decide which direction to walk next (see Figure 1.6a). In two dimensions, the walker is walking on a grid of streets, and at each intersection he chooses one of the four possible directions with equal probability (see Figure 1.6b). In three dimensions (we might better speak of a random climber), the walker moves on a three-dimensional grid, and at each intersection there are now six different directions that the walker may choose, each with equal probability (see Figure 1.6c).
</li>
<li>
The reader is referred to Section 12.1, where this and related problems are discussed.
</li>
<li>
(a) Write a program to simulate a random walk in one dimension starting at 0. Have your program print out the lengths of the times between returns to the starting point (returns to 0). See if you can guess from this simulation the answer to the following question: Will the walker always return to his starting point eventually or might he drift away forever?
</li>
<li>
(b) The paths of two walkers in two dimensions who meet after n steps can be considered to be a single path that starts at (0,0) and returns to (0,0) after 2n steps. This means that the probability that two random walkers in two dimensions meet is the same as the probability that a single walker in two dimensions ever returns to the starting point. Thus the question of whether two walkers are sure to meet is the same as the question of whether a single walker is sure to return to the starting point. Write a program to simulate a random walk in two dimensions and see if you think that the walker is sure to return to (0,0). If so, Pólya would be sure to keep meeting his friends in the park. Perhaps by now you have conjectured the answer to the question: Is a random walker in one or two dimensions sure to return to the starting point? Pólya answered this question in 1921.
</li>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pólya</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Two Incidents</source>
<comment>Scientists at Work: Festschrift in Honour of Herman Wold, ed. T. Dalenius, G. Karlsson, and S. Malmquist (Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells Boktryckeri AB, 1970).</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="1.2">
<target target-type="page" id="page_18">18</target>
<label>CHAPTER 1</label>
<title>DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<li>
this question for dimensions one, two, and three. He established the remarkable result that the answer is yes in one and two dimensions and no in three dimensions.
</li>
<li>
(c) Write a program to simulate a random walk in three dimensions and see whether, from this simulation and the results of (a) and (b), you could have guessed Pólya's result.
</li>
</sec>
</ol>
<sec id="1.2_main">
<label>1.2</label>
<title>Discrete Probability Distributions</title>

<p role="indent">
In this book we shall study many different experiments from a probabilistic point of view. What is involved in this study will become evident as the theory is developed and examples are analyzed. However, the overall idea can be described and illustrated as follows: to each experiment that we consider there will be associated a random variable, which represents the outcome of any particular experiment. The set of possible outcomes is called the sample space. In the first part of this section, we will consider the case where the experiment has only finitely many possible outcomes, i.e., the sample space is finite. We will then generalize to the case that the sample space is either finite or countably infinite. This leads us to the following definition.
</p>

<sec id="random_variables">
<title>Random Variables and Sample Spaces</title>

<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Definition 1.1</emphasis> Suppose we have an experiment whose outcome depends on chance. We represent the outcome of the experiment by a capital Roman letter, such as X, called a random variable. The sample space of the experiment is the set of all possible outcomes. If the sample space is either finite or countably infinite, the random variable is said to be discrete.
</p>

<p role="indent">
We generally denote a sample space by the capital Greek letter Ω. As stated above, in the correspondence between an experiment and the mathematical theory by which it is studied, the sample space Ω corresponds to the set of possible outcomes of the experiment.
</p>

<p role="indent">
We now make two additional definitions. These are subsidiary to the definition of sample space and serve to make precise some of the common terminology used in conjunction with sample spaces. First of all, we define the elements of a sample space to be outcomes. Second, each subset of a sample space is defined to be an event. Normally, we shall denote outcomes by lower case letters and events by capital letters.
</p>

<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Example 1.6</emphasis> A die is rolled once. We let X denote the outcome of this experiment. Then the sample space for this experiment is the 6-element set
</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>&#937;</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>3</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>4</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>6</mn>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="1.2_contd">
<label>1.2</label>
<title>DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<target target-type="page" id="page_19">19</target>
<p role="indent">
where each outcome i, for i = 1, ., 6, corresponds to the number of dots on the face which turns up. The event
</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>E</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
corresponds to the statement that the result of the roll is an even number. The event E can also be described by saying that X is even. Unless there is reason to believe the die is loaded, the natural assumption is that every outcome is equally likely. Adopting this convention means that we assign a probability of 1/6 to each of the six outcomes, i.e.,
</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>&#8804;</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>&#8804;</mo><mn>6</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
Distribution Functions
</p>
<p role="indent">We next describe the assignment of probabilities. The definitions are motivated by the example above, in which we assigned to each outcome of the sample space a nonnegative number such that the sum of the numbers assigned is equal to 1.</p>
<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Definition 1.2</emphasis> Let X be a random variable which denotes the value of the outcome of a certain experiment, and assume that this experiment has only finitely many possible outcomes. Let Ω be the sample space of the experiment (i.e., the set of all possible values of X, or equivalently, the set of all possible outcomes of the experiment). A distribution function for X is a real-valued function m whose domain is Ω and which satisfies:</p>
<p role="indent">1. 
<inline-formula>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#8805;</mo>
<mn>0</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
</inline-formula>
, for all ? ? Ω, and
</p>
<p role="indent">2. 
<math>
<mrow>
<mo>&#8721;</mo>
<mrow><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>&#937;</mi></mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
</p>
<p role="indent">For any subset E of Ω, we define the probability of E to be the number P(E) given by</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>E</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>&#8721;</mo>
<mrow><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>E</mi></mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Example 1.7</emphasis> Consider an experiment in which a coin is tossed twice. Let X be the random variable which corresponds to this experiment. We note that there are several ways to record the outcomes of this experiment. We could, for example, record the two tosses, in the order in which they occurred. In this case, we have Ω = {HH, HT, TH, TT}. We could also record the outcomes by simply noting the number of heads that appeared. In this case, we have Ω = {0,1,2}. Finally, we could record the two outcomes, without regard to the order in which they occurred. In this case, we have Ω = {HH, HT, TT}.
</p>
<p role="indent">We will use, for the moment, the first of the sample spaces given above. We will assume that all four outcomes are equally likely, and define the distribution function m(?) by
</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>HH</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>HT</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>TH</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>TT</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
</sec>
<sec id="1.2_contd2">
<label>CHAPTER 1</label>
<title>DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<target target-type="page" id="page_20">20</target>
<p role="indent">Let be the event that at least one head comes up. Then, the probability of E can be calculated as follows:
</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>E</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>HH</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>HT</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>TH</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<math>
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent"> Similarly, if the event that heads comes up on the first toss, then we have</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>F</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>HH</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>HT</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<math>
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Example 1.8</emphasis> (Example 1.6 continued) The sample space for the experiment in which the die is rolled is the 6-element set Ω = {1,2,3,4,5,6}. We assumed that the die was fair, and we chose the distribution function defined by
</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mtext> for</mtext>
<mi>i</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mo>&#8230;</mo><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent"> If E is the event that the result of the roll is an even number, then E = {2,4,6} and</p>


<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>E</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<math>
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Notice that it is an immediate consequence of the above definitions that, for every ? ? Ω,</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>{</mo><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>}</mo><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>&#969;</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>


<p role="indent">That is, the probability of the elementary event {?}, consisting of a single outcome ?, is equal to the value m(?) assigned to the outcome ? by the distribution function.
</p>

<p role="indent">
<emphasis role="bold">Example 1.9</emphasis> Three people, A, B, and C, are running for the same office, and we assume that one and only one of them wins. The sample space may be taken as the 3-element set Ω = {A,B,C} where each element corresponds to the outcome of that candidate's winning. Suppose that A and B have the same chance of winning, but that C has only 1/2 the chance of A or B. Then we assign
</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>

</sec>
<sec id="1.2_contd3">
<label>1.2</label>
<title>DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<target target-type="page" id="page_21">21</target>
<p role="indent">we see that</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mn>2</mn><mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">which implies that 5m(C) = 1. Hence,</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Let E be the event that either A or C wins. </p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>E</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>m</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>C</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">In many cases, events can be described in terms of other events through the use of the standard constructions of set theory. We will briefly review the definitions of these constructions. The reader is referred to Figure 1.7 for Venn diagrams which illustrate these constructions.
</p>

<p role="indent">Let A and B be two sets. Then the union of A and B is the set</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>A</mi><mo>&#8746;</mo><mi>B</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>A</mi>
<mo>or</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>B</mi>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The intersection of A and B is the set</p>
<math>
<mrow>
<mi>A</mi><mo>&#8745;</mo><mi>B</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>A</mi>
<mo>and</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>B</mi>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">The difference of A and B is the set</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mi>A</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mi>B</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>A</mi>
<mo>and</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8713;</mo><mi>B</mi>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">The set A is a subset of B, written A ? B, if every element of A is also an element of B. Finally, the complement of A is the set</p>

<math>
<mrow>
<mover><mi>A</mi><mo>_</mo></mover>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>{</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8712;</mo><mi>&#937;</mi>
<mo>and</mo>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#8713;</mo><mi>A</mi>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">
The reason that these constructions are important is that it is typically the case that complicated events described in English can be broken down into simpler events using these constructions. For example, if A is the event that "it will snow tomorrow and it will rain the next day," B is the event that "it will snow tomorrow," and C is the event that "it will rain two days from now," then A is the intersection of the events B and C. Similarly, if D is the event that "it will snow tomorrow or it will rain the next day," then D = B ? C. (Note that we use the word "or" in English means that exactly one of the two alternatives will occur. The meaning is usually clear from context. In this book, we will always use the word "or" in the inclusive sense, i.e., A or B means that at least one of the two events A, B is true.) The event B─ is the event that "it will not snow tomorrow." Finally, if E is the event that "it will snow tomorrow but it will not rain the next day," then E = B - C.
</p>
</sec>

<target target-type="pages" id="page_22">22</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p22">
<title>CHAPTER&#x00A0;1. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<fig id="fig-1-2">
<label>Figure&#x00A0;1.2</label>
<caption><p>Basic set operations.</p></caption>
<graphic href="figure_1_2_basic_set_operations.png"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec-properties">
<title>Properties</title>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Theorem&#x00A0;1.1</bold><i>The probabilities assigned to events by a distribution
function on a sample space</i> &#x03A9;<i>satisfy the following properties:</i>
</p>
<table-wrap id="tbl-properties">
<table>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>1.</entry>
<entry>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
for every<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2.</entry>
<entry>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>3.</entry>
<entry>
If<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, then
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4.</entry>
<entry>
If<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> and<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> are disjoint subsets of &#x03A9;, then
<disp-formula id="eq-disjoint-union">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>5.</entry>
<entry>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
for every<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Proof.</bold> For any event<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> the probability<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is determined from the distribution as
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-sum-omega">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
for every<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Since the function<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> is nonnegative, it follows that<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is also nonnegative. This proves Property&#x00A0;1 is true.
</p>
<p role="indent">Property&#x00A0;2 is proved by the equation:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-omega-1">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
Suppose that<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Then every element that belongs to<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> also belongs to<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Therefore,
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-subset-sum">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">since each term in the left-hand sum is in the right-hand sum, and all the terms in both sums are non-negative. This implies that
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-subset">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">and Property&#x00A0;3 is proved. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_23">23</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p23">
<title>1.2. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<p role="indent">Suppose next that<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> and<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> are disjoint subsets of &#x03A9;. Then every element
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> of
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is either in<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> and not in<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula>, or in<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> and not in<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula>. It follows that
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-disjoint-sum">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">and Property&#x00A0;4 is proved.</p>
<p role="indent">Finally, to prove Property&#x00A0;5, consider the disjoint union:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-omega-disjoint">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
Since<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the property of disjoint additivity (Property&#x00A0;4) implies that
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-complement-sum">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">whence</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-complement">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Theorem&#x00A0;1.2</bold><i>If</i><inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>are pairwise disjoint subsets of</i> &#x03A9;<i>(i.e., no two of the</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>&#x2019;s have an element in common), then</i>
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-finite-additivity">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Proof.</bold> Let<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> be any element in the union. Then
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> occurs exactly once on each side of the equality in the statement of the theorem. &#x25A1;
</p>
<p role="indent">We shall often use the following theorem:</p>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Theorem&#x00A0;1.3</bold><i>Let</i><inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>be pairwise disjoint events with</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>,<i>and let</i><inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>be any event. Then</i>
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-total-probability">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Proof.</bold> The sets
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> are pairwise disjoint, and their union is<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The result now follows from Theorem&#x00A0;1.2. &#x25A1;
</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_24">24</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p24">
<title>CHAPTER&#x00A0;1. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>

<p role="indent">
<bold>Corollary&#x00A0;1.1</bold><i>For any two events</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>and</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula>,
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-corollary-1-1">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Theorem&#x00A0;1.2</bold><i>If</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>and</i>
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula><i>are any subsets of</i> &#x03A9;,<i>then</i>
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-theorem-1-2-inclusion-exclusion">
<label>(1.1)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<sec id="sec-tree-diagrams">
<title>Tree Diagrams</title>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Example&#x00A0;1.40</bold> Let us illustrate the properties of probabilities of events
in terms of three tosses of a coin&#x2026;
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-E-toss">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>TTT</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">By Property&#x00A0;5 of Theorem&#x00A0;1.1:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-E-complement">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_25">25</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p25">
<title>1.2. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<fig id="fig-1-9">
<label>Figure&#x00A0;1.9</label>
<caption><p>Tree diagram for three tosses of a coin.</p></caption>
<graphic href="figure_1_9_tree_diagram_coin_tosses.png"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl-tree-outcomes">
<caption><p>Outcomes for three tosses of a coin</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>First toss</entry>
<entry>Second toss</entry>
<entry>Third toss</entry>
<entry>Outcome</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry morerows="3">H</entry>
<entry morerows="1">H</entry>
<entry>H</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>T</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry morerows="1">T</entry>
<entry>H</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>T</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry morerows="3">T</entry>
<entry morerows="1">H</entry>
<entry>H</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>T</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry morerows="1">T</entry>
<entry>H</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>T</entry>
<entry><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-AuB-tree">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x222A;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2229;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<sec id="sec-uniform-distribution">
<title>Uniform Distribution</title>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Definition&#x00A0;1.3</bold> The<i>uniform distribution</i> on a sample space &#x03A9;
containing<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> elements is the function<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> defined by
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-uniform-dist">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">for every<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_26">26</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p26">
<title>CHAPTER&#x00A0;1. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<disp-formula id="eq-m-three-element">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2em"/>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2em"/>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Example&#x00A0;1.11</bold> Consider the experiment that consists of rolling a pair of dice.
We take as the sample space &#x03A9; the set of all ordered pairs
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> of integers with
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>:
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-dice-uniform">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-E-dice">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>33</mml:mn><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>11</mml:mn><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<sec id="sec-determination-of-probs">
<title>Determination of Probabilities</title>
<p role="indent">It is important to consider ways in which probability distributions are determinedin practice. One way is by<i>symmetry</i>&#x2026; In general, considerations of symmetryoften suggest the<i>uniform distribution function</i>. Care must be used here&#x2026;Another way that probabilities can be determined is by<i>past observation</i>.
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec-odds">
<title>Odds</title>
<p role="indent">Statistical relatives for probabilities are that if the experiment under considerationcan be repeated a number of times&#x2026;
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_27">27</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p27">
<title>1.2. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-A-odds">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-Acomp-odds">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x7E;</mml:mo></mml:mover>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Definition&#x00A0;1.3</bold> If<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the<i>odds</i> in favor of the event
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> occurring are given by the equation
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-odds-def">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_28">28</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p28">
<title>CHAPTER&#x00A0;1. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<sec id="sec-infinite-sample-spaces">
<title>Infinite Sample Spaces</title>
<p role="indent">If a sample space has an infinite number of points, then the way that a distributionfunction is defined depends upon the nature of the sample space. A sample space is
<i>countably infinite</i> if the elements can be counted, i.e., can be put in one-to-onecorrespondence with the positive integers, and<i>uncountably infinite</i> otherwise.</p>
<p role="indent">
<bold>Example&#x00A0;1.13</bold> A coin is tossed until the first time that a head turns up. Thenthe possible outcomes of our experiment are:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-coin-until-head">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03A9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq-geometric-sum">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>&#x221E;</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>&#x221E;</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">That this is true follows from the formula for the sum of a geometric series:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-geometric-series">
<label>(1.2)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
for<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Putting<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> in Equation&#x00A0;1.2:
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-sum-from-1">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>&#x221E;</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">
Let<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math>
</inline-formula> be the event that the first head turns up after an even number of tosses. Then
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-E-even-tosses">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>&#x2026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq-prob-E-even-result">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">Thus the probability that a head turns up for the first time after an even numberof tosses and after an odd number of tosses is 2/3.
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<ref-list id="references">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref-hacking1975">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
I.&#x00A0;Hacking,<i>The Emergence of Probability</i>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975).
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
O.&#x00A0;Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953).
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953-p150">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
O.&#x00A0;Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i>
(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953), p.&#x00A0;150.
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953-p189">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
Ibid., p.&#x00A0;189.
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_30">30</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p30">
<title>CHAPTER 1. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<sec id="sec-historical-remarks">
<title>Historical Remarks</title>
<p role="indent">An interesting question in the history of science is: Why was probability not developeduntil the sixteenth century? We know that in the sixteenth century problemsin gambling and games of chance made people start to think about probability. Butgambling and games of chance are very old. Gambling was common in ancientEgypt (in the time of the First Dynasty, ca. 3500 BC) a game now called &#x201C;Houndsand Jackals&#x201D; was played. In this game the movement of the hounds and jackals wasbased on the outcome of the roll of four-sided dice made out of animal bones called<i>astragali</i>. Recorded dice made of a variety of materials date from the sixteenthcentury BC. Gambling was widespread in ancient Greece and Rome. Indeed, in theRoman Empire it was sometimes found necessary to invoke laws against gambling.Why, then, were probabilities not calculated until the sixteenth century?</p>
<p role="indent">Several explanations have been advanced for this late development. One is thatthe relevant mathematics was not developed and was not easy to develop. Theancient mathematical notation was not well suited to such calculations and otherfamiliar algebraic notation was not developed until the sixteenth century. However,we could say many of the necessary computations were within reach of ancientmathematicians. Another explanation is that ancient peoples attributed the outcomesof these times had to do with invoices relating to religious affairs. It has beensuggested that there may have been religious obstacles to the analysis of games ofgambling. Another suggestion is that a stronger incentive, such as the developmentof commerce, was necessary. However, none of these explanations seems completelysatisfactory, and people still wonder why it took so long for probability to be studiedseriously. An interesting discussion of this problem can be found in Hacking.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
<p role="indent">The first person to calculate probabilities systematically was Gerolamo Cardano(1501&#x2013;1576) in his book<i>Liber de Ludo Aleae</i>. This book was written in about 1525by Gerol and appears in the book<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i> by Ore.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref>Oreprovides a fascinating discussion of the life of this curious scholar and his resultsof his interests in many different fields, including medicine, astrology, and mathematics.You will also find there a translation of<i>Liber de Ludo Aleae</i> (The Book onGames of Chance) by Sydney Henry Gould.</p>
<p role="indent">In his book on probability Cardano dealt only with the special case that we havebeen studying: the case of equally likely outcomes. He assumed that the game wasto continue for a long time. In this case Cardano realized that the probability ofa particular outcome is the ratio of the number of favorable outcomes to the totalnumber of outcomes.</p>
<p role="indent">Many of Cardano&#x2019;s examples dealt with rolling dice. Here he realized that theoutcomes for two rolls should be taken to be the 36 ordered pairs
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>rather than the 21 unordered pairs. This is a key point that has still confused mathematicianslater for other writers on probability. For example, in the eighteenth century thefamous French mathematician<i>d&#x2019;Alembert</i> made the same mistake on probability. Heclaimed that when a coin is tossed twice the number of heads that result is one of</p>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1">
<label>1</label>
<p>I. Hacking,<i>The Emergence of Probability</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn2">
<label>2</label>
<p>O. Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="pages" id="page_31">31</target>
<sec id="sec-ch1-p31">
<title>1.2. DISCRETE PROBABILITY DISTRIBUTIONS</title>
<p role="indent">be 0, 1, or 2, and hence we should assign equal probabilities for these three possibleoutcomes.
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>3</sup></xref>Cardano chose the correct sample space to fit the experiment andcalculated the correct probabilities for a variety of events.
</p>
<p role="indent">Cardano&#x2019;s mathematical analyses of gambling were given as advice to the potentialgambler in short paragraphs, entitled, for example, &#x201C;Who Should Play and When,&#x201D;&#x201C;Why Gambling Was Thought to be Unlawful,&#x201D; &#x201C;On Those Who Gamble as a BusinessWell&#x201D; and so forth. In a paragraph entitled &#x201C;The Fundamental Principle of Gambling,&#x201D;Cardano states:</p>
<p role="indent">The most fundamental principle of all in gambling is simply equal con&#x2011;ditions, e.g., of opponents, of bystanders, of money, of situation, of thedice box, and of the die itself. To the extent to which you depart fromthat equality, if it is in your opponent&#x2019;s favor, you are a fool, and if inyour own, you are unjust.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>4</sup></xref></p>
<p role="indent">Cardano did make mistakes, and if he realized it later he did not go back andchange his work. For example, in a problem that he proposed, he considered threepossible outcomes of an experiment with three possible outcomes, and to each heassigned odds by equating their numbers (0 : 1 : 3) for the event to happen twice ina row of
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>36</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>turns and used this to claim that the probability that an eventwith probability
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
occurs is
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>if it occurs for the first time in the round of outcomes.The correct formula for the probability that an event with probability
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
occurs at least once in
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>independent repetitions of an experiment. This willfollow from the multiplication law to be introduced in Chapter 4.</p>
<p role="indent">Cardano&#x2019;s work was a remarkable first attempt at writing down the laws ofprobability, but it was not published until 1663, more than 100 years after it was written.This came from a famous series of letters between Pascal and Fermat. This correspondence,the derivation of which is discussed in Chapter 7 of this book, tookplace in 1654 in the reign of Louis XIV, and an edited gambler.</p>
<p role="indent">Cardano proceeded to establish that for those outcomes the formula should be
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
to
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
successes in
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>independent repetitions of an experiment. This willfollow from the multiplication law to be introduced in Chapter 4.
</p>
<p role="indent">It is pointed out that it is equivalent by the realization that if the probability thatan event occurs in one repetition of an experiment is
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>,
then Cardano proceeded to claim that for these successes the formula should be
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
for the probability. Cardano found that a gambling at least one of the time suggested that,for a favorable outcome, you should offer on
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
repetitions, where
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
The probability of a favorable outcome in
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
repetitions is
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.
The probability of a successful outcome in a game of chance, by the repetition givesthe ratio of outcomes that belong to the event to the total. The probability of agambling result is
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>,
and the appropriate number of rolls (
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>)
for getting at least one six is
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. The probability of getting at least one six in
<inline-formula>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
rolls is:
</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-cardano-six">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0.665</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="indent">On his return Cardano noted at least one of his &#x201C;on odds&#x201D; at the time suggested that,for a favorable outcome, you should offer on at least XII, and an edited gambler.Ore&#x2019;s claims show that a gambling at least one of the time suggested that, for afavorable outcome, you should offer on at least XII.</p>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn3">
<label>3</label>
<p>See O. Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953), p. 150.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn4">
<label>4</label>
<p>Ibid., p. 189.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</sec>
<ref-list id="references">
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref-hacking1975">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">I. Hacking,<i>The Emergence of Probability</i>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975).
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">O. Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953).
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953b">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">O. Ore,<i>Cardano: The Gambling Scholar</i>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953), p.&#x00A0;150.
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="ref-ore1953c">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book">
Ibid., p.&#x00A0;189.
</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<target type="page" id="40">40</target>
a favorable bet. Pascal showed, by exact calculation, that 25 rolls are required for a favorable bet for a pair of sixes.</p>
<p role="indent">The second problem was a much harder one: it was an old problem and concerned the determination of a fair division of the stakes in a tournament when the series, for some reason, is interrupted before it is completed. This problem is now referred to as the problem of points. The problem had been a standard problem inmathematical texts; it appeared in Fra Luca Paccioli's book summa de Arithmetica,Geometria, Proportioni et Proportionalit`a, printed in Venice in 1494,19 in the form:</p>
<p role="indent">A team plays ball such that a total of 60 points are required to win the game, and each inning counts 10 points. The stakes are 10 ducats. By some incident they cannot finish the game and one side has 50 points and the other 20. One wants to know what share of the prize money belongs to each side. In this case I have found that opinions differ from one to another but all seem to me insufficient in their arguments, but I shall state the truth and give the correct way.</p>
<p role="indent">Reasonable solutions, such as dividing the stakes according to the ratio of games won by each player, had been proposed, but no correct solution had been found at the time of the Pascal-Fermat correspondence. The letters deal mainly with the attempts of Pascal and Fermat to solve this problem. Blaise Pascal (1623-1662 was a child prodigy, having published his treatise on conic sections at age sixteen, and having invented a calculating machine at age eighteen. At the time of the letters, his demonstration of the weight of the atmosphere had already established his position at the forefront of contemporary physicists. Pierre de Fermat (1601- 1665) was a learned jurist in Toulouse, who studied mathematics in his spare time. He has been called by some the prince of amateurs and one of the greatest pure mathematicians of all times.</p>
<p role="indent">The letters, translated by Maxine Merrington, appear in Florence David's fascinating historical account of probability, Games, Gods and Gambling.20 In a letter dated Wednesday, 29th July, 1654, Pascal writes to Fermat:</p>
<p role="indent">Sir, Like you, I am equally impatient, and although I am again ill in bed, I cannot help telling you that yesterday evening I received from M. de Carcavi your letter on the problem of points, which I admire more than I can possibly say. I have not the leisure to write at length, but, in a word, you have solved the two problems of points, one with dice and the other with sets of games with perfect justness; I am entirely satisfied with it for I do not doubt that I was in the wrong, seeing the admirableagreement in which I find myself with you now. . .</p>
<p role="indent">Your method is very sound and is the one which first came to my mind in this research; but because the labour of the combination is excessive, I have found a short cut and indeed another method which is much
<target type="page" id="41">41</target>
<fig id="fig_1.9">
<label>Figure 1.9</label>
<caption>Pascal's table..</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure1.9.jpg"/>
</fig>
quicker and neater, which I would like to tell you here in a few words:for henceforth I would like to open my heart to you, if I may, as I am sooverjoyed with our agreement. I see that truth is the same in Toulouseas in Paris.</p>
<p role="indent">Here, more or less, is what I do to show the fair value of each game,when two opponents play, for example, in three games and each personhas staked 32 pistoles.</p>
<p role="indent">Let us say that the first man had won twice and the other once; nowthey play another game, in which the conditions are that, if the firstwins, he takes all the stakes; that is 64 pistoles; if the other wins it,then they have each won two games, and therefore, if they wish to stopplaying, they must each take back their own stake, that is, 32 pistoleseach.</p>
<p role="indent">Then consider, Sir, if the first man wins, he gets 64 pistoles; if he loseshe gets 32. Thus if they do not wish to risk this last game but wish toseparate without playing it, the first man must say: `I am certain to get32 pistoles, even if I lost I still get them; but as for the other 32, perhapsI will get them, perhaps you will get them, the chances are equal. Letus then divide these 32 pistoles in half and give one half to me as wellas my 32 which are mine for sure.' He will then have 48 pistoles and theother 16. . .</p>
<p role="indent">Pascal's argument produces the table illustrated in Figure 1.9 for the amountdue player A at any quitting point.</p>
<p role="indent">Each entry in the table is the average of the numbers just above and to the rightof the number. This fact, together with the known values when the tournament iscompleted, determines all the values in this table. If player A wins the first game,
<target type="page" id="42">42</target>
then he needs two games to win and B needs three games to win; and so, if thetounament is called off, A should receive 44 pistoles.</p>
<p role="indent">The letter in which Fermat presented his solution has been lost; but fortunately,Pascal describes Fermat's method in a letter dated Monday, 24th August, 1654.From Pascal's letter:21</p>
<p role="indent">This is your procedure when there are two players: If two players, playingseveral games, find themselves in that position when the first manneeds two games and second needs three, then to find the fair divisionof stakes, you say that one must know in how many games the play willbe absolutely decided.</p>
<p role="indent">It is easy to calculate that this will be in four games, from which you canconclude that it is necessary to see in how many ways four games can bearranged between two players, and one must see how many combinationswould make the first man win and how many the second and to shareout the stakes in this proportion. I would have found it difficult tounderstand this if I had not known it myself already; in fact you hadexplained it with this idea in mind.</p>
<p role="indent">Fermat realized that the number of ways that the game might be finished maynot be equally likely. For example, if A needs two more games and B needs three towin, two possible ways that the tournament might go for A to win are WLW andLWLW. These two sequences do not have the same chance of occurring. To avoidthis difficulty, Fermat extended the play, adding fictitious plays, so that all the waysthat the games might go have the same length, namely four. He was shrewd enoughto realize that this extension would not change the winner and that he now couldsimply count the number of sequences favorable to each player since he had madethem all equally likely. If we list all possible ways that the extended game of fourplays might go, we obtain the following 16 possible outcomes of theplay:</p>
<p role="indent">Player A wins in the cases where there are at least two wins (the 11 underlinedcases), and B wins in the cases where there are at least three losses (the other5 cases). Since A wins in 11 of the 16 possible cases Fermat argued that theprobability that A wins is 11/16. If the stakes are 64 pistoles, A should receive44 pistoles in agreement with Pascal's result. Pascal and Fermat developed moresystematic methods for counting the number of favorable outcomes for problemslike this, and this will be one of our central problems. Such counting methods fallunder the subject of combinatorics, which is the topic of Chapter 3.</p>
<target type="page" id="43">43</target>
<p role="indent">We see that these two mathematicians arrived at two very different ways to solvethe problem of points. Pascal's method was to develop an algorithm and use it tocalculate the fair division. This method is easy to implement on a computer and easyto generalize. Fermat's method, on the other hand, was to change the problem intoan equivalent problem for which he could use counting or combinatorial methods.We will see in Chapter 3 that, in fact, Fermat used what has become known asPascal's triangle! In our study of probability today we shall find that both thealgorithmic approach and the combinatorial approach share equal billing, just asthey did 300 years ago when probability got its start.</p>
<sec sec_id="Exercises">
<title>Exercises</title>
<list type="1">
<ol>
<li>Let<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03A9;</mi><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x007B;</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>c</mi><mo>&#x007D;</mo></mrow>
</math> be a sample space.Let<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mrow>
<mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>m</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>b</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>3</mn></mrow>
</mrow></mrow>
<mo>,</mo><mi>m</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>c</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>6</mn></mrow>
</mrow>
</math>Find the probabilities for all eight subsets of<math display='block'>
<mi>&#x03A9;</mi>
</math></li>
<li>Give a possible sample space<math display='block'>
<mi>&#x03A9;</mi>
</math> for each of the following experiments:</li>
<li>(a) An election decides between two candidates A and B.</li>
<li>(b) A two-sided coin is tossed.</li>
<li>(c) A student is asked for the month of the year and the day of the week on which her birthday falls.</li>
<li>(d) A student is chosen at random from a class of ten students.</li>
<li>(e) You receive a grade in this course.</li>
<li>For which of the cases in Exercise 2 would it be reasonable to assign the uniform distribution function?</li>
<li>4 Describe in words the events specified by the following subsets of</li> 
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03A9;</mi><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x007B;</mo><mi>H</mi><mi>H</mi><mi>H</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>H</mi><mi>H</mi><mi>T</mi><mo>,</mo><mtext>HTH,&#x00A0;HTT,&#x00A0;THH,&#x00A0;THT,&#x00A0;TTH,&#x00A0;TTT&#x00A0;&#x007D;</mtext></mrow>
</math>
<li><math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mtext>E&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;&#x007B;HHH,HHT,HTH,HTT&#x007D;</mtext></mrow>
</math></li>
<li><math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mtext>E&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;&#x007B;HHH,TTT&#x007D;</mtext></mrow>
</math></li>
<li><math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mtext>E&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;&#x007B;HHT,HTH,THH&#x007D;</mtext></mrow>
</math></li>
<li><math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mtext>E&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;&#x007B;HHT,HTH,HTT,THH,THT,TTH,TTT&#x007D;</mtext></mrow>
</math></li>
<li> What are the probabilities of the events described in Exercise
4?</li>
<li> A die is loaded in such a way that the probability of each face turning upis proportional to the number of dots on that face. (For example, a six isthree times as probable as a two.) What is the probability of getting an evennumber in one throw?</li>
<target type="page" id="44">44</target>
<li>A student must choose one of the subjects, art, geology, or psychology, as anelective. She is equally likely to choose art or psychology and twice as likelyto choose geology. What are the respective probabilities that she chooses art,geology, and psychology?</li>
<li> A student must choose exactly two out of three electives: art, French, andmathematics. He chooses art with probability 5/8, French with probability5/8, and art and French together with probability 1/4. What is the probabilitythat he chooses mathematics? What is the probability that he chooses eitherart or French?</li><li> For a bill to come before the president of the United States, it must be passedby both the House of Representatives and the Senate. Assume that, of thebills presented to these two bodies, 60 percent pass the House, 80 percentpass the Senate, and 90 percent pass at least one of the two. Calculate theprobability that the next bill presented to the two groups will come before thepresident.</li>
<li>What odds should a person give in favor of the following events?</li>
<li>(a) A card chosen at random from a 52-card deck is an ace.</li>
<li>(b) Two heads will turn up when a coin is tossed twice.</li>
<li>(c) Boxcars (two sixes) will turn up when two dice are rolled.</li>
<li> You offer 3 : 1 odds that your friend Smith will be elected mayor of your city.What probability are you assigning to the event that Smith wins?</li>
<li> In a horse race, the odds that Romance will win are listed as 2 : 3 and thatDownhill will win are 1 : 2. What odds should be given for the event thateither Romance or Downhill wins?</li>
<li> Let X be a random variable with distribution function mX(x) defined by
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<msub>
<mi>m</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mrow>
<mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><msub>
<mi>m</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>/</mo><mrow>
<mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><msub>
<mi>m</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>5</mn></mrow>
</mrow></mrow>
</mrow></mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
</li>
<li>*15 John and Mary are taking a mathematics course. The course has only three grades: A, B, and C. The probability that John gets a B is .3. The probability that Mary gets a B is .4. The probability that neither gets an A but at least one gets a B is .1. What is the probability that at least one gets a B butneither gets a C?</li>
<li>16 In a fierce battle, not less than 70 percent of the soldiers lost one eye, not lessthan 75 percent lost one ear, not less than 80 percent lost one hand, and not
<target type="page" id="45">45</target>less than 85 percent lost one leg. What is the minimal possible percentage ofthose who simultaneously lost one ear, one eye, one hand, and oneleg?</li>
<li>*17 Assume that the probability of a "success" on a single experiment with noutcomes is 1/n. Let m be the number of experiments necessary to make it afavorable bet that at least one success will occur (see Exercise1.1.5).</li>
<li>(a) Show that the probability that, in m trials, there are no successes is(1 - 1/n)m.</li>
<li>(b) (de Moivre) Show that if m = n log 2 then Hence for large n weshould choose m to be about n log 2.</li>
<li>(c) Would DeMoivre have been led to the correct answer for de M'er'e's twobets if he had used his approximation?</li>

<li>20 Explain why it is not possible to define a uniform distribution function (seeDefinition 1.3) on a countably infinite sample space. Hint : Assume m(?) = afor all ?, where 0 = a = 1. Does m(?) have all the properties of a distributionfunction?</li>
<li>21 In Example 1.13 find the probability that the coin turns up heads for the first
time on the tenth, eleventh, or twelfth toss.</li>
<li>22 A die is rolled until the first time that a six turns up. We shall see that theprobability that this occurs on the nth roll is (5/6)n-1 · (1/6). Using this fact,describe the appropriate infinite sample space and distribution function forthe experiment of rolling a die until a six turns up for the first time. Verifythat for your distribution function<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mstyle displaystyle='true'>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo><mrow>
<msub>
<mrow></mrow>
<mi>&#x03C9;</mi>
</msub>
<mo>=</mo></mrow>
</mstyle><mi>m</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C9;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</math></li>
<target type="page" id="46">46</target>
<li>23 Let O be the sample spaceO = {0, 1, 2, . . .} ,and define a distribution function bym(j) = (1 - r)jr ,for some fixed r, 0< r< 1, and for j = 0, 1, 2, . . .. Show that this is adistribution function for O.</li>
<li>24 Our calendar has a 400-year cycle. B. H. Brown noticed that the number oftimes the thirteenth of the month falls on each of the days of the week in the4800 months of a cycle is as follows:
Sunday 687
Monday 685
Tuesday 685
Wednesday 687
Thursday 684
Friday 688
Saturday 684
From this he deduced that the thirteenth was more likely to fall on Fridaythan on any other day. Explain what he meant by this.</li>
<li>25 Tversky and Kahneman23 asked a group of subjects to carry out the followingtask. They are told that:Linda is 31, single, outspoken, and very bright. She majored inphilosophy in college. As a student, she was deeply concerned withracial discrimination and other social issues, and participated inanti-nuclear demonstrations.</li>
<li>The subjects are then asked to rank the likelihood of various alternatives, suchas:</li>
<li>(1) Linda is active in the feminist movement.</li>
<li>(2) Linda is a bank teller.</li>
<li>(3) Linda is a bank teller and active in the feminist movement.</li>
<li>Tversky and Kahneman found that between 85 and 90 percent of the subjectsrated alternative (1) most likely, but alternative (3) more likely than alternative(2). Is it? They call this phenomenon the conjunction fallacy, and notethat it appears to be unaffected by prior training in probability or statistics.Is this phenomenon a fallacy? If so, why? Can you give a possible explanationfor the subjects' choices?</li>
<target type="page" id="47">47</target>
<li>26 Two cards are drawn successively from a deck of 52 cards. Find the probability
that the second card is higher in rank than the first card. Hint : Show that 1 =
P(higher)+P(lower)+P(same) and use the fact that P(higher) = P(lower).</li>
<li>27 A life table is a table that lists for a given number of births the estimatednumber of people who will live to a given age. In Appendix C we give a lifetable based upon 100,000 births for ages from 0 to 85, both for women and formen. Show how from this table you can estimate the probability m(x) that aperson born in 1981 would live to age x. Write a program to plot m(x) bothfor men and for women, and comment on the differences that you see in thetwo cases.</li>
<li>*28 Here is an attempt to get around the fact that we cannot choose a "randominteger."</li>
<li>(a) What, intuitively, is the probability that a "randomly chosen" positiveinteger is a multiple of 3?</li>
<li>(b) Let P3(N) be the probability that an integer, chosen at random between1 and N, is a multiple of 3 (since the sample space is finite, this is alegitimate probability). Show that the limit
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<msub>
<mi>P</mi>
<mn>3</mn>
</msub>
<mo>=</mo><munder>
<mstyle mathsize='140%' displaystyle='true'><mrow>
<mi>lim</mi></mrow></mstyle>
<mrow>
<mi>N</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<msub>
<mi>P</mi>
<mn>3</mn>
</msub>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo></mrow>
</math>
exists and equals 1/3. This formalizes the intuition in (a), and gives usa way to assign "probabilities" to certain events that are infinite subsetsof the positive integers.</li>
<li>(c) If A is any set of positive integers, let A(N) mean the number of elementsof A which are less than or equal to N. Then define the "probability" of,provided this limit exists. Show that this definition would assign probability0 to any finite set and probability 1 to the set of all positiveintegers. Thus, the probability of the set of all integers is not the sum ofthe probabilities of the individual integers in this set. This means thatthe definition of probability given here is not a completely satisfactorydefinition.</li>
<li>(d) Let A be the set of all positive integers with an odd number of digits.Show that P(A) does not exist. This shows that under the abovedefinition of probability, not all sets have probabilities.</li>
<li>29 (from Sholander24) In a standard clover-leaf interchange, there are four rampsfor making right-hand turns, and inside these four ramps, there are four moreramps for making left-hand turns. Your car approaches the interchange fromthe south. A mechanism has been installed so that at each point where thereexists a choice of directions, the car turns to the right with fixedprobability r.</li>
<target type="page" id="48">48</target>
<li>(a) If r = 1/2, what is your chance of emerging from the interchange goingwest?</li>
<li>(b) Find the value of r that maximizes your chance of a westward departurefrom the interchange.</li>
<li>30 (from Benkoski25) Consider a "pure" cloverleaf interchange in which thereare no ramps for right-hand turns, but only the two intersecting straighthighways with cloverleaves for left-hand turns. (Thus, to turn right in suchan interchange, one must make three left-hand turns.) As in the precedingproblem, your car approaches the interchange from the south. What is thevalue of r that maximizes your chances of an eastward departure from theinterchange?</li>
<li>31 (from vos Savant26) A reader of Marilyn vos Savant's column wrote in withthe following question:My dad heard this story on the radio. At Duke University, twostudents had received A's in chemistry all semester. But on thenight before the final exam, they were partying in another stateand didn't ge back to Duke until it was over. Their excuse to theprofessor was that they had a flat tire, and they asked if they couldtake a make-up test. The professor agreed, wrote out a test and sentthe two to separate rooms to take it. The first question (on one sideof the paper) was worth 5 points, and they answered it easily. Thenthey flipped the paper over and found the second question, worth95 points: `Which tire was it?' What was the probability that bothstudents would say the same thing? My dad and I think it's 1 in16. Is that right?"</li>
<li>(a) Is the answer 1/16?</li>
<li>(b) The following question was asked of a class of students. "I was drivingto school today, and one of my tires went flat. Which tire do you thinkit was?" The responses were as follows: right front, 58%, left front, 11%,right rear, 18%, left rear, 13%. Suppose that this distribution holds inthe general population, and assume that the two test-takers are randomlychosen from the general population. What is the probability that theywill give the same answer to the second question?</li>
</ol>
</sec>
</sec>
</chapter>

<chapter id="chap9">
<label>Chapter 9</label>
<title>Central Limit Theorem</title>
<sec id="sec_9_1">
<label>9.1</label>
<title>Central Limit Theorem for Bernoulli Trials</title>
<p role="noindent">The second fundamental theorem of probability is the <i>Central Limit Theorem</i>. This theorem says that if <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is the sum of <i>n</i> mutually independent random variables, then the distribution function of <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is well-approximated by a certain type of continuous function known as a normal density function, which is given by the formula</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>f</mi><mrow><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>&#x03C3;</mi></mrow></msub>
<mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt><mi>&#x03C3;</mi></mrow>
</mfrac>
<msup>
<mi>e</mi>
<mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">as we have seen in Chapter 4.3. In this section, we will deal only with the case that &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1. We will call this particular normal density function the <i>standard normal density</i>, and we will denote it by &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>):</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">A graph of this function is given in Figure 9.1. It can be shown that the area under any normal density equals 1.</p>
<p role="indent">The Central Limit Theorem tells us, quite generally, what happens when we have the sum of a large number of independent random variables each of which contributes a small amount to the total. In this section we shall discuss this theorem as it applies to the Bernoulli trials and in Section 9.2 we shall consider more general processes. We will discuss the theorem in the case that the individual random variables are identically distributed, but the theorem is true, under certain conditions, even if the individual random variables have different distributions.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_325">325</target>

<fig id="fig_9_1">
<label>Figure 9.1</label>
<caption><p>Standard normal density.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_1.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_326">326</target>
<sec id="sec_BernoulliTrials_9_1">
<title>Bernoulli Trials</title>

<p role="noindent">Consider a Bernoulli trials process with probability <i>p</i> for success on each trial. Let <i>X</i><sub>i</sub> = 1 or 0 according as the <i>i</i>th outcome is a success or failure, and let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>. Then <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is the number of successes in <i>n</i> trials. We know that <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> has as its distribution the binomial probabilities <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>j</i>). In Section 3.2, we plotted these distributions for <i>p</i> = .3 and <i>p</i> = .5 for various values of <i>n</i> (see Figure 3.5).</p>
<p role="indent">We note that the maximum values of the distributions appeared near the expected value <i>np</i>, which causes their spike graphs to drift off to the right as <i>n</i> increased. Moreover, these maximum values approach 0 as <i>n</i> increased, which causes the spike graphs to flatten out.</p>
</sec>

<sec id="sec_StandardizedSums_9_1">
<title>Standardized Sums</title>

<p role="noindent">We can prevent the drifting of these spike graphs by subtracting the expected number of successes <i>np</i> from <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>, obtaining the new random variable <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2212; <i>np</i>. Now the maximum values of the distributions will always be near 0.</p>
<p role="indent">To prevent the spreading of these spike graphs, we can normalize <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2212; <i>np</i> to have variance 1 by dividing by its standard deviation &#x221A;<i>npq</i> (see Exercise 6.2.12 and Exercise 6.2.16).</p>
<p role="indent"><bold>Definition 9.1</bold> The <i>standardized sum</i> of <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is given by</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent"><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> always has expected value 0 and variance 1. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">Suppose we plot a spike graph with the spikes placed at the possible values of <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>: <i>x</i><sub>0</sub>, <i>x</i><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <i>x</i><sub>n</sub>, where</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>x</mi><mi>j</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">(9.1)</p>
<p role="indent">We make the height of the spike at <i>x</i><sub>j</sub> equal to the distribution value <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>j</i>). An example of this standardized spike graph, with <i>n</i> = 270 and <i>p</i> = .3, is shown in Figure 9.2. This graph is beautifully bell-shaped. We would like to fit a normal density to this spike graph. The obvious choice to try is the standard normal density, since it is centered at 0, just as the standardized spike graph is. In this figure, we have drawn this standard normal density. The reader will note that a horrible thing has occurred: Even though the shapes of the two graphs are the same, the heights are quite different.</p>

<fig id="fig_9_2">
<label>Figure 9.2</label>
<caption><p>Normalized binomial distribution and standard normal density.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_2.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_327">327</target>
<p role="indent">If we want the two graphs to fit each other, we must modify one of them; we choose to modify the spike graph. Since the shapes of the two graphs look fairly close, we will attempt to modify the spike graph without changing its shape. The reason for the differing heights is that the sum of the heights of the spikes equals 1, while the area under the standard normal density equals 1. If we were to draw a continuous curve through the top of the spikes, and find the area under this curve, we see that we would obtain, approximately, the sum of the heights of the spikes multiplied by the distance between consecutive spikes, which we will call &#x03F5;. Since the sum of the heights of the spikes equals one, the area under this curve would be approximately &#x03F5;. Thus, to change the spike graph so that the area under this curve has value 1, we need only multiply the heights of the spikes by 1/&#x03F5;. It is easy to see from Equation 9.1 that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03F5;</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">In Figure 9.3 we show the standardized sum <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> for <i>n</i> = 270 and <i>p</i> = .3, after correcting the heights, together with the standard normal density. (This figure was produced with the program <bold>CLTBernoulliPlot</bold>.) The reader will note that the standard normal fits the height-corrected spike graph extremely well. In fact, one version of the Central Limit Theorem (see Theorem 9.1) says that as <i>n</i> increases, the standard normal density will do an increasingly better job of approximating the height-corrected spike graphs corresponding to a Bernoulli trials process with <i>n</i> summands.</p>

<fig id="fig_9_3">
<label>Figure 9.3</label>
<caption><p>Corrected spike graph with standard normal density.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_3.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_328">328</target>
<p role="indent">Let us fix a value <i>x</i> on the <i>x</i>-axis and let <i>n</i> be a fixed positive integer. Then, using Equation 9.1, the point <i>x</i><sub>j</sub> that is closest to <i>x</i> has a subscript <i>j</i> given by the formula</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>&#x27E8;</mo>
<mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mo>&#x27E9;</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where &#x27E8;<i>a</i>&#x27E9; means the integer nearest to <i>a</i>. Thus the height of the spike above <i>x</i><sub>j</sub> will be</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo>
<mo>&#x27E8;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><msub><mi>x</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt><mo>&#x27E9;</mo>
<mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">For large <i>n</i>, we have seen that the height of the spike is very close to the height of the normal density at <i>x</i>. This suggests the following theorem.</p>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.1 (Central Limit Theorem for Binomial Distributions)</bold> For the binomial distribution <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>j</i>) we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo>
<mo>&#x27E8;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>x</mi><msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt><mo>&#x27E9;</mo>
<mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">where &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>) is the standard normal density.</p>
<p role="indent">The proof of this theorem can be carried out using Stirling&#x2019;s approximation from Section 3.1. We indicate this method of proof by considering the case <i>x</i> = 0. In this case, the theorem states that</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x27E8;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x27E9;</mo><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.3989</mn>
<mo>&#x2026;</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">In order to simplify the calculation, we assume that <i>np</i> is an integer, so that &#x27E8;<i>np</i>&#x27E9; = <i>np</i>. Then</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<msup><mi>p</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mi>q</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msup>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo><mspace width="0.2em"/><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Recall that Stirling&#x2019;s formula (see Theorem 3.3) states that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo>
<mo>&#x223C;</mo>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>n</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<msup><mi>n</mi><mi>n</mi></msup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="2em"/>
<mtext>as </mtext><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<target target-type="page" id="page_329">329</target>
<p role="indent">Using this, we have</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x223C;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<msup><mi>p</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mi>q</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msup>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>n</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<msup><mi>n</mi><mi>n</mi></msup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></msup>
</mrow>
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<msup><mo>(</mo><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mo>)</mo><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mo>(</mo><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mo>)</mo><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msup>
</mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">which simplifies to 1/&#x221A;(2&#x03C0;). &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_ApproxBinomial">
<title>Approximating Binomial Distributions</title>
<p role="noindent">We can use Theorem 9.1 to find approximations for the values of binomial distribution functions. If we wish to find an approximation for <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>j</i>), we set</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and solve for <i>x</i>, obtaining</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Theorem 9.1 then says that</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">is approximately equal to &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>), so</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mi>&#x03C6;</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<sec id="example9_1">
<label>Example 9.1</label>
<p role="noindent">Let us estimate the probability of exactly 55 heads in 100 tosses of a coin. For this case <i>np</i> = 100 &#x00B7; 1/2 = 50 and &#x221A;<i>npq</i> = &#x221A;(100 &#x00B7; 1/2 &#x00B7; 1/2) = 5. Thus <i>x</i><sub>55</sub> = (55 &#x2212; 50)/5 = 1 and</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>100</mn></msub><mo>=</mo><mn>55</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x223C;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mn>5</mn>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.0484</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">To four decimal places, the actual value is .0485, and so the approximation is very good. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">The program <bold>CLTBernoulliLocal</bold> illustrates this approximation for any choice of <i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, and <i>j</i>. We have run this program for two examples. The first is the probability of exactly 50 heads in 100 tosses of a coin; the estimate is .0798, while the actual value, to four decimal places, is .0796. The second example is the probability of exactly eight sixes in 36 rolls of a die; here the estimate is .1093, while the actual value, to four decimal places, is .1196.</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_330">330</target>
<p role="indent">The individual binomial probabilities tend to 0 as <i>n</i> tends to infinity. In most applications we are not interested in the probability that a specific outcome occurs, but rather in the probability that the outcome lies in a given interval, say the interval [<i>a</i>, <i>b</i>]. In order to find this probability, we add the heights of the spike graphs for values of <i>j</i> between <i>a</i> and <i>b</i>. This is the same as asking for the probability that the standardized sum <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> lies between <i>a</i>* and <i>b</i>*, where <i>a</i>* and <i>b</i>* are the standardized values of <i>a</i> and <i>b</i>. But as <i>n</i> tends to infinity the sum of these areas could be expected to approach the area under the standard normal density between <i>a</i>* and <i>b</i>*. The Central Limit Theorem states that this does indeed happen.</p>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.2 (Central Limit Theorem for Bernoulli Trials)</bold> Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> be the number of successes in <i>n</i> Bernoulli trials with probability <i>p</i> for success, and let <i>a</i> and <i>b</i> be two fixed real numbers. Then</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>b</mi>
</msubsup>
<mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">This theorem can be proved by adding together the approximations to <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>k</i>) given in Theorem 9.1. It is also a special case of the more general Central Limit Theorem (see Section 10.3).</p>
<p role="indent">We know from calculus that the integral on the right side of this equation is equal to the area under the graph of the standard normal density &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>) between <i>a</i> and <i>b</i>. We denote this area by NA(<i>a</i>*, <i>b</i>*). Unfortunately, there is no simple way to integrate the function <i>e</i><sup>&#x2212;<i>x</i><sup>2</sup>/2</sup>, and so we must either use a table of values or else a numerical integration program. (See Figure 9.4 for values of NA(0, <i>z</i>). A more extensive table is given in Appendix A.)</p>
<p role="indent">It is clear from the symmetry of the standard normal density that areas such as that between &#x2212;2 and 3 can be found from this table by adding the area from 0 to 2 (same as that from &#x2212;2 to 0) to the area from 0 to 3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_ApproxBinomialProb">
<title>Approximation of Binomial Probabilities</title>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is binomially distributed with parameters <i>n</i> and <i>p</i>. We have seen that the above theorem shows how to estimate a probability of the form</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">(9.2)</p>
<p role="indent">where <i>i</i> and <i>j</i> are integers between 0 and <i>n</i>. As we have seen, the binomial distribution can be represented as a spike graph, with spikes at the integers between 0 and <i>n</i>, and with the height of the <i>k</i>th spike given by <i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, <i>p</i>, <i>k</i>). For moderate-sized values of <i>n</i>, if we standardize this spike graph, and change the heights of its spikes, in the manner described above, the sum of the heights of the spikes is approximated by the area under the standard normal density between <i>i</i>* and <i>j</i>*. It turns out that a slightly more accurate approximation is afforded by the area under the standard</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_331">331</target>

<table-wrap id="table_9_1">
<label>Figure 9.4</label>
<caption><p>Table of values of NA(0, <i>z</i>), the normal area from 0 to <i>z</i>.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><i>z</i></th>
<th>NA(<i>z</i>)</th>
<th><i>z</i></th>
<th>NA(<i>z</i>)</th>
<th><i>z</i></th>
<th>NA(<i>z</i>)</th>
<th><i>z</i></th>
<th>NA(<i>z</i>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>.0</td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>.3413</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>.4772</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>.4987</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.1</td>
<td>.0398</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>.3643</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>.4821</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>.4990</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.2</td>
<td>.0793</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>.3849</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>.4861</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>.4993</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.3</td>
<td>.1179</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>.4032</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>.4893</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>.4995</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.4</td>
<td>.1554</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>.4192</td>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>.4918</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>.4997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.5</td>
<td>.1915</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>.4332</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>.4938</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>.4998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.6</td>
<td>.2257</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>.4452</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>.4953</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>.4998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.7</td>
<td>.2580</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>.4554</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>.4965</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td>.4999</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.8</td>
<td>.2881</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>.4641</td>
<td>2.8</td><td>.4974</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>.4999</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.9</td>
<td>.3159</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>.4713</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>.4981</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>.5000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>

<target target-type="page" id="page_332">332</target>
<p role="indent">normal density between the standardized values corresponding to (<i>i</i> &#x2212; 1/2) and (<i>j</i> + 1/2); these values are</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">and</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Thus,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mtext>NA</mtext>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">It should be stressed that the approximations obtained by using the Central Limit Theorem are only approximations, and sometimes they are not very close to the actual values (see Exercise 12).</p>
<p role="indent">We now illustrate this idea with some examples.</p>
<sec id="example9_2">
<label>Example 9.2</label>
<p role="noindent">A coin is tossed 100 times. Estimate the probability that the number of heads lies between 40 and 60 (the word &#x201C;between&#x201D; in mathematics means inclusive of the endpoints). The expected number of heads is 100&#x00B7;1/2 = 50, and the standard deviation for the number of heads is &#x221A;(100 &#x00B7; 1/2 &#x00B7; 1/2) = 5. Thus, since <i>n</i> = 100 is reasonably large, we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>40</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>60</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac><mrow><mn>39.5</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>50</mn></mrow><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac><mrow><mn>60.5</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>50</mn></mrow><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2.1</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>2.1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mtext>NA</mtext><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2.1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2.1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mtext>NA</mtext><mo>(</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2.1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.9642</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">The actual value is .96480, to five decimal places.</p>
<p role="indent">Note that in this case we are asking for the probability that the outcome will not deviate by more than two standard deviations from the expected value. Had we asked for the probability that the number of successes is between 35 and 65, this would have represented three standard deviations from the mean, and, using our 1/2 correction, our estimate would be the area under the standard normal curve between &#x2212;3.1 and 3.1, or 2NA(0, 3.1) = .9980. The actual answer in this case, to five places, is .99821. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">It is important to work a few problems by hand to understand the conversion from a given inequality to an inequality relating to the standardized variable. After this, one can then use a computer program that carries out this conversion, including the 1/2 correction. The program <bold>CLTBernoulliGlobal</bold> is such a program for estimating probabilities of the form <i>P</i>(<i>a</i> &#x2264; <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2264; <i>b</i>).</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_333">333</target>
<sec id="example9_3">
<label>Example 9.3</label>
<p role="noindent">Dartmouth College would like to have 1050 freshmen. This college cannot accommodate more than 1060. Assume that each applicant accepts with probability .6 and that the acceptances can be modeled by Bernoulli trials. If the college accepts 1700, what is the probability that it will have too many acceptances?</p>
<p role="indent">If it accepts 1700 students, the expected number of students who matriculate is .6 &#x00B7; 1700 = 1020. The standard deviation for the number that accept is &#x221A;(1700 &#x00B7; .6 &#x00B7; .4) &#x2248; 20. Thus we want to estimate the probability</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>1700</mn></msub><mo>&gt;</mo><mn>1060</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>1700</mn></msub><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mn>1061</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>1700</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&#x2265;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mn>1060.5</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1020</mn></mrow>
<mn>20</mn>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>1700</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mn>2.025</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">From Table 9.4, if we interpolate, we would estimate this probability to be .5 &#x2212; .4784 = .0216. Thus, the college is fairly safe using this admission policy. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_ApplicationsStats">
<title>Applications to Statistics</title>
<p role="noindent">There are many important questions in the field of statistics that can be answered using the Central Limit Theorem for independent trials processes. The following example is one that is encountered quite frequently in the news. Another example of an application of the Central Limit Theorem to statistics is given in Section 9.2.</p>
<sec id="example9_4">
<label>Example 9.4</label>
<p role="noindent">One frequently reads that a poll has been taken to estimate the proportion of people in a certain population who favor one candidate over another in a race with two candidates. (This model also applies to races with more than two candidates A and B, and two ballot propositions.) Clearly, it is not possible for pollsters to ask everyone for their preference. What is done instead is to pick a subset of the population, called a sample, and ask everyone in the sample for their preference. Let <i>p</i> be the actual proportion of people in the population who are in favor of candidate A and let <i>q</i> = 1 &#x2212; <i>p</i>. If we choose a sample of size <i>n</i> from the population, the preferences of the people in the sample can be represented by random variables <i>X</i><sub>1</sub>, <i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . . , <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>, where <i>X</i><sub>i</sub> = 1 if person <i>i</i> is in favor of candidate A, and <i>X</i><sub>i</sub> = 0 if person <i>i</i> is in favor of candidate B. Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>. If each subset of size <i>n</i> is chosen with the same probability, then <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is hypergeometrically distributed. If <i>n</i> is small relative to the size of the population (which is typically true in practice), then <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is approximately binomially distributed, with parameters <i>n</i> and <i>p</i>.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_334">334</target>
<p role="indent">The pollster wants to estimate the value <i>p</i>. An estimate for <i>p</i> is provided by the value <i>p&#x0305;</i> = <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>/<i>n</i>, which is the proportion of people in the sample who favor candidate B. The Central Limit Theorem says that the random variable <i>p&#x0305;</i> is approximately normally distributed. (In fact, our version of the Central Limit Theorem says that the distribution function of the random variable</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">is approximated by the standard normal density.) But we have</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<msqrt><mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac></msqrt>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>p</mi>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">i.e., <i>p&#x0305;</i> is just a linear function of <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>. Since the distribution of <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> is approximated by the standard normal density, the distribution of the random variable <i>p&#x0305;</i> must also be bell-shaped. We also know how to write the mean and standard deviation of <i>p&#x0305;</i> in terms of <i>p</i> and <i>n</i>. The mean of <i>p&#x0305;</i> is just <i>p</i>, and the standard deviation is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt>
<mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</msqrt>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Thus, it is easy to write down the standardized version of <i>p&#x0305;</i>; it is</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>p</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi><mo>/</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Since the distribution of the standardized version of <i>p&#x0305;</i> is approximated by the standard normal density, we know, for example, that 95% of its values will lie within two standard deviations of its mean, and the same is true of <i>p&#x0305;</i>. So we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mi>p</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn>
<msqrt><mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac></msqrt>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>2</mn>
<msqrt><mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac></msqrt>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.954</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Now the pollster does not know <i>p</i> or <i>q</i>, but he can use <i>p&#x0305;</i> and <i>q&#x0305;</i> = 1 &#x2212; <i>p&#x0305;</i> in their place without too much danger. With this idea in mind, the above statement is equivalent to the statement</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn>
<msqrt><mfrac><mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mover><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac></msqrt>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mi>p</mi>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>+</mo><mn>2</mn>
<msqrt><mfrac><mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mover><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac></msqrt>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.954</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The resulting interval</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><msqrt><mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mover><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover></mrow></msqrt></mrow>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><msqrt><mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mover><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover></mrow></msqrt></mrow>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">is called the <i>95 percent confidence interval</i> for the unknown value of <i>p</i>. The name is suggested by the fact that if we use this method to estimate <i>p</i> in a large number of samples we should expect that in about 95 percent of the samples the true value of <i>p</i> is contained in the confidence interval obtained from the sample. In Exercise 11 you are asked to write a program to illustrate that this does indeed happen.</p>
<p role="indent">The pollster has control over the value of <i>n</i>. Thus, if he wants to create a 95% confidence interval with length 6%, then he should choose a value of <i>n</i> so that</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><msqrt><mrow><mover><mi>p</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mover><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover></mrow></msqrt></mrow>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mn>.03</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Using the fact that <i>p&#x0305;q&#x0305;</i> &#x2264; 1/4, no matter what the value of <i>p&#x0305;</i> is, it is easy to show that if he chooses a value of <i>n</i> so that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mn>.03</mn>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">he will be safe. This is equivalent to choosing</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
<mo>&#x2265;</mo>
<mn>1111</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_335">335</target>

<fig id="fig_9_5">
<label>Figure 9.5</label>
<caption><p>Polling simulation.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_5.jpg"/>
</fig>
<p role="indent">So if the pollster chooses <i>n</i> to be 1200, say, and calculates <i>p&#x0305;</i> using his sample of size 1200, then 19 times out of 20 (i.e., 95% of the time), his confidence interval, which is of length 6%, will contain the true value of <i>p</i>. This type of confidence interval is typically reported in the news as follows: this survey has a 3% margin of error. In fact, most of the surveys that one sees reported in the paper will have sample sizes around 1000. A somewhat surprising fact is that the size of the population has apparently no effect on the sample size needed to obtain a 95% confidence interval for <i>p</i> with a given margin of error. To see this, note that the value of <i>n</i> that was needed depended only on the number .03, which is the margin of error. In other words, whether the population is of size 100,000 or 100,000,000, the pollster needs only to choose a sample of size 1200 or so to get the same accuracy of estimate of <i>p</i>. (We did use the fact that the sample size was small relative to the population size in the statement that <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is approximately binomially distributed.)</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_336">336</target>
<fig id="fig_9_6">
<label>Figure 9.6</label>
<caption><p>Confidence interval simulation.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_6.jpg"/>
</fig>
<p role="indent">In Figure 9.5, we show the results of simulating the polling process. The population is of size 100,000, and for the population, <i>p</i> = .54. The sample size was chosen to be 1200. The spike graph shows the distribution of <i>p&#x0305;</i> for 10,000 randomly chosen samples. For this simulation, the program kept track of the number of samples for which <i>p&#x0305;</i> was within 3% of .54. This number was 9648, which is close to 95% of the number of samples used.</p>
<p role="indent">Another way to see what the idea of confidence intervals means is shown in Figure 9.6. In this figure, we show 100 confidence intervals, obtained by computing <i>p&#x0305;</i> for 100 different samples of size 1200 from the same population as before. The reader can see that most of these confidence intervals (96, to be exact) contain the true value of <i>p</i>.</p>
<p role="indent">The Gallup Poll has used these polling techniques in every Presidential election since 1936 (and in innumerable other elections as well). Table 9.1 shows the results of their efforts. The reader will note that most of the approximations to <i>p</i> are within 3% of the actual value of <i>p</i>. The sample sizes for these polls were typically around 1500. (In the table, both the predicted and actual percentages for the winning candidate refer to the percentage of the vote among the &#x201C;major&#x201D; political parties. In most elections, there were two major parties, but in several elections, there were three.)</p>
<table-wrap id="table_9_1_gallup">
<label>Table 9.1</label>
<caption><p>Gallup Poll accuracy record.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Year</th>
<th>Winning Candidate</th>
<th>Gallup Final Survey</th>
<th>Election Result</th>
<th>Deviation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1936</td>
<td>Roosevelt</td>
<td>55.7%</td>
<td>62.5%</td>
<td>6.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1940</td>
<td>Roosevelt</td>
<td>52.0%</td>
<td>55.0%</td>
<td>3.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1944</td>
<td>Roosevelt</td>
<td>51.5%</td>
<td>53.3%</td>
<td>1.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr
><td>1948</td
<td>Truman</td>
<td>44.5%</td>
<td>49.9%</td>
<td>5.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1952</td>
<td>Eisenhower</td>
<td>51.0%</td>
<td>55.4%</td>
<td>4.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1956</td>
<td>Eisenhower</td>
<td>59.5%</td>
<td>57.8%</td>
<td>1.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
1960</td>
<td>Kennedy</td>
<td>51.0%</td>
<td>50.1%</td>
<td>0.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1964</td>
<td>Johnson</td>
<td>64.0%</td>
<td>61.3%</td>
<td>2.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1968</td>
<td>Nixon</td>
<td>43.0%</td>
<td>43.5%</td>
<td>0.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1972</td>
<td>Nixon</td>
<td>62.0%</td>
<td>61.8%</td>
<td>0.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1976</td>
<td>Carter</td>
<td>48.0%</td>
<td>50.0%</td>
<td>2.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1980</td>
<td>Reagan</td>
<td>47.0%</td>
<td>50.8%</td>
<td>3.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1984</td>
<td>Reagan</td>
<td>59.0%</td>
<td>59.1%</td>
<td>0.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1988</td>
<td>Bush</td>
<td>56.0%</td>
<td>53.9%</td>
<td>2.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1992</td>
<td>Clinton</td>
<td>49.0%</td>
<td>43.2%</td>
<td>5.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1996</td>
<td>Clinton</td>
<td>52.0%</td>
<td>50.1%</td>
<td>1.9%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="indent">This technique also plays an important role in the evaluation of the effectiveness of drugs in the medical profession. For example, it is sometimes desired to know what proportion of patients will be helped by a new drug. This proportion can be estimated by giving the drug to a subset of the patients, and determining the proportion of this sample who are helped by the drug. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_337">337</target>
<sec id="sec_HistoricalRemarks_9_1">
<title>Historical Remarks</title>
<p role="noindent">The Central Limit Theorem for Bernoulli trials was first proved by Abraham de Moivre and appeared in his book, <i>The Doctrine of Chances</i>, first published in 1718.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_1_2">2</xref></p>
<p role="indent">De Moivre spent his years from age 18 to 21 in prison in France because of his Protestant background. When he was released he left France for England, where he worked as a tutor to the sons of noblemen. Newton had presented a copy of his <i>Principia Mathematica</i> to the Earl of Devonshire. The story goes that, while de Moivre was tutoring at the Earl&#x2019;s house, he came upon Newton&#x2019;s work and found that it was beyond him. It is said that he then bought a copy of his own and tore it into separate pages, learning it page by page as he walked around London to his tutoring jobs. De Moivre frequented the coffeehouses in London, where he started his probability work by calculating odds for gamblers. He also met Newton at such a coffeehouse and they became fast friends. De Moivre dedicated his book to Newton.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_338">338</target>
<p role="indent"><i>The Doctrine of Chances</i> provides the techniques for solving a wide variety of gambling problems. In the midst of these gambling problems de Moivre rather modestly introduces his proof of the Central Limit Theorem, writing</p>
<p role="indent">A Method of approximating the Sum of the Terms of the Binomial (<i>a</i> + <i>b</i>)<sup>n</sup> expanded into a Series, from whence are deduced some practical Rules to estimate the Degree of Assent which is to be given to Experiments.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_1_3">3</xref></p>
<p role="indent">De Moivre&#x2019;s proof used the approximation to factorials that we now call Stirling&#x2019;s formula. De Moivre states that he had obtained this formula before Stirling but without determining the exact value of the constant &#x221A;(2&#x03C0;). While he says it is not really necessary to know this exact value, he concedes that knowing it &#x201C;has spread a singular Elegancy on the Solution.&#x201D;</p>
<p role="indent">The complete proof and an interesting discussion of the life of de Moivre can be found in the book <i>Games, Gods and Gambling</i> by F. N. David.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_1_4">4</xref></p>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn_9_1_2">
<label>2</label>
<p>A. de Moivre, <i>The Doctrine of Chances</i>, 3d ed. (London: Millar, 1756).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn_9_1_3">
<label>3</label>
<p>ibid., p. 243.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn_9_1_4">
<label>4</label>
<p>F. N. David, <i>Games, Gods and Gambling</i> (London: Griffin, 1962).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_Exercises_9_1">
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol>
<li>Let <i>S</i><sub>100</sub> be the number of heads that turn up in 100 tosses of a fair coin. Use the Central Limit Theorem to estimate
<ol>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>100</sub> &#x2264; 45).</li>
<li><i>P</i>(45 &lt; <i>S</i><sub>100</sub> &lt; 55).</li>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>100</sub> &gt; 63).</li>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>100</sub> &lt; 57).</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Let <i>S</i><sub>200</sub> be the number of heads that turn up in 200 tosses of a fair coin. Estimate
<ol>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>200</sub> = 100).</li>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>200</sub> = 90).</li>
<li><i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>200</sub> = 80).</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>A true-false examination has 48 questions. June has probability 3/4 of answering a question correctly. April just guesses on each question. A passing score is 30 or more correct answers. Compare the probability that June passes the exam with the probability that April passes it.</li>
<li>Let <i>S</i> be the number of heads in 1,000,000 tosses of a fair coin. Use (a) Chebyshev&#x2019;s inequality, and (b) the Central Limit Theorem, to estimate the probability that <i>S</i> lies between 499,500 and 500,500. Use the same two methods to estimate the probability that <i>S</i> lies between 499,000 and 501,000, and the probability that <i>S</i> lies between 498,500 and 501,500.</li>
<li>A rookie is brought to a baseball club on the assumption that he will have a .300 batting average. (Batting average is the ratio of the number of hits to the number of times at bat.) In the first year, he comes to bat 300 times and his batting average is .267. Assume that his at bats can be considered Bernoulli trials with probability .3 for success. Could such a low average be considered just bad luck or should he be sent back to the minor leagues? Comment on the assumption of Bernoulli trials in this situation.</li>
<li>Once upon a time, there were two railway trains competing for the passenger traffic of 1000 people leaving from Chicago at the same hour and going to Los Angeles. Assume that passengers are equally likely to choose each train. How many seats must a train have to assure a probability of .99 or better of having a seat for each passenger?</li>
<li>Assume that, as in Example 9.3, Dartmouth admits 1750 students. What is the probability of too many acceptances?</li>
<li>A club serves dinner to members only. They are seated at 12-seat tables. The manager observes over a long period of time that 95 percent of the time there are between six and nine full tables of members, and the remainder of the time the numbers are equally likely to fall above or below this range. Assume that each member decides to come with a given probability <i>p</i>, and that the decisions are independent. How many members are there? What is <i>p</i>?</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_339">339</target>
<li>Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> be the number of successes in <i>n</i> Bernoulli trials with probability .8 for success on each trial. Let <i>A</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>/<i>n</i> be the average number of successes. In each case give the value for the limit, and give a reason for your answer.
<ol>
<li>
<math display="inline"><mrow><msub><mi>lim</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow></msub><mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>=</mo><mn>.8</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.
</li>
<li>
<math display="inline"><mrow><msub><mi>lim</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow></msub><mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>.7</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>&lt;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&lt;</mo><mn>.9</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.
</li>
<li>
<math display="inline"><mrow><msub><mi>lim</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow></msub><mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&lt;</mo><mn>.8</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>.8</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.
</li>
<li>
<math display="inline"><mrow><msub><mi>lim</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow></msub><mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>.79</mn><mo>&lt;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&lt;</mo><mn>.81</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.
</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Find the probability that among 10,000 random digits the digit 3 appears not more than 931 times.</li>
<li>Write a computer program to simulate 10,000 Bernoulli trials with probability .3 for success on each trial. Have the program compute the 95 percent confidence interval for the probability of success based on the proportion of successes. Repeat the experiment 100 times and see how many times the true value of .3 is included within the confidence limits.</li>
<li>A balanced coin is flipped 400 times. Determine the number <i>x</i> such that the probability that the number of heads is between 200 &#x2212; <i>x</i> and 200 + <i>x</i> is approximately .80.</li>
<li>A noodle machine in Spumoni&#x2019;s spaghetti factory makes about 5 percent defective noodles even when properly adjusted. The noodles are then packed in crates containing 1900 noodles each. A crate is examined and found to contain 115 defective noodles. What is the approximate probability of finding at least this many defective noodles if the machine is properly adjusted?</li>
<li>A restaurant feeds 400 customers per day. On the average 20 percent of the customers order apple pie.
<ol>
<li>Give a range (called a 95 percent confidence interval) for the number of pieces of apple pie ordered on a given day such that you can be 95 percent sure that the actual number will fall in this range.</li>
<li>How many customers must the restaurant have, on the average, to be at least 95 percent sure that the number of customers ordering pie on that day falls in the 19 to 21 percent range?</li>
</ol>
</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_340">340</target>
<li>Recall that if <i>X</i> is a random variable, the <i>cumulative distribution function</i> of <i>X</i> is the function <i>F</i>(<i>x</i>) defined by <math display="inline"><mrow><mi>F</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.
<ol>
<li>Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> be the number of successes in <i>n</i> Bernoulli trials with probability <i>p</i> for success. Write a program to plot the cumulative distribution for <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>.</li>
<li>Modify your program in (a) to plot the cumulative distribution <msubsup><mi>F</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>(<i>x</i>) of the standardized random variable <math display="inline"><mrow><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow><msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac></mrow></math>.</li>
<li>Define the normal distribution <i>N</i>(<i>x</i>) to be the area under the normal curve up to the value <i>x</i>. Modify your program in (b) to plot the normal distribution as well, and compare it with the cumulative distribution of <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>. Do this for <i>n</i> = 10, 50, and 100.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>In Example 3.11, we were interested in testing the hypothesis that a new form of aspirin is effective 80 percent of the time rather than the 60 percent of the time as reported for standard aspirin. The new aspirin is given to <i>n</i> people. If it is effective in <i>m</i> or more cases, we accept the claim that the new drug is effective 80 percent of the time and if not we reject the claim. Using the Central Limit Theorem, show that you can choose the number of trials <i>n</i> and the critical value <i>m</i> so that the probability that we reject the hypothesis when it is true is less than .01 and the probability that we accept it when it is false is also less than .01. Find the smallest value of <i>n</i> that will suffice for this.</li>
<li>In an opinion poll it is assumed that an unknown proportion <i>p</i> of the people are in favor of a proposed new law and a proportion 1 &#x2212; <i>p</i> are against it. A sample of <i>n</i> people is taken to obtain their opinion. The proportion <i>p&#x0305;</i> in favor in the sample is taken as an estimate of <i>p</i>. Using the Central Limit Theorem, determine how large a sample will ensure that the estimate will, with probability .95, be correct to within .01.</li>
<li>A description of a poll in a certain newspaper says that one can be 95% confident that error due to sampling will be no more than plus or minus 3 percentage points. A poll in the New York Times taken in Iowa says that &#x201C;according to statistical theory, in 19 out of 20 cases the results based on such samples will differ by no more than 3 percentage points in either direction from what would have been obtained by interviewing all adult Iowans.&#x201D; These are both attempts to explain the concept of confidence intervals. Do both statements say the same thing? If not, which do you think is the more accurate description?</li>
</ol>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_341">341</target>
<sec id="sec_9_2">
<label>9.2</label>
<title>Central Limit Theorem for Discrete Independent Trials</title>
<p role="noindent">We have illustrated the Central Limit Theorem in the case of Bernoulli trials, but this theorem applies to a much more general class of chance processes. In particular, it applies to any independent trials process such that the individual trials have finite variance. For such a process, both the normal approximation for individual terms and the Central Limit Theorem are valid.</p>
<p role="indent">Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> be the sum of <i>n</i> independent discrete random variables of an independent trials process with common distribution function <i>m</i>(<i>x</i>) defined on the integers, with mean &#x03BC; and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>. We have seen in Section 7.2 that the distributions for such independent sums have shapes resembling the normal curve, but the largest values drift to the right and the curves flatten out (see Figure 7.6). We can prevent this just as we did for Bernoulli trials.</p>
<sec id="sec_StandardizedSums_9_2">
<title>Standardized Sums</title>
<p role="noindent">Consider the standardized random variable</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>&#x03BC;</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">This standardizes <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> to have expected value 0 and variance 1. If <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>j</i>, then <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> has the value <i>x</i><sub>j</sub> with</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>x</mi><mi>j</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>&#x03BC;</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">We can construct a spike graph just as we did for Bernoulli trials. Each spike is centered at some <i>x</i><sub>j</sub>. The distance between successive spikes is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">and the height of the spike is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>h</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">The case of Bernoulli trials is the special case for which <i>X</i><sub>j</sub> = 1 if the <i>j</i>th outcome is a success and 0 otherwise; then &#x03BC; = <i>p</i> and &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> = &#x221A;<i>pq</i>.</p>
<p role="indent">We now illustrate this process for two different discrete distributions. The first is the distribution <i>m</i>, given by</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>5</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>.2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.2</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">In Figure 9.7 we show the standardized sums for this distribution for the cases <i>n</i> = 2 and <i>n</i> = 10. Even for <i>n</i> = 2 the approximation is surprisingly good.</p>
<p role="indent">For our second discrete distribution, we choose</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>m</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>5</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>.4</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.3</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.1</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.1</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>.1</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">This distribution is quite asymmetric and the approximation is not very good for <i>n</i> = 3, but by <i>n</i> = 10 we again have an excellent approximation (see Figure 9.8). Figures 9.7 and 9.8 were produced by the program <bold>CLTIndTrialsPlot</bold>.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_342">342</target>
<fig id="fig_9_7">
<label>Figure 9.7</label>
<caption><p>Distribution of standardized sums.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_7.jpg"/>
</fig>

<fig id="fig_9_8">
<label>Figure 9.8</label>
<caption><p>Distribution of standardized sums.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_8.jpg"/>
</fig>
</sec>

<sec id="sec_ApproxTheorem_9_2">
<title>Approximation Theorem</title>
<p role="noindent">As in the case of Bernoulli trials, these graphs suggest the following approximation theorem for the individual probabilities.</p>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.3</bold> Let <i>X</i><sub>1</sub>, <i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . . , <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> be an independent trials process and let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>. Assume that the greatest common divisor of the differences of all the values that the <i>X</i><sub>j</sub> can take on is 1. Let <i>E</i>(<i>X</i><sub>j</sub>) = &#x03BC; and <i>V</i>(<i>X</i><sub>j</sub>) = &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>. Then for <i>n</i> large,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x223C;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>x</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where <i>x</i><sub>j</sub> = (<i>j</i> &#x2212; <i>n</i>&#x03BC;)/&#x221A;(<i>n</i>&#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>), and &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>) is the standard normal density. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">The program <bold>CLTIndTrialsLocal</bold> implements this approximation. When we run this program for 6 rolls of a die, and ask for the probability that the sum of the rolls equals 21, we obtain an actual value of .09285, and a normal approximation value of .09537. If we run this program for 24 rolls of a die, and ask for the probability that the sum of the rolls is 72, we obtain an actual value of .01724 and a normal approximation value of .01705. These results show that the normal approximations are quite good.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_343">343</target>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_CLT_DiscreteIndep">
<title>Central Limit Theorem for a Discrete Independent Trials Process</title>
<p role="noindent">The Central Limit Theorem for a discrete independent trials process is as follows.</p>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.4 (Central Limit Theorem)</bold> Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> be the sum of <i>n</i> discrete independent random variables with common distribution having expected value &#x03BC; and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>. Then, for <i>a</i> &lt; <i>b</i>,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>&#x03BC;</mi></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mi>n</mi><msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>b</mi>
</msubsup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">We will give the proofs of Theorems 9.3 and Theorem 9.4 in Section 10.3. Here we consider several examples.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_Examples_9_2">
<title>Examples</title>
<sec id="example9_5">
<label>Example 9.5</label>
<p role="noindent">A die is rolled 420 times. What is the probability that the sum of the rolls lies between 1400 and 1550</p>
<p role="indent">The sum is a random variable</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>S</mi><mn>420</mn></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>420</mn></msub>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where each <i>X</i><sub>j</sub> has distribution</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>m</mi><mi>X</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>5</mn></mtd><mtd><mn>6</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">We have seen that &#x03BC; = <i>E</i>(<i>X</i>) = 7/2 and &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> = <i>V</i>(<i>X</i>) = 35/12. Thus, <i>E</i>(<i>S</i><sub>420</sub>) = 420 &#x00B7; 7/2 = 1470, &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>(<i>S</i><sub>420</sub>) = 420 &#x00B7; 35/12 = 1225, and &#x03C3;(<i>S</i><sub>420</sub>) = 35. Therefore,</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>1400</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>420</mn></msub><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>1550</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac><mrow><mn>1399.5</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1470</mn></mrow><mn>35</mn></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>420</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac><mrow><mn>1550.5</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1470</mn></mrow><mn>35</mn></mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2.01</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>420</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>2.30</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mtext>NA</mtext><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2.01</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2.30</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.9670</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">We note that the program <bold>CLTIndTrialsGlobal</bold> could be used to calculate these probabilities. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_344">344</target>
<sec id="example9_6">
<label>Example 9.6</label>
<p role="noindent">A student&#x2019;s grade point average is the average of his grades in 30 courses. The grades are based on 100 possible points and are recorded as integers. Assume that, in each course, the instructor makes an error in grading of <i>k</i> with probability |<i>p</i>/<i>k</i>|, where <i>k</i> = &#x00B1;1, &#x00B1;2, &#x00B1;3, &#x00B1;4, &#x00B1;5. The probability of no error is then 1 &#x2212; (137/30)<i>p</i>. (The parameter <i>p</i> represents the inaccuracy of the instructor&#x2019;s grading.) Thus, in each course, there are two grades for the student, namely the &#x201C;correct&#x201D; grade and the recorded grade. So there are two average grades for the student, namely the average of the correct grades and the average of the recorded grades.</p>
<p role="indent">We wish to estimate the probability that these two average grades differ by less than .05 for a given student. We now assume that <i>p</i> = 1/20. We also assume that the total error is the sum <i>S</i><sub>30</sub> of 30 independent random variables each with distribution</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>m</mi><mi>X</mi></msub>
<mo>:</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>{</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>5</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>4</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>3</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>0</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>5</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>100</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>80</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>60</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>40</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>20</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>463</mn><mn>600</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>20</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>40</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>60</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>80</mn></mfrac></mtd>
<mtd><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>100</mn></mfrac></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>}</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">One can easily calculate that <i>E</i>(<i>X</i>) = 0 and &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>(<i>X</i>) = 1.5. Then we have</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>.05</mn>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>30</mn></msub><mn>30</mn></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mn>.05</mn>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1.5</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msub><mi>S</mi><mn>30</mn></msub><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>1.5</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1.5</mn></mrow>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>30</mn><mo>&#x00B7;</mo><mn>1.5</mn></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>30</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1.5</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>30</mn><mo>&#x00B7;</mo><mn>1.5</mn></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>.224</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mn>30</mn><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>.224</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mtext>NA</mtext><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>.224</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>.224</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>.1772</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">This means that there is only a 17.7% chance that a given student&#x2019;s grade point average is accurate to within .05. (Thus, for example, if two candidates for valedictorian have recorded averages of 97.1 and 97.2, there is an appreciable probability that their correct averages are in the reverse order.) For a further discussion of this example, see the article by R. M. Kozelka.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_2_5">5</xref> &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
</sec>

<sec id="sec_MoreGeneralCLT">
<title>A More General Central Limit Theorem</title>
<p role="noindent">In Theorem 9.4, the discrete random variables that were being summed were assumed to be independent and identically distributed. It turns out that the assumption of identical distributions can be substantially weakened. Much work has been done in this area, with an important contribution being made by J. W. Lindeberg. Lindeberg found a condition on the sequence {<i>X</i><sub>n</sub>} which guarantees that the distribution of the sum <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is asymptotically normally distributed. Feller showed that Lindeberg&#x2019;s condition is necessary as well, in the sense that if the condition does not hold, then the sum <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is not asymptotically normally distributed. For a precise statement of Lindeberg&#x2019;s Theorem, we refer the reader to Feller.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_2_6">6</xref> A sufficient condition that is stronger (but easier to state) than Lindeberg&#x2019;s condition, and is weaker than the condition in Theorem 9.4, is given in the following theorem.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_345">345</target>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.5 (Central Limit Theorem)</bold> Let <i>X</i><sub>1</sub>, <i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . . , <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>, . . . be a sequence of independent discrete random variables, and let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub>. For each <i>n</i>, denote the mean and variance of <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> by &#x03BC;<sub>n</sub> and &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup><sub>n</sub>, respectively. Define the mean and variance of <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> to be <i>m</i><sub>n</sub> and <i>s</i><sup>2</sup><sub>n</sub>, respectively, and assume that <i>s</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2192; &#x221E;. If there exists a constant <i>A</i>, such that |<i>X</i><sub>n</sub>| &#x2264; <i>A</i> for all <i>n</i>, then for <i>a</i> &lt; <i>b</i>,</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msub><mi>m</mi><mi>n</mi></msub></mrow>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
</mfrac>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>b</mi>
</msubsup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>

<p role="indent">The condition that |<i>X</i><sub>n</sub>| &#x2264; <i>A</i> for all <i>n</i> is sometimes described by saying that the sequence {<i>X</i><sub>n</sub>} is <i>uniformly bounded</i>. The condition that <i>s</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2192; &#x221E; is necessary (see Exercise 15).</p>

<fn-group>
<fn id="fn_9_2_5">
<label>5</label>
<p>R. M. Kozelka, &#x201C;Grade-Point Averages and the Central Limit Theorem,&#x201D; <i>American Math. Monthly</i>, vol. 86 (Nov 1979), pp. 773&#x2013;777.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn_9_2_6">
<label>6</label>
<p>W. Feller, <i>Introduction to Probability Theory and its Applications</i>, vol. 1, 3rd ed. (New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1968), p. 254.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>

<target target-type="page" id="page_346">346</target>

<fig id="fig_9_9">
<label>Figure 9.9</label>
<caption><p>Sums of randomly chosen random variables.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_9.jpg"/>
</fig>

<target target-type="page" id="page_347">347</target>

<fig id="fig_9_10">
<label>Figure 9.10</label>
<caption><p>Distribution of heights of adult women.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_10.jpg"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec_NormalGeneticsDiscrete">
<title>The Normal Distribution and Genetics</title>
<p role="noindent">When one looks at the distribution of heights of adults of one sex in a given population, one cannot help but notice that this distribution looks like the normal distribution. An example of this is shown in Figure 9.10. This figure shows the distribution of heights of 9593 women between the ages of 21 and 74. These data come from the Health and Nutrition Examination Survey I (HANES I). For this survey, a sample of the U.S. civilian population was chosen. The survey was carried out between 1971 and 1974.</p>
<p role="indent">A natural question to ask is &#x201C;How does this come about?&#x201D;. Francis Galton, an English scientist in the 19th century, studied this question, and other related questions, and constructed probability models that were of great importance in explaining the genetic effects on such attributes as height. In fact, one of the most important ideas in statistics, the idea of regression to the mean, was invented by Galton in his attempts to understand these genetic effects.</p>
<p role="indent">Galton was faced with an apparent contradiction. On the one hand, he knew that the normal distribution arises in situations in which many small independent effects are being summed. On the other hand, he also knew that many quantitative attributes, such as height, are strongly influenced by genetic factors: tall parents tend to have tall offspring. Thus in this case, there seem to be two large effects, namely the parents. Galton was certainly aware of the fact that non-genetic factors played a role in determining the height of an individual. Nevertheless, unless these non-genetic factors overwhelm the genetic ones, thereby refuting the hypothesis that heredity is important in determining height, it did not seem possible for sets of parents of given heights to have offspring whose heights were normally distributed.</p>
<p role="indent">An alternative hypothesis, which does explain the observation of normally distributed heights in offspring of a given sex, is the multiple-gene hypothesis. Under this hypothesis, we assume that there are many genes that affect the height of an individual. The height of the offspring is a random variable, which can be expressed as</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>H</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>W</mi>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">if there are <i>n</i> genes that affect height. (Here, as before, the random variable <i>W</i> denotes non-genetic effects.) Although <i>n</i> is fixed, if it is fairly large, then Theorem 9.5 implies that the sum <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> is approximately normally distributed. Now, if we assume that the <i>X</i><sub>i</sub>&#x2019;s have a significantly larger cumulative effect than <i>W</i> does, then <i>H</i> is approximately normally distributed.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_352">352</target>
<fig id="fig_9_11">
<label>Figure 9.11</label>
<caption><p>Two-stage version of the quincunx.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_11.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_353">353</target>
<fig id="fig_9_12">
<label>Figure 9.12</label>
<caption><p>Galton&#x2019;s explanation of reversion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_12.jpg"/>
</fig>
</sec>

<sec id="sec_Exercises_9_2">
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol>
<target target-type="page" id="page_354">354</target>
<li>A die is rolled 24 times. Use the Central Limit Theorem to estimate the probability that
<ol>
<li>the sum is greater than 84.</li>
<li>the sum is equal to 84.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>A random walker starts at 0 on the <i>x</i>-axis and at each time unit moves 1 step to the right or 1 step to the left with probability 1/2. Estimate the probability that, after 100 steps, the walker is more than 10 steps from the starting position.</li>
<li>A piece of rope is made up of 100 strands. Assume that the breaking strength of the rope is the sum of the breaking strengths of the individual strands. Assume further that this sum may be considered to be the sum of an independent trials process with 100 experiments each having expected value of 10 pounds and standard deviation 1. Find the approximate probability that the rope will support a weight
<ol>
<li>of 1000 pounds.</li>
<li>of 970 pounds.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Write a program to find the average of 1000 random digits 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9. Have the program test to see if the average lies within three standard deviations of the expected value of 4.5. Modify the program so that it repeats this simulation 1000 times and keeps track of the number of times the test is passed. Does your outcome agree with the Central Limit Theorem?</li>
<li>A die is thrown until the first time the total sum of the face values of the die is 700 or greater. Estimate the probability that, for this to happen,
<ol>
<li>more than 210 tosses are required.</li>
<li>less than 190 tosses are required.</li>
<li>between 180 and 210 tosses, inclusive, are required.</li>
</ol>
</li>

<target target-type="page" id="page_355">355</target>

<li>A bank accepts rolls of pennies and gives 50 cents credit to a customer without counting the contents. Assume that a roll contains 49 pennies 30 percent of the time, 50 pennies 60 percent of the time, and 51 pennies 10 percent of the time.
<ol>
<li>Find the expected value and the variance for the amount that the bank loses on a typical roll.</li>
<li>Estimate the probability that the bank will lose more than 25 cents in 100 rolls.</li>
<li>Estimate the probability that the bank will lose exactly 25 cents in 100 rolls.</li>
<li>Estimate the probability that the bank will lose any money in 100 rolls.</li>
<li>How many rolls does the bank need to collect to have a 99 percent chance of a net loss?</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>A surveying instrument makes an error of &#x2212;2, &#x2212;1, 0, 1, or 2 feet with equal probabilities when measuring the height of a 200-foot tower.
<ol>
<li>Find the expected value and the variance for the height obtained using this instrument once.</li>
<li>Estimate the probability that in 18 independent measurements of this tower, the average of the measurements is between 199 and 201, inclusive.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>For Example 9.6 estimate <i>P</i>(<i>S</i><sub>30</sub> = 0). That is, estimate the probability that the errors cancel out and the student&#x2019;s grade point average is correct.</li>
<li>Prove the Law of Large Numbers using the Central Limit Theorem.</li>
<li>Peter and Paul match pennies 10,000 times. Describe briefly what each of the following theorems tells you about Peter&#x2019;s fortune.
<ol>
<li>The Law of Large Numbers.</li>
<li>The Central Limit Theorem.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>A tourist in Las Vegas was attracted by a certain gambling game in which the customer stakes 1 dollar on each play; a win then pays the customer 2 dollars plus the return of her stake, although a loss costs her only her stake. Las Vegas insiders, and alert students of probability theory, know that the probability of winning at this game is 1/4. When driven from the tables by hunger, the tourist had played this game 240 times. Assuming that no near miracles happened, about how much poorer was the tourist upon leaving the casino? What is the probability that she lost no money?</li>
<li>We have seen that, in playing roulette at Monte Carlo (Example 6.13), betting 1 dollar on red or 1 dollar on 17 amounts to choosing between the distributions
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>m</mi><mi>X</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>18</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>37</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>37</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>18</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>37</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
or
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>m</mi><mi>X</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>35</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>36</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>37</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>37</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
You plan to choose one of these methods and use it to make 100 1-dollar bets using the method chosen. Using the Central Limit Theorem, estimate the probability of winning any money for each of the two games. Compare your estimates with the actual probabilities, which can be shown, from exact calculations, to equal .437 and .509 to three decimal places.
</li>
<li>In Example 9.6 find the largest value of <i>p</i> that gives probability .954 that the first decimal place is correct.</li>
<li>It has been suggested that Example 9.6 is unrealistic, in the sense that the probabilities of errors are too low. Make up your own (reasonable) estimate for the distribution <i>m</i>(<i>x</i>), and determine the probability that a student&#x2019;s grade point average is accurate to within .05. Also determine the probability that it is accurate to within .5.</li>
<li>Find a sequence of uniformly bounded discrete independent random variables {<i>X</i><sub>n</sub>} such that the variance of their sum does not tend to &#x221E; as <i>n</i> &#x2192; &#x221E;, and such that their sum is not asymptotically normally distributed.</li>
</ol>
</sec>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_356">356</target>
<sec id="sec_9_3">
<label>9.3</label>
<title>Central Limit Theorem for Continuous Independent Trials</title>
<p role="noindent">We have seen in Section 9.2 that the distribution function for the sum of a large number <i>n</i> of independent discrete random variables with mean &#x03BC; and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> tends to look like a normal density with mean <i>n</i>&#x03BC; and variance <i>n</i>&#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>. What is remarkable about this result is that it holds for <i>any</i> distribution with finite mean and variance. We shall see in this section that the same result also holds true for continuous random variables having a common density function.</p>
<p role="indent">Let us begin by looking at some examples to see whether such a result is even plausible.</p>
<sec id="sec_StandardizedSums_9_3">
<title>Standardized Sums</title>
<sec id="example9_7">
<label>Example 9.7</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose we choose <i>n</i> random numbers from the interval [0, 1] with uniform density. Let <i>X</i><sub>1</sub>, <i>X</i><sub>2</sub>, . . . , <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> denote these choices, and <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> their sum.</p>
<p role="indent">We saw in Example 7.9 that the density function for <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> tends to have a normal shape, but is centered at <i>n</i>/2 and is flattened out. In order to compare the shapes of these density functions for different values of <i>n</i>, we proceed as in the previous section: we standardize <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> by defining</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>&#x03BC;</mi></mrow>
<mrow><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt><mi>&#x03C3;</mi></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Then we see that for all <i>n</i> we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>E</mi><mo>(</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>0</mn>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>V</mi><mo>(</mo><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The density function for <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> is just a standardized version of the density function for <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> (see Figure 9.13). &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec id="example9_8">
<label>Example 9.8</label>
<p role="noindent">Let us do the same thing, but now choose numbers from the interval [0, +&#x221E;) with an exponential density with parameter &#x03BB;. Then (see Example 6.26)</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03BC;</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>E</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>X</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mi>&#x03BB;</mi></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>V</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>X</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Here we know the density function for <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> explicitly (see Section 7.2). We can use Corollary 5.1 to calculate the density function for <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>. We obtain</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>f</mi><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03BB;</mi>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mi>x</mi></mrow></msup>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
</mrow>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>f</mi><msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt><mi>&#x03BB;</mi></mfrac>
<msub><mi>f</mi><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub></msub>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt><mi>x</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow>
<mi>&#x03BB;</mi>
</mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The graph of the density function for <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> is shown in Figure 9.14. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_357">357</target>
<fig id="fig_9_13">
<label>Figure 9.13</label>
<caption><p>Density function for <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> (uniform case, <i>n</i> = 2, 3, 4, 10).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_13.jpg"/>
</fig>

<p role="indent">These examples make it seem plausible that the density function for the normalized random variable <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> for large <i>n</i> will look very much like the normal density with mean 0 and variance 1 in the continuous case as well as in the discrete case. The Central Limit Theorem makes this statement precise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_CLT_Continuous">
<title>Central Limit Theorem</title>
<p role="indent"><bold>Theorem 9.6 (Central Limit Theorem)</bold> Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> be the sum of <i>n</i> independent continuous random variables with common density function <i>p</i> having expected value &#x03BC; and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>. Let <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> = (<i>S</i><sub>n</sub> &#x2212; <i>n</i>&#x03BC;)/&#x221A;<i>n</i>&#x03C3;. Then we have, for all <i>a</i> &lt; <i>b</i>,</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2192;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mi>b</mi>
<mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>b</mi>
</msubsup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_358">358</target>
<fig id="fig_9_14">
<label>Figure 9.14</label>
<caption><p>Density function for <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> (exponential case, <i>n</i> = 2, 3, 10, 30, &#x03BB; = 1).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_14.jpg"/>
</fig>
<p role="indent">We shall give a proof of this theorem in Section 10.3. We will now look at some examples.</p>

<sec id="example9_9">
<label>Example 9.9</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose a surveyor wants to measure a known distance, say of 1 mile, using a transit and some method of triangulation. He knows that because of possible motion of the transit, atmospheric distortions, and human error, any one measurement is apt to be slightly in error. He plans to make several measurements and take an average. He assumes that his measurements are independent random variables with a common distribution of mean &#x03BC; = 1 and standard deviation &#x03C3; = .0002 (so, if the errors are approximately normally distributed, then his measurements are within 1 foot of the correct distance about 65% of the time). What can he say about the average?</p>
<p role="indent">He can say that if <i>n</i> is large, the average <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>/<i>n</i> has a density function that is approximately normal, with mean &#x03BC; = 1 mile, and standard deviation &#x03C3; = .0002/&#x221A;<i>n</i> miles.</p>
<p role="indent">How many measurements should he make to be reasonably sure that his average lies within .0001 of the true value? The Chebyshev inequality says</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>|</mo>
<mfrac><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mi>&#x03BC;</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2265;</mo>
<mn>.0001</mn>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mfrac>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>.0002</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><msup><mn>10</mn><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>8</mn></mrow></msup><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>4</mn><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">so that we must have <i>n</i> &#x2265; 80 before the probability that his error is less than .0001 exceeds .95.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_359">359</target>
<p role="indent">We have already noticed that the estimate in the Chebyshev inequality is not always a good one, and here is a case in point. If we assume that <i>n</i> is large enough so that the density for <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> is approximately normal, then we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>|</mo>
<mfrac><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mi>&#x03BC;</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mn>.0001</mn>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mn>.5</mn>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>.5</mn>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt></mfrac>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>.5</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt></mrow>
<mrow><mo>+</mo><mn>.5</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt></mrow>
</msubsup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">and this last expression is greater than .95 if .5&#x221A;<i>n</i> &#x2265; 2. This says that it suffices to take <i>n</i> = 16 measurements for the same results. This second calculation is stronger, but depends on the assumption that <i>n</i> = 16 is large enough to establish the normal density as a good approximation to <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>, and hence to <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>. The Central Limit Theorem here says nothing about how large <i>n</i> has to be. In most cases involving sums of independent random variables, a good rule of thumb is that for <i>n</i> &#x2265; 30, the approximation is a good one. In the present case, if we assume that the errors are approximately normally distributed, then the approximation is probably fairly good even for <i>n</i> = 16. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>

<sec id="sec_EstimatingMean">
<title>Estimating the Mean</title>

<sec id="example9_10">
<label>Example 9.10</label>
<p role="noindent">(Continuation of Example 9.9) Now suppose our surveyor is measuring an unknown distance with the same instruments under the same conditions. He takes 36 measurements and averages them. How sure can he be that his measurement lies within .0002 of the true value?</p>
<p role="indent">Again using the normal approximation, we get</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mrow>
<mo>|</mo>
<mfrac><msub><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mi>&#x03BC;</mi>
<mo>|</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mn>.0002</mn>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mo>|</mo>
<msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>
<mo>|</mo>
<mo>&lt;</mo>
<mn>.5</mn>
<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>2</mn>
<msqrt><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi></mrow></msqrt>
</mfrac>
<msubsup>
<mo>&#x222B;</mo>
<mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>3</mn></mrow>
<mn>3</mn>
</msubsup>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></msup>
<mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.997</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">This means that the surveyor can be 99.7 percent sure that his average is within .0002 of the true value. To improve his confidence, he can take more measurements, or require less accuracy, or improve the quality of his measurements (i.e., reduce the variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>). In each case, the Central Limit Theorem gives quantitative information about the confidence of a measurement process, assuming always that the normal approximation is valid.</p>
<p role="indent">Now suppose the surveyor does not know the mean or standard deviation of his measurements, but assumes that they are independent. How should he proceed?</p>
<p role="indent">Again, he makes several measurements of a known distance and averages them. As before, the average error is approximately normally distributed, but now with unknown mean and variance. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_360">360</target>
<sec id="sec_SampleMean">
<title>Sample Mean</title>
<p role="noindent">If he knows the variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> of the error distribution is .0002, then he can estimate the mean &#x03BC; by taking the average, or <i>sample mean</i> of, say, 36 measurements:</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msub><mi>x</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>x</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
</mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where <i>n</i> = 36. Then, as before, <i>E</i>(<mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>) = &#x03BC;. Moreover, the preceding argument shows that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mo>|</mo><mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>|</mo><mo>&lt;</mo><mn>.0002</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.997</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">The interval (<mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover> &#x2212; .0002, <mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover> + .0002) is called the 99.7% confidence interval for &#x03BC; (see Example 9.4).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_SampleVariance">
<title>Sample Variance</title>
<p role="noindent">If he does not know the variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> of the error distribution, then he can estimate &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> by the <i>sample variance</i>:</p>

<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mover><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>x</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>x</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup>
</mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">where <i>n</i> = 36. The Law of Large Numbers, applied to the random variables (<i>X</i><sub>i</sub> &#x2212; <mover><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover>)<sup>2</sup>, says that for large <i>n</i>, the sample variance <msup><mover><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup> lies close to the variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>, so that the surveyor can use <msup><mover><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x0305;</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup> in place of &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> in the argument above.</p>
<p role="indent">Experience has shown that, in most practical problems of this type, the sample variance is a good estimate for the variance, and can be used in place of the variance to determine confidence levels for the sample mean. This means that we can rely on the Law of Large Numbers for estimating the variance, and the Central Limit Theorem for estimating the mean.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_tDensity">
<title><i>t</i>-Density</title>
<p role="noindent">The statistician W. S. Gosset<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_9_3_13">13</xref> has shown that in this case <msubsup><mi>T</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> has a density function that is not normal but rather a <i>t</i>-density with <i>n</i> degrees of freedom. (The number <i>n</i> of degrees of freedom is simply a parameter which tells us which <i>t</i>-density to use.) In this case we can use the <i>t</i>-density in place of the normal density to determine confidence levels for &#x03BC;. As <i>n</i> increases, the <i>t</i>-density approaches the normal density. Indeed, even for <i>n</i> = 8 the <i>t</i>-density and normal density are practically the same (see Figure 9.15).</p>

<fn-group>
<fn id="fn_9_3_13">
<label>13</label>
<p>W. S. Gosset discovered the distribution we now call the <i>t</i>-distribution while working for the Guinness Brewery in Dublin. He wrote under the pseudonym &#x201C;Student.&#x201D; The results discussed here first appeared in Student, &#x201C;The Probable Error of a Mean,&#x201D; <i>Biometrika</i>, vol. 6 (1908), pp. 1&#x2013;24.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<target target-type="page" id="page_361">361</target>
<fig id="fig_9_15">
<label>Figure 9.15</label>
<caption><p>Graph of <i>t</i>&#x2212;density for <i>n</i> = 1, 3, 8 and the normal density with &#x03BC; = 0, &#x03C3; = 1.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure9_15.jpg"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_Exercises_9_3">
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol>
<target target-type="page" id="page_362">362</target>
<li>Let <i>X</i> be a continuous random variable with mean &#x03BC;(<i>X</i>) and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>(<i>X</i>), and let <i>X</i>* = (<i>X</i> &#x2212; &#x03BC;)/&#x03C3; be its standardized version. Verify directly that &#x03BC;(<i>X</i>*) = 0 and &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>(<i>X</i>*) = 1.</li>
<li>Let {<i>X</i><sub>k</sub>}, 1 &#x2264; <i>k</i> &#x2264; <i>n</i>, be a sequence of independent random variables, all with mean 0 and variance 1, and let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>, <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup>, and <i>A</i><sub>n</sub> be their sum, standardized sum, and average, respectively. Verify directly that <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> = <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>/&#x221A;<i>n</i> = &#x221A;<i>n</i> <i>A</i><sub>n</sub>.</li>
<li>Let {<i>X</i><sub>k</sub>}, 1 &#x2264; <i>k</i> &#x2264; <i>n</i>, be a sequence of random variables, all with mean &#x03BC; and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup>, and <i>Y</i><sub>k</sub> = <i>X</i>*<sub>k</sub> be their standardized versions. Let <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> and <i>T</i><sub>n</sub> be the sum of the <i>X</i><sub>k</sub> and <i>Y</i><sub>k</sub>, and <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> and <msubsup><mi>T</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> their standardized version. Show that <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> = <msubsup><mi>T</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup> = <i>T</i><sub>n</sub>/&#x221A;<i>n</i>.</li>
<li>Suppose we choose independently 25 numbers at random (uniform density) from the interval [0, 20]. Write the normal densities that approximate the densities of their sum <i>S</i><sub>25</sub>, their standardized sum <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><sub>25</sub>, and their average <i>A</i><sub>25</sub>.</li>
<li>Write a program to choose independently 25 numbers at random from [0, 20], compute their sum <i>S</i><sub>25</sub>, and repeat this experiment 1000 times. Make a bar graph for the density of <i>S</i><sub>25</sub> and compare it with the normal approximation of Exercise 4. How good is the fit? Now do the same for the standardized sum <msubsup><mi>S</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2217;</mo></msubsup><sub>25</sub> and the average <i>A</i><sub>25</sub>.</li>
<li>In general, the Central Limit Theorem gives a better estimate than Chebyshev&#x2019;s inequality for the average of a sum. To see this, let <i>A</i><sub>25</sub> be the average calculated in Exercise 5, and let <i>N</i> be the normal approximation for <i>A</i><sub>25</sub>. Modify your program in Exercise 5 to provide a table of the function <i>F</i>(<i>x</i>) = <i>P</i>(|<i>A</i><sub>25</sub> &#x2212; 10| &#x2265; <i>x</i>) = fraction of the total of 1000 trials for which |<i>A</i><sub>25</sub> &#x2212; 10| &#x2265; <i>x</i>. Do the same for the function <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = <i>P</i>(|<i>N</i> &#x2212; 10| &#x2265; <i>x</i>). (You can use the normal table, Table 9.4, or the procedure NormalArea for this.) Now plot on the same axes the graphs of <i>F</i>(<i>x</i>), <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>), and the Chebyshev function <i>g</i>(<i>x</i>) = 4/(3<i>x</i><sup>2</sup>). How do <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) and <i>g</i>(<i>x</i>) compare as estimates for <i>F</i>(<i>x</i>)?</li>
<li>The Central Limit Theorem says the sums of independent random variables tend to look normal, no matter what crazy distribution the individual variables have. Let us test this by a computer simulation. Choose independently 25 numbers from the interval [0, 1] with the probability density <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) given below, and compute their sum <i>S</i><sub>25</sub>. Repeat this experiment 1000 times, and make up a bar graph of the results. Now plot on the same graph the density &#x03C6;(<i>x</i>) = normal (<i>x</i>, &#x03BC;(<i>S</i><sub>25</sub>), &#x03C3;(<i>S</i><sub>25</sub>)). How well does the normal density fit your bar graph in each case?
<ol>
<li><i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = 1.</li>
<li><i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = 2<i>x</i>.</li>
<li><i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = 3<i>x</i><sup>2</sup>.</li>
<li><i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = 4|<i>x</i> &#x2212; 1/2|.</li>
<li><i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = 2 &#x2212; 4|<i>x</i> &#x2212; 1/2|.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Repeat the experiment described in Exercise 7 but now choose the 25 numbers from [0, &#x221E;), using <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = <i>e</i><sup>&#x2212;<i>x</i></sup>.</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_363">363</target>
<li>How large must <i>n</i> be before <i>S</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> is approximately normal? This number is often surprisingly small. Let us explore this question with a computer simulation. Choose <i>n</i> numbers from [0, 1] with probability density <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>), where <i>n</i> = 3, 6, 12, 20, and <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) is each of the densities in Exercise 7. Compute their sum <i>S</i><sub>n</sub>, repeat this experiment 1000 times, and make up a bar graph of 20 bars of the results. How large must <i>n</i> be before you get a good fit?</li>
<li>A surveyor is measuring the height of a cliff known to be about 1000 feet. He assumes his instrument is properly calibrated and that his measurement errors are independent, with mean &#x03BC; = 0 and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> = 10. He plans to take <i>n</i> measurements and form the average. Estimate, using (a) Chebyshev&#x2019;s inequality and (b) the normal approximation, how large <i>n</i> should be if he wants to be 95 percent sure that his average falls within 1 foot of the true value. Now estimate, using (a) and (b), what value should &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> have if he wants to make only 10 measurements with the same confidence?</li>
<li>The price of one share of stock in the Pilsdorff Beer Company (see Exercise 8.2.12) is given by <i>Y</i><sub>n</sub> on the <i>n</i>th day of the year. Finn observes that the differences <i>X</i><sub>n</sub> = <i>Y</i><sub>n+1</sub> &#x2212; <i>Y</i><sub>n</sub> appear to be independent random variables with a common distribution having mean &#x03BC; = 0 and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> = 1/4. If <i>Y</i><sub>1</sub> = 100, estimate the probability that <i>Y</i><sub>365</sub> is
<ol>
<li>&#x2265; 100.</li>
<li>&#x2265; 110.</li>
<li>&#x2265; 120.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Test your conclusions in Exercise 11 by computer simulation. First choose 364 numbers <i>X</i><sub>i</sub> with density <i>f</i>(<i>x</i>) = normal(<i>x</i>, 0, 1/4). Now form the sum <i>Y</i><sub>365</sub> = 100 + <i>X</i><sub>1</sub> + <i>X</i><sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + <i>X</i><sub>364</sub>, and repeat this experiment 200 times. Make up a bar graph on [50, 150] of the results, superimposing the graph of the approximating normal density. What does this graph say about your answers in Exercise 11?</li>
<li>Physicists say that particles in a long tube are constantly moving back and forth along the tube, each with a velocity <i>V</i><sub>k</sub> (in cm/sec) at any given moment that is normally distributed, with mean &#x03BC; = 0 and variance &#x03C3;<sup>2</sup> = 1. Suppose there are 10<sup>20</sup> particles in the tube.
<ol>
<li>Find the mean and variance of the average velocity of the particles.</li>
<li>What is the probability that the average velocity is &#x2265; 10<sup>&#x2212;9</sup> cm/sec?</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>An astronomer makes <i>n</i> measurements of the distance between Jupiter and a particular one of its moons. Experience with the instruments used leads her to believe that for the proper units the measurements will be normally distributed with mean <i>d</i>, the true distance, and variance 16. She performs a series of <i>n</i> measurements. Let
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>X</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
</mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
be the average of these measurements.
<ol>
<li>Show that
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac><mn>8</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<mi>d</mi>
<mo>&#x2264;</mo>
<msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>8</mn><msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt></mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mo>&#x2248;</mo>
<mn>.95</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
</li>
<li>When nine measurements were taken, the average of the distances turned out to be 23.2 units. Putting the observed values in (a) gives the 95 percent confidence interval for the unknown distance <i>d</i>. Compute this interval.</li>
<li>Why not say in (b) more simply that the probability is .95 that the value of <i>d</i> lies in the computed confidence interval?</li>
<li>What changes would you make in the above procedure if you wanted to compute a 99 percent confidence interval?</li>
</ol>
</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_364">364</target>
<li>Plot a bar graph similar to that in Figure 9.10 for the heights of the mid-parents in Galton&#x2019;s data as given in Appendix B and compare this bar graph to the appropriate normal curve.</li>
</ol>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</chapter>