<chapter id="chap3">
<label>Chapter 3</label>
<title>Combinatorics</title>
<sec id="sec_3_1">
<label>3.1</label>
<title>Permutations</title>
<p role="noindent">Many problems in probability theory require that we count the number of ways that a particular event can occur. For this, we study the topics of permutations and combinations. We consider permutations in this section and combinations in the next section.</p>
<p role="indent">Before discussing permutations, it is useful to introduce a general counting technique that will enable us to solve a variety of counting problems, including the problem of counting the number of possible permutations of n objects.</p>
<sec id="sec_CountingProblems">
<title>Counting Problems</title>
<p role="noindent">Consider an experiment that takes place in several stages and is such that the number of outcomes m at the nth stage is independent of the outcomes of the previous stages. The number m may be different for different stages. We want to count the number of ways that the entire experiment can be carried out.</p>
<sec id="example3.1">
<label>Example 3.1</label>
<p role="noindent">You are eating at Emile's restaurant and the waiter informs you that you have (a) two choices for appetizers: soup or juice; (b) three for the main course: a meat, fish, or vegetable dish; and (c) two for dessert: ice cream or cake. How many possible choices do you have for your complete meal? We illustrate the possible meals by a tree diagram shown in Figure 3.1. Your menu is decided in three stages-at each stage the number of possible choices does not depend on what is chosen in the previous stages: two choices at the first stage, three at the second, and two at the third. From the tree diagram we see that the total number of choices is the product of the number of choices at each stage. In this examples we have 2 · 3 · 2 = 12 possible menus. Our menu example is an example of the following general counting technique. ?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_CountingTechnique">
<title>A Counting Technique</title>
<p role="noindent">A task is to be carried out in a sequence of r stages. There are n<sub>1</sub> ways to carry out the first stage; for each of these n<sub>1</sub> ways, there are n<sub>2</sub> ways to carry out the second stage; for each of these n<sub>2</sub> ways, there are n<sub>3</sub> ways to carry out the third stage, and so forth. Then the total number of ways in which the entire task can be accomplished is given by the product</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>N</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<msub><mi>n</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mo>·</mo>
<msub><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<msub><mi>n</mi><mi>r</mi></msub>
</mrow>
</math>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_85">85</target>
<sec id="sec_TreeDiagrams">
<title>Tree Diagrams</title>
<p role="noindent">It will often be useful to use a tree diagram when studying probabilities of events relating to experiments that take place in stages and for which we are given the probabilities for the outcomes at each stage. For example, assume that the owner of Emile's restaurant has observed that 80 percent of his customers choose the soup for an appetizer and 20 percent choose juice. Of those who choose soup, 50 percent choose meat, 30 percent choose fish, and 20 percent choose the vegetable dish. Of those who choose juice for an appetizer, 30 percent choose meat, 40 percent choose fish, and 30 percent choose the vegetable dish. We can use this to estimate the probabilities at the first two stages as indicated on the tree diagram of Figure 3.2.</p>
<p role="indent">We choose for our sample space the set Ω of all possible paths ? = ?<sub>1</sub>, ?<sub>2</sub>, . . . , ?<sub>6</sub> through the tree. How should we assign our probability distribution? For example, what probability should we assign to the customer choosing soup and then the meat? If 8/10 of the customers choose soup and then 1/2 of these choose meat, a proportion 8/10 · 1/2 = 4/10 of the customers choose soup and then meat. This suggests choosing our probability distribution for each path through the tree to be the product of the probabilities at each of the stages along the path. This results in the probability distribution for the sample points ? indicated in Figure 3.2. (Note that m(?<sub>1</sub>) + · · · + m(?<sub>6</sub>) = 1.) From this we see, for example, that the probability that a customer chooses meat is m(?<sub>1</sub>) + m(?<sub>4</sub>) = .46.</p>
<p role="indent">We shall say more about these tree measures when we discuss the concept of conditional probability in Chapter 4. We return now to more counting problems.</p>
<sec id="example3.2">
<label>Example 3.2</label>
<p role="noindent">We can show that there are at least two people in Columbus, Ohio, who have the same three initials. Assuming that each person has three initials, there are 26 possibilities for a person's first initial, 26 for the second, and 26 for the third. Therefore, there are 26<sup>3</sup> = 17,576 possible sets of initials. This number is smaller than the number of people living in Columbus, Ohio; hence, there must be at least two people with the same three initials. ?</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec> 
<sec id="sec_BirthdayProblem">
<title>Birthday Problem</title>
 
<sec id="example3.3">
<label>Example 3.3</label>
<title>(Birthday Problem)</title>
<p role="noindent">How many people do we need to have in a room to make it a favorable bet (probability of success greater than 1/2) that two people in the room will have the same birthday?</p>
<p role="indent">Since there are 365 possible birthdays, it is tempting to guess that we would need about 1/2 this number, or 183. You would surely win this bet. In fact, the number required for a favorable bet is only 23. To show this, we find the probability p<sub>r</sub> that, in a room with r people, there is no duplication of birthdays; we will have a favorable bet if this probability is less than one half.</p>
<p role="indent">Assume that there are 365 possible birthdays for each person (we ignore leap years). Order the people from 1 to r. For a sample point ?, we choose a possible sequence of length r of birthdays each chosen as one of the 365 possible dates. There are 365 possibilities for the first element of the sequence, and for each of these choices there are 365 for the second, and so forth, making 365<sup>r</sup> possible sequences of birthdays. We must find the number of these sequences that have no duplication of birthdays. For such a sequence, we can choose any of the 365 days for the first element, then any of the remaining 364 for the second, 363 for the third, and so forth, until we make r choices. For the rth choice, there will be 365 - r + 1 possibilities. Hence, the total number of sequences with no duplications is</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_84">84</target> 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>365</mn>
<mo>·</mo>
<mn>364</mn>
<mo>·</mo>
<mn>363</mn>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mn>365</mn>
<mo>-</mo>
<mi>r</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Thus, assuming that each sequence is equally likely,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>p</mi><mi>r</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mn>365</mn>
<mo>·</mo>
<mn>364</mn>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mn>365</mn>
<mo>-</mo>
<mi>r</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<msup><mn>365</mn><mi>r</mi></msup>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">We denote the product</p>
 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mi>r</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="inline">by (n)<sub>r</sub> (read "n down r," or "n lower r"). Thus,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msub><mi>p</mi><mi>r</mi></msub>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<msub><mo>(</mo><mn>365</mn><mo>)</mo><mi>r</mi></msub>
<msup><mo>(</mo><mn>365</mn><mo>)</mo><mi>r</mi></msup>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The program Birthday carries out this computation and prints the probabilities for r = 20 to 25. Running this program, we get the results shown in Table 3.1. As we asserted above, the probability for no duplication changes from greater than one half to less than one half as we move from 22 to 23 people. To see how unlikely it is that we would lose our bet for larger numbers of people, we have run the program again, printing out values from r = 10 to r = 100 in steps of 10. We see that in a room of 40 people the odds already heavily favor a duplication, and in a room of 100 the odds are overwhelmingly in favor of a duplication. We have assumed that birthdays are equally likely to fall on any particular day. Statistical evidence suggests that this is not true. However, it is intuitively clear (but not easy to prove) that this makes it even more likely to have a duplication with a group of 23 people. (See Exercise 19 to find out what happens on planets with more or fewer than 365 days per year.) ?</p>
<table-wrap id="table_3_1">
<label>Table 3.1</label>
<caption><p>Birthday problem.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Number of people</th>
<th>Probability that all birthdays are different</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>.5885616</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td>.5563117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td>.5243047</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>.4927028</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>.4616557</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>.4313003</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec> 
<sec id="sec_PermutationsMain">
<target target-type="page" id="page_86">86</target>
<title>Permutations</title>
<sec id="sec_PermutationDefinition">
<title>Definition</title>
 
<def id="def3.1">
<label>Definition 3.1</label>
<p role="noindent">Let A be any finite set. A permutation of A is a one-to-one mapping of A onto itself. ?</p>
</def>
<p role="indent">To specify a particular permutation we list the elements of A and, under them, show where each element is sent by the one-to-one mapping. For example, if A = {a, b, c} a possible permutation σ would be</p>
 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>σ</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="{" close="}">
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mi>a</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mi>b</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mi>c</mi></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mi>b</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mi>c</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mi>a</mi></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">By the permutation σ, a is sent to b, b is sent to c, and c is sent to a. The condition that the mapping be one-to-one means that no two elements of A are sent, by the mapping, into the same element of A.</p>
<p role="indent">We can put the elements of our set in some order and rename them 1, 2, .. . , n. Then, a typical permutation of the set A = {a<sub>1</sub>, a<sub>2</sub>, a<sub>3</sub>, a<sub>4</sub>} can be written in the form</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>σ</mi>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="{" close="}">
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>2</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>1</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>4</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mn>3</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">, indicating that a<sub>1</sub> went to a<sub>2</sub>, a<sub>2</sub> to a<sub>1</sub>, a<sub>3</sub> to a<sub>4</sub>, and a<sub>4</sub> to a<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p role="indent">If we always choose the top row to be 1 2 3 4 then, to prescribe the permutation, we need only give the bottom row, with the understanding that this tells us where 1 goes, 2 goes, and so forth, under the mapping. When this is done, the permutation is often called a rearrangement of the n objects 1, 2, 3, . . . , n. For example, all possible permutations, or rearrangements, of the numbers A = {1, 2, 3} are:</p>
<p role="indent">123, 132, 213, 231, 312, 321 .</p>
<p role="indent">It is an easy matter to count the number of possible permutations of n objects. By our general counting principle, there are n ways to assign the first element, for each of these we have n - 1 ways to assign the second object, n - 2 for the third, and so forth. This proves the following theorem.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_PermutationTheorem">
<title>Theorem 3.1: Permutations</title>
 
<thm id="thm3.1">
<label>Theorem 3.1</label>
<p role="noindent">The total number of permutations of a set A of n elements is given by</p>
 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="inline">. ?</p>
</thm>
</sec>
<p role="indent">It is sometimes helpful to consider orderings of subsets of a given set. This prompts the following definition.</p>
<sec id="sec_kPermutationDef">
<target target-type="page" id="page_89">89</target>
<title>k-Permutations</title>
 
<def id="def3.2">
<label>Definition 3.2</label>
<p role="noindent">Let A be an n-element set, and let k be an integer between 0 and n. Then a k-permutation of A is an ordered listing of a subset of A of size k. ?</p>
</def>
<p role="indent">Using the same techniques as in the last theorem, the following result is easily proved.</p>
<thm id="thm3.2">
<label>Theorem 3.2</label>
<p role="noindent">The total number of k-permutations of a set A of n elements is given by</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>?</mo>
<mo>·</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi>
<mo>-</mo>
<mi>k</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="inline">. ?</p>
</thm>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_Factorials">
<title>Factorials</title>
<p role="noindent">The number given in Theorem 3.1 is called n factorial, and is denoted by n!. The expression 0! is defined to be 1 to make certain formulas come out simpler. The first few values of this function are shown in Table 3.3. The reader will note that this function grows very rapidly.</p>
<p role="indent">The expression n! will enter into many of our calculations, and we shall need to have some estimate of its magnitude when n is large. It is clearly not practical to make exact calculations in this case. We shall instead use a result called Stirling's formula. Before stating this formula we need a definition.</p>
<def id="def3.3">
<label>Definition 3.3</label>
<p role="noindent">Let a<sub>n</sub> and b<sub>n</sub> be two sequences of numbers. We say that a<sub>n</sub> is asymptotically equal to b<sub>n</sub>, and write a<sub>n</sub> ~ b<sub>n</sub>, if</p>
 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munder>
<mi>lim</mi>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo></mo><mi>∞</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mfrac>
<msub><mi>a</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
<msub><mi>b</mi><mi>n</mi></msub>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="inline">. ?</p>
</def>
<sec id="example3.4">
<label>Example 3.4</label>
<p role="noindent">If a<sub>n</sub> = n +<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt> and b<sub>n</sub> = n then, since a<sub>n</sub>/b<sub>n</sub> = 1 + 1/<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt> and this ratio tends to 1 as n tends to infinity, we have a<sub>n</sub> ~ b<sub>n</sub>. ?</p>
</sec>
 
<thm id="thm3.3">
<label>Theorem 3.3 (Stirling's Formula)</label>
<p role="noindent">The sequence n! is asymptotically equal to</p>
 
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msqrt>
<mn>2</mn><mi>π</mi><mi>n</mi>
</msqrt>
<msup>
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo>
<mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>e</mi></mfrac>
<mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
</mrow>
</math>
 
<p role="inline">. ?</p>
</thm>
 
<p role="indent">The proof of Stirling's formula may be found in most analysis texts. Let us verify this approximation by using the computer. The program StirlingApproximations prints n!, the Stirling approximation, and, finally, the ratio of these two numbers. Sample output of this program is shown in Table 3.4. Note that, while the ratio of the numbers is getting closer to 1, the difference between the exact value and the approximation is increasing, and indeed, this difference will tend to infinity as n tends to infinity, even though the ratio tends to 1. (This was also true in our Example 3.4 where n +<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt> ~ n, but the difference is<msqrt><mi>n</mi></msqrt>.)</p>
 
<table-wrap id="table_3_3">
<label>Table 3.3</label>
<caption><p>Values of the factorial function.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>n</th>
<th>n!</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr>
<tr><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>2</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>6</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>24</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>120</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>720</td></tr>
<tr><td>7</td><td>5040</td></tr>
<tr><td>8</td><td>40320</td></tr>
<tr><td>9</td><td>362880</td></tr>
<tr><td>10</td><td>3628800</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table_3_4">
<label>Table 3.4</label>
<caption><p>Stirling approximations to the factorial function.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>n</th>
<th>n!</th>
<th>Approximation</th>
<th>Ratio</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>.922</td><td>1.084</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>1.919</td><td>1.042</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>6</td><td>5.836</td><td>1.028</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>24</td><td>23.506</td><td>1.021</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>120</td><td>118.019</td><td>1.016</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>720</td><td>710.078</td><td>1.013</td></tr>
<tr><td>7</td><td>5040</td><td>4980.396</td><td>1.011</td></tr>
<tr><td>8</td><td>40320</td><td>39902.395</td><td>1.010</td></tr>
<tr><td>9</td><td>362880</td><td>359536.873</td><td>1.009</td></tr>
<tr><td>10</td><td>3628800</td><td>3598696.619</td><td>1.008</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_RandomPermutations">
<title>Generating Random Permutations</title>
<p role="noindent">We now consider the question of generating a random permutation of the integers between 1 and n. Consider the following experiment. We start with a deck of n cards, labelled 1 through n. We choose a random card out of the deck, note its label, and put the card aside. We repeat this process until all n cards have been chosen. It is clear that each permutation of the integers from 1 to n can occur as a sequence of labels in this experiment, and that each sequence of labels is equally likely to occur. In our implementations of the computer algorithms, the above procedure is called RandomPermutation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_FixedPoints">
<title>Fixed Points</title>
<p role="noindent">There are many interesting problems that relate to properties of a permutation chosen at random from the set of all permutations of a given finite set. For example, since a permutation is a one-to-one mapping of the set onto itself, it is interesting to ask how many points are mapped onto themselves. We call such points fixed points of the mapping.</p>
<p role="indent">Let p<sub>k</sub>(n) be the probability that a random permutation of the set {1, 2, . . ., n} has exactly k fixed points. We will attempt to learn something about these probabilities using simulation. The program FixedPoints uses the procedure RandomPermutation to generate random permutations and count fixed points. The program prints the proportion of times that there are k fixed points as well as the average number of fixed points. The results of this program for 500 simulations for the cases n = 10, 20, and 30 are shown in Table 3.5. Notice the rather surprising fact that our estimates for the probabilities do not seem to depend very heavily on the number of elements in the permutation. For example, the probability that there are no fixed points, when n = 10, 20, or 30 is estimated to be between .35 and .37. We shall see later (see Example 3.12) that for n ≥ 10 the exact probabilities p<sub>n</sub>(0) are, to six decimal place accuracy, equal to 1/e ≈ .367879. Thus, for all practical purposes, after n = 10 the probability that a random permutation of the set {1, 2, . . ., n} has no fixed points does not depend upon n. These simulations also suggest that the average number of fixed points is close to 1. It can be shown (see Example 6.8) that the average is exactly equal to 1 for all n.</p>
<p role="indent">More picturesque versions of the fixed-point problem are: You have arranged the books on your book shelf in alphabetical order by author and they get returned to your shelf at random; what is the probability that exactly k of the books end up in their correct position? (The library problem.) In a restaurant n hats are checked and they are hopelessly scrambled; what is the probability that no one gets his own hat back? (The hat check problem.) In the Historical Remarks at the end of this section, we give one method for solving the hat check problem exactly. Another method is given in Example 3.12.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_90">90</target> 
<table-wrap id="table_3_5">
<label>Table 3.5</label>
<caption><p>Fixed point distributions.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Number of fixed points</th>
<th colspan="3">Fraction of permutations</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>n = 10</th>
<th>n = 20</th>
<th>n = 30</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0</td><td>.362</td><td>.370</td><td>.358</td></tr>
<tr><td>1</td><td>.368</td><td>.396</td><td>.358</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>.202</td><td>.164</td><td>.192</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>.052</td><td>.060</td><td>.070</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>.012</td><td>.008</td><td>.020</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>.004</td><td>.002</td><td>.002</td></tr>
<tr><td>Average number of fixed points</td><td>.996</td><td>.948</td><td>1.042</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec> 
<sec id="sec_Records">
<title>Records</title>
<p role="noindent">Here is another interesting probability problem that involves permutations. Estimates for the amount of measured snow in inches in Hanover, New Hampshire, in the ten years from 1974 to 1983 are shown in Table 3.6. Suppose we have started keeping records in 1974. Then our first year's snowfall could be considered a record snowfall starting from this year. A new record was established in 1975; the next record was established in 1977, and there were no new records established after this year. Thus, in this ten-year period, there were three records established: 1974, 1975, and 1977. The question that we ask is: How many records should we expect to be established in such a ten-year period? We can count the number of records in terms of a permutation as follows: We number the years from 1 to 10. The actual amounts of snowfall are not important but their relative sizes are. We can, therefore, change the numbers measuring snowfalls to numbers 1 to 10 by replacing the smallest number by 1, the next smallest by 2, and so forth. (We assume that there are no ties.) For our example, we obtain the data shown in Table 3.7.</p>
<p role="indent">This gives us a permutation of the numbers from 1 to 10 and, from this permutation, we can read off the records; they are in years 1, 2, and 4. Thus we can define records for a permutation as follows:</p>
<def id="def3.4">
<label>Definition 3.4</label>
<p role="noindent">Let σ be a permutation of the set {1, 2, . . ., n}. Then i is a record of σ if either i = 1 or σ(j) &lt; σ(i) for every j = 1, . . ., i - 1. ?</p>
</def>
<p role="indent">Now if we regard all rankings of snowfalls over an n-year period to be equally likely (and allow no ties), we can estimate the probability that there will be k records in n years as well as the average number of records by simulation. We have written a program Records that counts the number of records in randomly chosen permutations. We have run this program for the cases n = 10, 20, 30. For n = 10 the average number of records is 2.968, for 20 it is 3.656, and for 30 it is 3.960. We see now that the averages increase, but very slowly. We shall see later (see Example 6.11) that the average number is approximately log n. Since log 10 = 2.3, log 20 = 3, and log 30 = 3.4, this is consistent with the results of our simulations.</p>
<p role="indent">As remarked earlier, we shall be able to obtain formulas for exact results of certain problems of the above type. However, only minor changes in the problem make this impossible. The power of simulation is that minor changes in a problem do not make the simulation much more difficult. (See Exercise 20 for an interesting variation of the hat check problem.)</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_91">91</target>
<table-wrap id="table_3_6">
<label>Table 3.6</label>
<caption><p>Snowfall in Hanover.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Date</th>
<th>Snowfall in inches</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>1974</td><td>75</td></tr>
<tr><td>1975</td><td>88</td></tr>
<tr><td>1976</td><td>72</td></tr>
<tr><td>1977</td><td>110</td></tr>
<tr><td>1978</td><td>85</td></tr>
<tr><td>1979</td><td>30</td></tr>
<tr><td>1980</td><td>55</td></tr>
<tr><td>1981</td><td>86</td></tr>
<tr><td>1982</td><td>51</td></tr>
<tr><td>1983</td><td>64</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table_3_7">
<label>Table 3.7</label>
<caption><p>Ranking of total snowfall.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Year</th>
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th>
<th>9</th>
<th>10</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<th>Ranking</th>
<td>6</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_3_2">
<label>3.2</label>
<title>Combinations</title>
<p role="noindent">Having mastered permutations, we now consider combinations. Let U be a set with n elements; we want to count the number of distinct subsets of the set U that have exactly j elements. The empty set and the set U are considered to be subsets of U. The empty set is usually denoted by φ.</p>
<sec id="sec_3_2">
<label>3.2</label>
<title>Combinations</title>
<fig id="fig_3_7">
<label>Figure 3.7</label>
<caption><p>The power curve.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure3_7.jpg"/>
</fig>
<sec id="theorem_3_7">
<title>Binomial Theorem</title>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>Theorem 3.7 (Binomial Theorem)</bold> The quantity
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo><msup><mrow/><mi>n</mi></msup></mrow></math>
can be expressed in the form</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</munderover>
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0">
<mi>n</mi>
<mi>j</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
<msup><mi>a</mi><mi>j</mi></msup>
<msup><mi>b</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>j</mi></mrow></msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
<italic>Proof.</italic> To see that this expansion is correct, write
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<munder>
<munder>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</munder>
</munder>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">When we multiply this out we will have a sum of terms each of which results froma choice of an<i>a</i> or<i>b</i> for each of<i>n</i> factors. When we choose<i>j</i><i>a</i>'s and
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>
<i>b</i>'s, we obtain a term of the form
<math display="inline"><mrow><msup><mi>a</mi><mi>j</mi></msup><msup><mi>b</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>j</mi></mrow></msup></mrow></math>.
To determine such a term, we have to specify<i>j</i> of the<i>n</i> terms in the product
from which we choose the<i>a</i>. This can be done in
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
</math>
ways. Thus, collecting these terms in the sum contributes a term
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup><mi>a</mi><mi>j</mi></msup>
<msup><mi>b</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>j</mi></mrow></msup>
</mrow>
</math>. &#x25A1;
</p>
<p role="indent">For example, we have</p>
<math display="block">
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd columnalign="right">
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>0</mn></msup>
</mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left"><mn>1</mn></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd columnalign="right">
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>1</mn></msup>
</mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left"><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd columnalign="right">
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup>
</mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left">
<msup><mi>a</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>a</mi><mi>b</mi><mo>+</mo><msup><mi>b</mi><mn>2</mn></msup>
</mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd columnalign="right">
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>3</mn></msup>
</mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left">
<msup><mi>a</mi><mn>3</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><mn>3</mn><msup><mi>a</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi>b</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>3</mn><mi>a</mi><msup><mi>b</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><msup><mi>b</mi><mn>3</mn></msup>
</mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
<p role="indent">We see here that the coefficients of successive powers do indeed yield Pascal's triangle.</p>
</sec>

<sec id="corollary_3_1">
<title>Corollary</title>
<p role="noindent"><bold>Corollary 3.1</bold> The sum of the elements in the<i>n</i>th row of Pascal's triangle is
<math display="inline"><msup><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></msup></math>.If the elements in the<i>n</i>th row of Pascal's triangle are added with alternating signs,the sum is 0.</p>
<p role="indent"><i>Proof.</i> The first statement in the corollary follows from the fact that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>0</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>1</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and the second from the fact that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>0</mn>
<mo>=</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>0</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>1</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">&#x25A1;</p>
<p role="indent">The first statement of the corollary tells us that the number of subsets of a setof<i>n</i> elements is<math display="inline"><msup><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></msup></math>. We shall use the second statement in our next application ofthe binomial theorem.</p>
<p role="indent">We have seen that, when<i>A</i> and<i>B</i> are any two events (cf. Section 1.2),</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>&#x222A;</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>A</mi><mo>&#x2229;</mo><mi>B</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">We now extend this theorem to a more general version, which will enable us to findthe probability that at least one of a number of events occurs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_inclusion_exclusion">
<title>Inclusion-Exclusion Principle</title>
<p role="noindent"><bold>Theorem 3.8</bold> Let<i>P</i> be a probability distribution on a sample space &#x03A9;, and let
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>{</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x2026;</mo><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>}</mo></mrow></math>be a finite set of events. Then</p>
<math display="block" id="eq_3_3">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>&#x222A;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>&#x222A;</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>&#x222A;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>i</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</munderover>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<munder>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>&lt;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<munder>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>&lt;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>&lt;</mo><mi>k</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">That is, to find the probability that at least one of<i>n</i> events<i>A<sub>i</sub></i> occurs, first addthe probability of each event, then subtract the probabilities of all possible two-wayintersections, add the probability of all three-way intersections, and so forth.</p>
<p role="indent"><i>Proof.</i> If the outcome &#x03C9; occurs in at least one of the events<i>A<sub>i</sub></i>, its probability isadded exactly once by the left side of Equation 3.3. We must show that it is addedexactly once by the right side of Equation 3.3. Assume that &#x03C9; is in exactly<i>k</i> of thesets. Then its probability is added<i>k</i> times in the first term, subtracted
<math display="inline">
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
</math>
times in the second, added
<math display="inline">
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>3</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
</math>
times in the third term, and so forth. Thus, the total numberof times that it is added is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>1</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>3</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>k</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mi>k</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">But</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>0</mn>
<mo>=</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>k</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow>
<mi>k</mi>
</munderover>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>j</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>0</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>k</mi>
</munderover>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_105">105</target>
<p role="indent">Hence,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mn>0</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>k</mi>
</munderover>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>k</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">If the outcome &#x03C9; is not in any of the events<i>A<sub>i</sub></i>, then it is not counted on either sideof the equation. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_hat_check">
<title>Hat Check Problem</title>
<sec id="example_3_12">
<label>Example 3.12</label>
<p role="noindent">We return to the hat check problem discussed in Section 3.1, thatis, the problem of finding the probability that a random permutation contains atleast one fixed point. Recall that a permutation is a one-to-one map of a set
<math display="inline">
<mrow><mi>A</mi><mo>=</mo><mo>{</mo><msub><mi>a</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>a</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x2026;</mo><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>a</mi><mi>n</mi></msub><mo>}</mo></mrow>
</math>
onto itself. Let<i>A<sub>i</sub></i> be the event that the<i>i</i>th element<i>a<sub>i</sub></i> remains
fixed under this map. If we require that<i>a<sub>i</sub></i> is fixed, then the map of the remaining
<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math>
elements provides an arbitrary permutation of
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>
objects. Since there are
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow></math>
such permutations,
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mo>/</mo>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mo>=</mo>
<mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow>
</mrow>
</math>.
Since there are<i>n</i> choices for<i>a<sub>i</sub></i>, the first term of Equation 3.3 is 1. In the same way, to have a particularpair<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>a</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>a</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>fixed, we can choose any permutation of the remaining<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></math> elements;there are<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow></math> such choices and thus</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
The number of terms of this form in the right side of Equation 3.3 is
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Hence, the second term of Equation 3.3 is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>&#x22C5;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
Similarly, for any specific three events<i>A<sub>i</sub></i>,<i>A<sub>j</sub></i>,<i>A<sub>k</sub></i>,
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>j</mi></msub><mo>&#x2229;</mo><msub><mi>A</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and the number of such terms is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>3</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
making the third term of Equation 3.3 equal to 1/3!. Continuing in this way, we
obtain
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mtext>at least one fixed point</mtext><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mtext>no fixed point</mtext><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_106">106</target>

<table-wrap id="table_3_9">
<label>Table 3.9</label>
<caption><p>Hat check problem.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>n</entry>
<entry>Probability that no one gets his own hat back</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>3</entry><entry>.333333</entry></row>
<row><entry>4</entry><entry>.375</entry></row>
<row><entry>5</entry><entry>.366667</entry></row>
<row><entry>6</entry><entry>.368056</entry></row>
<row><entry>7</entry><entry>.367857</entry></row>
<row><entry>8</entry><entry>.367882</entry></row>
<row><entry>9</entry><entry>.367879</entry></row>
<row><entry>10</entry><entry>.367879</entry></row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>

<p role="indent">From calculus we learn that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<msup><mi>e</mi><mi>x</mi></msup>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>+</mo>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<msup><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<msup><mi>x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<msup><mi>x</mi><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
Thus, if<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>x</mi><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math>, we have
</p>
<math display="block">
<mtable>
<mtr>
<mtd columnalign="right">
<msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
</mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left">
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow></mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfrac>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>+</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
</mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd/>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd columnalign="left">
<mn>.3678794</mn>
<mo>.</mo>
</mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
<p role="indent">Therefore, the probability that there is no fixed point, i.e., that none of the<i>n</i> peoplegets his own hat back, is equal to the sum of the first<i>n</i> terms in the expression for
<math display="inline"><msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup></math>.This series converges very fast. Calculating the partial sums for<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>3</mn></mrow></math> to 10gives the data in Table 3.9.</p>
<p role="indent">After<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>9</mn></mrow></math> the probabilities are essentially the same to six significant figures.Interestingly, the probability of no fixed point alternately increases and decreasesas<i>n</i> increases. Finally, we note that our exact results are in good agreement withour simulations reported in the previous section. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_choosing_sample_space">
<title>Choosing a Sample Space</title>
<p role="noindent">We now have some of the tools needed to accurately describe sample spaces andto assign probability functions to those sample spaces. Nevertheless, in some cases,the description and assignment process is somewhat arbitrary. Of course, it is tobe hoped that the description of the sample space and the subsequent assignmentof a probability function will yield a model which accurately predicts what wouldhappen if the experiment were actually carried out. As the following examples show,there are situations in which &#x201C;reasonable&#x201D; descriptions of the sample space do notproduce a model which fits the data.</p>
<p role="indent">In Feller's book,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref> a pair of models is given which describe arrangements ofcertain kinds of elementary particles, such as photons and protons. It turns out thatexperiments have shown that certain types of elementary particles exhibit behavior</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_107">107</target>
<p role="indent">which is accurately described by one model, called &#x201C;Bose-Einstein statistics,&#x201D; whileother types of elementary particles can be modelled using &#x201C;Fermi-Dirac statistics.&#x201D;Feller says:</p>
<p role="indent">We have here an instructive example of the impossibility of selecting orjustifying probability models by<i>a priori</i> arguments. In fact, no purereasoning could tell that photons and protons would not obey the sameprobability laws.</p>
<p role="indent">We now give some examples of this description and assignment process.</p>

<sec id="example_3_13">
<label>Example 3.13</label>
<p role="noindent">In the quantum mechanical model of the helium atom, variousparameters can be used to classify the energy states of the atom. In the tripletspin state (<i>S</i> = 1) with orbital angular momentum 1 (<i>L</i> = 1), there are threepossibilities, 0, 1, or 2, for the total angular momentum (<i>J</i>). (It is not assumed thatthe reader knows what any of this means; in fact, the example is more illustrativeif the reader does not know anything about quantum mechanics.) We would liketo assign probabilities to the three possibilities for<i>J</i>. The reader is undoubtedlyresisting the idea of assigning the probability of 1/3 to each of these outcomes. Sheshould now ask herself why she is resisting this assignment. The answer is probablybecause she does not have any &#x201C;intuition&#x201D; (i.e., experience) about the way in whichhelium atoms behave. In fact, in this example, the probabilities 1/9, 3/9, and5/9 are assigned by the theory. The theory gives these assignments because thesefrequencies were observed in experiments and further parameters were developed inthe theory to allow these frequencies to be predicted. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>

<sec id="example_3_14">
<label>Example 3.14</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose two pennies are flipped once each. There are several &#x201C;reasonable&#x201D; ways to describe the sample space. One way is to count the number ofheads in the outcome; in this case, the sample space can be written
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>{</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>}</mo></mrow></math>.Another description of the sample space is the set of all ordered pairs of<i>H</i>'s and<i>T</i>'s,i.e.,</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>{</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>H</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>H</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>H</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>H</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>}</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Both of these descriptions are accurate ones, but it is easy to see that (at most) oneof these, if assigned a constant probability function, can claim to accurately modelreality. In this case, as opposed to the preceding example, the reader will probablysay that the second description, with each outcome being assigned a probability of1/4, is the &#x201C;right&#x201D; description. This conviction is due to experience; there is noproof that this is the way reality works. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<p role="indent">The reader is also referred to Exercise 26 for another example of this process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_historical_remarks_3_2">
<title>Historical Remarks</title>
<p role="noindent">The binomial coefficients have a long and colorful history leading up to Pascal's<i>Treatise on the Arithmetical Triangle</i>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref> where Pascal developed many important</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_108">108</target>
<table-wrap id="table_3_10">
<label>Table 3.10</label>
<caption><p>Pascal's triangle.</p></caption>
<table>
<tbody>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>9</entry><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>21</entry><entry>28</entry><entry>36</entry><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>35</entry><entry>56</entry><entry>84</entry><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>35</entry><entry>70</entry><entry>126</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>21</entry><entry>56</entry><entry>126</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>28</entry><entry>84</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>36</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>9</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>1</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table_3_11">
<label>Table 3.11</label>
<caption><p>Figurate numbers.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<row>
<th/>
<entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>9</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>natural numbers</entry>
<entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>9</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>triangular numbers</entry>
<entry>1</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>21</entry><entry>28</entry><entry>36</entry><entry>45</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>tetrahedral numbers</entry>
<entry>1</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>35</entry><entry>56</entry><entry>84</entry><entry>120</entry><entry>165</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>

<p role="indent">properties of these numbers. This history is set forth in the book<i>Pascal's Arithmetical Triangle</i> by A. W. F. Edwards.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref> Pascal wrote his triangle in the formshown in Table 3.10.</p>
<p role="indent">Edwards traces three different ways that the binomial coefficients arose. Herefers to these as the<i>figurate numbers</i>, the<i>combinatorial numbers</i>, and the<i>binomialnumbers</i>. They are all names for the same thing (which we have called binomialcoefficients) but that they are all the same was not appreciated until the sixteenthcentury.</p>
<p role="indent">The<i>figurate numbers</i> date back to the Pythagorean interest in number patterns around 540 BC. The Pythagoreans considered, for example, triangular patternsshown in Figure 3.8. The sequence of numbers</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>10</mn><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x2026;</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">obtained as the number of points in each triangle are called<i>triangular numbers</i>.From the triangles it is clear that the<i>n</i>th triangular number is simply the sum ofthe first<i>n</i> integers. The<i>tetrahedral numbers</i> are the sums of the triangular numbersand were obtained by the Greek mathematicians Theon and Nicomachus at thebeginning of the second century BC. The tetrahedral number 10, for example, hasthe geometric representation shown in Figure 3.9. The first three types of figuratenumbers can be represented in tabular form as shown in Table 3.11.</p>
<p role="indent">These numbers provide the first four rows of Pascal's triangle, but the table wasnot to be completed in the West until the sixteenth century.</p>
<p role="indent">
In the East, Hindu mathematicians began to encounter the binomial coefficients
in combinatorial problems. Bhaskara in his<i>Lilavati</i> of 1150 gave a rule to find the
</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_109">109</target>
<fig id="fig_3_8">
<label>Figure 3.8</label>
<caption><p>Pythagorean triangular patterns.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure3_8.jpg"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig_3_9">
<label>Figure 3.9</label>
<caption><p>Geometric representation of the tetrahedral number 10.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure3_9.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_110">110</target>
<table-wrap id="table_3_12">
<label>Table 3.12</label>
<caption><p>Outcomes for the roll of two dice.</p></caption>
<table>
<tbody>
<row><entry>11</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>12</entry><entry>22</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>13</entry><entry>23</entry><entry>33</entry><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>14</entry><entry>24</entry><entry>34</entry><entry>44</entry><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>15</entry><entry>25</entry><entry>35</entry><entry>45</entry><entry>55</entry><td/></row>
<row><entry>16</entry><entry>26</entry><entry>36</entry><entry>46</entry><entry>56</entry><entry>66</entry></row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="indent">
number of medicinal preparations using 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 possible ingredients.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref> His
rule is equivalent to our formula
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>r</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<msub><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>r</mi></msub>
<mrow><mi>r</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">The binomial numbers as coefficients of
<math display="inline"><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup></math>appeared in the works of mathematicians in China around 1100. There are references about this time to &#x201C;thetabulation system for unlocking binomial coefficients.&#x201D; The triangle to provide thecoefficients up to the eighth power is given by Chu Shih-chieh in a book writtenaround 1303 (see Figure 3.10).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref> The original manuscript of Chu's book has beenlost, but copies have survived. Edwards notes that there is an error in this copy ofChu's triangle. Can you find it? (<i>Hint</i>: Two numbers which should be equal arenot.) Other copies do not show this error.</p>
<p role="indent">The first appearance of Pascal's triangle in the West seems to have come fromcalculations of Tartaglia in calculating the number of possible ways that<i>n</i> dicemight turn up.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref> For one die the answer is clearly 6. For two dice the possibilitiesmay be displayed as shown in Table 3.12.</p>
<p role="indent">Displaying them this way suggests the sixth triangular number
<math display="inline">
<mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>+</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>=</mo><mn>21</mn></mrow>
</math>
for the throw of 2 dice. Tartaglia &#x201C;on the first day of Lent, 1523, inVerona, having thought about the problem all night,&#x201D;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref> realized that the extensionof the figurate table gave the answers for<i>n</i> dice. The problem had suggested itselfto Tartaglia from watching people casting their own horoscopes by means of a<i>Bookof Fortune</i>, selecting verses by a process which included noting the numbers on thefaces of three dice. The 56 ways that three dice can fall were set out on each page.The way the numbers were written in the book did not suggest the connection withfigurate numbers, but a method of enumeration similar to the one we used for 2dice does. Tartaglia's table was not published until 1556.</p>
<p role="indent">A table for the binomial coefficients was published in 1554 by the German mathematician Stifel.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref> Pascal's triangle appears also in Cardano's<i>Opus novum</i> of 1570.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref></p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_111">111</target>
<fig id="fig_3_10">
<label>Figure 3.10</label>
<caption>
<p>Chu Shih-chieh's triangle. [From J. Needham,<i>Science and Civilizationin China</i>, vol. 3 (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1959), p. 135. Reprintedwith permission.]</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="figure3_10.jpg"/>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_112">112</target>
<p role="indent">Cardano was interested in the problem of finding the number of ways to choose<i>r</i>objects out of<i>n</i>. Thus by the time of Pascal's work, his triangle had appeared asa result of looking at the figurate numbers, the combinatorial numbers, and thebinomial numbers, and the fact that all three were the same was presumably prettywell understood.</p>
<p role="indent">Pascal's interest in the binomial numbers came from his letters with Fermatconcerning a problem known as the<i>problem of points</i>. This problem, and thecorrespondence between Pascal and Fermat, were discussed in Chapter 1. Thereader will recall that this problem can be described as follows: Two players A andB are playing a sequence of games and the first player to win<i>n</i> games wins thematch. It is desired to find the probability that A wins the match at a time whenA has won<i>a</i> games and B has won<i>b</i> games. (See Exercises 4.1.40&#x2013;4.1.42.)</p>
<p role="indent">Pascal solved the problem by backward induction, much the way we would dotoday in writing a computer program for its solution. He referred to the combinatorial method of Fermat which proceeds as follows: If A needs<i>c</i> games and B needs
<i>d</i> games to win, we require that the players continue to play until they have played
<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>d</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math>games. The winner in this extended series will be the same as the winnerin the original series. The probability that A wins in the extended series and hencein the original series is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>c</mi></mrow>
<mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>d</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</munderover>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msup><mn>2</mn><mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>d</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
</mfrac>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0">
<mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>d</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>r</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Even at the time of the letters Pascal seemed to understand this formula.</p>
<p role="indent">Suppose that the first player to win<i>n</i> games wins the match, and suppose thateach player has put up a stake of<i>x</i>. Pascal studied the value of winning a particulargame. By this he meant the increase in the expected winnings of the winner of theparticular game under consideration. He showed that the value of the first game is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><mn>5</mn>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
<mrow>
<mn>2</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><mn>6</mn>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</mfrac>
<mi>x</mi>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">His proof of this seems to use Fermat's formula and the fact that the above ratio ofproducts of odd to products of even numbers is equal to the probability of exactly<i>n</i> heads in<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> tosses of a coin. (See Exercise 39.)</p>
<p role="indent">Pascal presented Fermat with the table shown in Table 3.13. He states:</p>
<p>You will see as always, that the value of the first game is equal to thatof the second which is easily shown by combinations. You will see, inthe same way, that the numbers in the first line are always increasing;so also are those in the second; and those in the third. But those in thefourth line are decreasing, and those in the fifth, etc. This seems odd.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref></p>
<p role="indent">The student can pursue this question further using the computer and Pascal'sbackward iteration method for computing the expected payoff at any point in theseries.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_113">113</target>
<table-wrap id="table_3_13">
<label>Table 3.13</label>
<caption><p>Pascal's solution for the problem of points.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<row>
<th/>
<th colspan="6">if each one staken 256 in</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>From my opponent's 256</entry>
<entry>6 games</entry>
<entry>5 games</entry>
<entry>4 games</entry>
<entry>3 games</entry>
<entry>2 games</entry>
<entry>1 game</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>positions I get, for the</entry>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>1st game</entry><entry>63</entry><entry>70</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>96</entry><entry>128</entry><entry>256</entry></row>
<row><entry>2nd game</entry><entry>63</entry><entry>70</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>96</entry><entry>128</entry><td/></row>
<row><entry>3rd game</entry><entry>56</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>64</entry><entry>64</entry><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>4th game</entry><entry>42</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>32</entry><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>5th game</entry><entry>24</entry><entry>16</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
<row><entry>6th game</entry><entry>8</entry><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="indent">In his treatise, Pascal gave a formal proof of Fermat's combinatorial formula aswell as proofs of many other basic properties of binomial numbers. Many of hisproofs involved induction and represent some of the first proofs by this method.His book brought together all the different aspects of the numbers in the Pascaltriangle as known in 1654, and, as Edwards states, &#x201C;That the Arithmetical Triangleshould bear Pascal's name cannot be disputed.&#x201D;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref></p>
<p role="indent">The first serious study of the binomial distribution was undertaken by JamesBernoulli in his<i>Ars Conjectandi</i> published in 1713.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref> We shall return to this workin the historical remarks in Chapter 8.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_exercises_3_2">
<title>Exercises</title>
<p role="noindent"><bold>1</bold> Compute the following:</p>
<p role="indent">(a)<math display="inline"><mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>6</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></mfenced></math></p>
<p role="indent">(b)<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>.2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math></p>
<p role="indent">(c)<math display="inline"><mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>7</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mfenced></math></p>
<p role="indent">(d)<math display="inline"><mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>26</mn><mn>26</mn></mfrac></mfenced></math></p>
<p role="indent">(e)<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>.2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math></p>
<p role="indent">(f)<math display="inline"><mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>6</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mfenced></math></p>
<p role="indent">(g)<math display="inline"><mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>10</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></mfenced></math></p>
<p role="indent">(h)<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>8</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>.3</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow></math></p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>2</bold> In how many ways can we choose five people from a group of ten to form acommittee?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>3</bold> How many seven-element subsets are there in a set of nine elements?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>4</bold> Using the relation Equation 3.1 write a program to compute Pascal's triangle,putting the results in a matrix. Have your program print the triangle for
<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>10</mn></mrow></math>.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_114">114</target>
<p role="noindent"><bold>5</bold> Use the program<bold>BinomialProbabilities</bold> to find the probability that, in 100tosses of a fair coin, the number of heads that turns up lies between 35 and65, between 40 and 60, and between 45 and 55.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>6</bold> Charles claims that he can distinguish between beer and ale 75 percent of thetime. Ruth bets that he cannot and, in fact, just guesses. To settle this, a betis made: Charles is to be given ten small glasses, each having been filled withbeer or ale, chosen by tossing a fair coin. He wins the bet if he gets seven ormore correct. Find the probability that Charles wins if he has the ability thathe claims. Find the probability that Ruth wins if Charles is guessing.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>7</bold> Show that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac><mi>p</mi><mi>q</mi></mfrac>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0">
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>j</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
for<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math>. Use this fact to determine the value or values of<i>j</i> which give
<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math> its greatest value.<i>Hint</i>: Consider the successive ratios as<i>j</i> increases.
</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>8</bold> A die is rolled 30 times. What is the probability that a 6 turns up exactly 5times? What is the most probable number of times that a 6 will turn up?</p>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>9</bold> Find integers<i>n</i> and<i>r</i> such that the following equation is true:</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>13</mn><mn>5</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>2</mn>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>13</mn><mn>6</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>13</mn><mn>7</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>r</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent"><bold>10</bold> In a ten-question true-false exam, find the probability that a student gets agrade of 70 percent or better by guessing. Answer the same question if thetest has 30 questions, and if the test has 50 questions.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>11</bold> A restaurant offers apple and blueberry pies and stocks an equal number ofeach kind of pie. Each day ten customers request pie. They choose, withequal probabilities, one of the two kinds of pie. How many pieces of each kindof pie should the owner provide so that the probability is about .95 that eachcustomer gets the pie of his or her own choice?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>12</bold> A poker hand is a set of 5 cards randomly chosen from a deck of 52 cards.Find the probability of a</p>
<p role="indent">(a) royal flush (ten, jack, queen, king, ace in a single suit).</p>
<p role="indent">(b) straight flush (five in a sequence in a single suit, but not a royal flush).</p>
<p role="indent">(c) four of a kind (four cards of the same face value).</p>
<p role="indent">(d) full house (one pair and one triple, each of the same face value).</p>
<p role="indent">(e) flush (five cards in a single suit but not a straight or royal flush).</p>
<p role="indent">(f) straight (five cards in a sequence, not all the same suit). (Note that instraights, an ace counts high or low.)</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>13</bold> If a set has<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> elements, show that it has more subsets with<i>n</i> elements thanwith any other number of elements.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_115">115</target>
<p role="noindent"><bold>14</bold> Let<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mn>.5</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math> be the probability that in<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> tosses of a fair coin exactly<i>n</i> headsturn up. Using Stirling's formula (Theorem 3.3), show that
<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mn>.5</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>&#x223C;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><msqrt><mrow><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>n</mi></mrow></msqrt></mrow></math>.Use the program<bold>BinomialProbabilities</bold> to compare this with theexact value for<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>10</mn></mrow></math> to 25.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>15</bold> A baseball player, Smith, has a batting average of .300 and in a typical gamecomes to bat three times. Assume that Smith's hits in a game can be considered to be a Bernoulli trials process with probability .3 for success. Find theprobability that Smith gets 0, 1, 2, and 3 hits.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>16</bold> The Siwash University football team plays eight games in a season, winningthree, losing three, and ending two in a tie. Show that the number of waysthat this can happen is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>8</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mn>5</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mn>8</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>!</mo><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent"><bold>17</bold> Using the technique of Exercise 16, show that the number of ways that onecan put<i>n</i> different objects into three boxes with<i>a</i> in the first,<i>b</i> in the second,and<i>c</i> in the third is<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo><mo>/</mo><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>!</mo><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mi>b</mi><mo>!</mo><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mi>c</mi><mo>!</mo><mo>)</mo></mrow></math>.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>18</bold> Baumgartner, Prosser, and Crowell are grading a calculus exam. There is atrue-false question with ten parts. Baumgartner notices that one student hasonly two out of the ten correct and remarks, &#x201C;The student was not even brightenough to have flipped a coin to determine his answers.&#x201D; &#x201C;Not so clear,&#x201D; saysProsser. &#x201C;With 340 students I bet that if they all flipped coins to determinetheir answers there would be at least one exam with two or fewer answercorrect.&#x201D; Crowell says, &#x201C;I'm with Prosser. In fact, I bet that we should expectat least one exam in which no answer is correct if everyone is just guessing.&#x201D;Who is right in all of this?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>19</bold> A gin hand consists of 10 cards from a deck of 52 cards. Find the probabilitythat a gin hand has</p>
<p role="indent">(a) all 10 cards of the same suit.</p>
<p role="indent">(b) exactly 4 cards in one suit and 3 in two other suits.</p>
<p role="indent">(c) a 4, 3, 2, 1, distribution of suits.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>20</bold> A six-card hand is dealt from an ordinary deck of cards. Find the probabilitythat:
</p>
<p role="indent">(a) All six cards are hearts.</p>
<p role="indent">(b) There are three aces, two kings, and one queen.</p>
<p role="indent">(c) There are three cards of one suit and three of another suit.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>21</bold> A lady wishes to color her fingernails on one hand using at most two of thecolors red, yellow, and blue. How many ways can she do this?</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_116">116</target>
<p role="noindent"><bold>22</bold> How many ways can six indistinguishable letters be put in three mail boxes?<i>Hint</i>: One representation of this is given by a sequence |LL|L|LLL| where the|'s represent the partitions for the boxes and the L's the letters. Any possibleway can be so described. Note that we need two bars at the ends and theremaining two bars and the six L's can be put in any order.</p>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>23</bold> Using the method for the hint in Exercise 22, show that<i>r</i> indistinguishable
objects can be put in<i>n</i> boxes in
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0">
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>r</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0">
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>r</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>r</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">different ways.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>24</bold> A travel bureau estimates that when 20 tourists go to a resort with ten hotelsthey distribute themselves as if the bureau were putting 20 indistinguishableobjects into ten distinguishable boxes. Assuming this model is correct, findthe probability that no hotel is left vacant when the first group of 20 touristsarrives.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>25</bold> An elevator takes on six passengers and stops at ten floors. We can assigntwo different equiprobable measures for the ways that the passengers are discharged: (a) we consider the passengers to be distinguishable or (b) we consider them to be indistinguishable (see Exercise 23 for this case). For eachcase, calculate the probability that all the passengers get off at different floors.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>26</bold> You are playing heads or tails with Prosser but you suspect that his coin isunfair. Von Neumann suggested that you proceed as follows: Toss Prosser'scoin twice. If the outcome is HT call the result win. if it is TH call the resultlose. If it is TT or HH ignore the outcome and toss Prosser's coin twice again.Keep going until you get either an HT or a TH and call the result win or losein a single play. Repeat this procedure for each play. Assume that Prosser'scoin turns up heads with probability<i>p</i>.</p>
<p role="indent">(a) Find the probability of HT, TH, HH, TT with two tosses of Prosser'scoin.</p>
<p role="indent">(b) Using part (a), show that the probability of a win on any one play is 1/2,no matter what<i>p</i> is.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>27</bold> John claims that he has extrasensory powers and can tell which of two symbolsis on a card turned face down (see Example 3.11). To test his ability he isasked to do this for a sequence of trials. Let the null hypothesis be that he isjust guessing, so that the probability is 1/2 of his getting it right each time,and let the alternative hypothesis be that he can name the symbol correctlymore than half the time. Devise a test with the property that the probabilityof a type 1 error is less than .05 and the probability of a type 2 error is lessthan .05 if John can name the symbol correctly 75 percent of the time.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_117">117</target>
<p role="noindent"><bold>28</bold> In Example 3.11 assume the alternative hypothesis is that<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>p</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>.8</mn></mrow></math> and that itis desired to have the probability of each type of error less than .01. Use theprogram<bold>PowerCurve</bold> to determine values of<i>n</i> and<i>m</i> that will achieve this.Choose<i>n</i> as small as possible.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>29</bold> A drug is assumed to be effective with an unknown probability<i>p</i>. To estimate<i>p</i> the drug is given to<i>n</i> patients. It is found to be effective for<i>m</i> patients.The method of maximum likelihood for estimating<i>p</i> states that we shouldchoose the value for<i>p</i> that gives the highest probability of getting what wegot on the experiment. Assuming that the experiment can be considered as aBernoulli trials process with probability<i>p</i> for success, show that the maximumlikelihood estimate for<i>p</i> is the proportion<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>m</mi><mo>/</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> of successes.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>30</bold> Recall that in the World Series the first team to win four games wins theseries. The series can go at most seven games. Assume that the Red Soxand the Mets are playing the series. Assume that the Mets win each gamewith probability<i>p</i>. Fermat observed that even though the series might not goseven games, the probability that the Mets win the series is the same as theprobability that they win four or more game in a series that was forced to goseven games no matter who wins the individual games.</p>
<p role="indent">(a) Using the program<bold>PowerCurve</bold> of Example 3.11 find the probabilitythat the Mets win the series for the cases<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>p</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>.5</mn></mrow></math>,<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>p</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>.6</mn></mrow></math>,<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>p</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>.7</mn></mrow></math>.</p>
<p role="indent">(b) Assume that the Mets have probability .6 of winning each game. Usethe program<bold>PowerCurve</bold> to find a value of<i>n</i> so that, if the series goesto the first team to win more than half the games, the Mets will have a95 percent chance of winning the series. Choose<i>n</i> as small as possible.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>31</bold> Each of the four engines on an airplane functions correctly on a given flightwith probability .99, and the engines function independently of each other.Assume that the plane can make a safe landing if at least two of its enginesare functioning correctly. What is the probability that the engines will allowfor a safe landing?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>32</bold> A small boy is lost coming down Mount Washington. The leader of the searchteam estimates that there is a probability<i>p</i> that he came down on the eastside and a probability<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>p</mi></mrow></math> that he came down on the west side. He has<i>n</i>people in his search team who will search independently and, if the boy ison the side being searched, each member will find the boy with probability<i>u</i>. Determine how he should divide the<i>n</i> people into two groups to searchthe two sides of the mountain so that he will have the highest probability offinding the boy. How does this depend on<i>u</i>?</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>*33</bold><math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> balls are chosen at random from a total of<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> red balls and<math display="inline"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> blue balls.Find a combinatorial expression for the probability that the chosen balls areequally divided in color. Use Stirling's formula to estimate this probability.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_118">118</target>
<p role="indent">Using<bold>BinomialProbabilities</bold>, compare the exact value with Stirling's approximation for<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>20</mn></mrow></math>.</p>
<p role="noindent"><bold>34</bold> Assume that every time you buy a box of Wheaties, you receive one of thepictures of the<i>n</i> players on the New York Yankees. Over a period of time,you buy<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>m</mi><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></math> boxes of Wheaties.</p>
<p role="indent">(a) Use Theorem 3.8 to show that the probability that you get all<i>n</i> picturesis</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>1</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mi>m</mi>
</msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mi>m</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mo>&#x22EF;</mo>
<mo>+</mo>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mi>m</mi>
</msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">
<i>Hint</i>: Let<i>E<sub>k</sub></i> be the event that you do not get the<i>k</i>th player's picture.
</p>
<p role="indent">(b) Write a computer program to compute this probability. Use this programto find, for given<i>n</i>, the smallest value of<i>m</i> which will give probability
<math display="inline"><mrow><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mn>.5</mn></mrow></math> of getting all<i>n</i> pictures. Consider<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>50</mn></mrow></math>, 100, and 150 and show
that<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>m</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>log</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>log</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></math> is a good estimate for the number of boxes
needed.
</p>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>*35</bold> Prove the following binomial identity
</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></mrow><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</munderover>
<msup>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mn>2</mn>
</msup>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent"><i>Hint</i>: Consider an urn with<i>n</i> red balls and<i>n</i> blue balls inside. Show thateach side of the equation equals the number of ways to choose<i>n</i> balls fromthe urn.</p>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>36</bold> Let<i>j</i> and<i>n</i> be positive integers, with<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>n</mi></mrow></math>. An experiment consists of
choosing, at random, a<i>j</i>-tuple of<i>positive</i> integers whose sum is at most<i>n</i>.
</p>
<p role="indent">(a) Find the size of the sample space.<i>Hint</i>: Consider<i>n</i> indistinguishableballs placed in a row. Place<i>j</i> markers between consecutive pairs of balls,with no two markers between the same pair of balls. (We also allow oneof the<i>n</i> markers to be placed at the end of the row of balls.) Show thatthere is a 1-1 correspondence between the set of possible positions forthe markers and the set of<i>j</i>-tuples whose size we are trying to count.</p>
<p role="indent">(b) Find the probability that the<i>j</i>-tuple selected contains at least one 1.</p>
<p role="noindent">
<bold>37</bold> Let<math display="inline"><mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>(</mo><mtext>mod</mtext><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mi>m</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow></math> denote the remainder when the integer<i>n</i> is divided by the
integer<i>m</i>. Write a computer program to compute the numbers
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mspace width="0.3em"/>
<mo>(</mo><mtext>mod</mtext><mo>&#x2009;</mo><mi>m</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
where
<math display="inline">
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac linethickness="0"><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
</math>
is a binomial coefficient and<i>m</i> is an integer. You can do this byusing the recursion relations for generating binomial coefficients, doing all the</p>
</sec>

<ref-list>
<ref id="fn14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Introduction to Probability Theory and Its Applications</source>
<volume>vol. 1</volume>
<edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1968</year>
<fpage>41</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Trait&#xe9; du Triangle Arithm&#xe9;tique</source>
<publisher-name>Desprez</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
<year>1665</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>AWF</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Pascal's Arithmetical Triangle</source>
<publisher-name>Griffin</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<year>1987</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation>
<comment>ibid., p. 27.</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Science and Civilization in China</source>
<volume>vol. 3</volume>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1959</year>
<fpage>135</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tartaglia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>General Trattato di Numeri et Misure</source>
<publisher-loc>Vinegia</publisher-loc>
<year>1556</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation>
<comment>Quoted in Edwards, op. cit., p. 37.</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stifel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Arithmetica Integra</source>
<publisher-loc>Norimburgae</publisher-loc>
<year>1544</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cardano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Opus Novum de Proportionibus Numerorum</source>
<publisher-loc>Basilea</publisher-loc>
<year>1570</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<comment>op. cit., p. 235.</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>AWF</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<comment>op. cit., p. ix.</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernoulli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Ars Conjectandi</source>
<publisher-name>Thurnisiorum</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Basil</publisher-loc>
<year>1713</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="fn26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<source>Introduction to Probability Theory and its Applications</source>
<volume>vol. I</volume>
<edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1968</year>
<fpage>106</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_3_2_exercises_continued">
<label>3.2</label>
<title>Combinations ? Exercises (continued)</title>
<exercise id="ex_37_continued">
<p role="noindent">arithmetic using the basic function<i>mod</i>(<i>n</i>,<i>m</i>). Try to write your program tomake as large a table as possible. Run your program for the cases<i>m</i> = 2 to 7.Do you see any patterns? In particular, for the case<i>m</i> = 2 and<i>n</i> a powerof 2, verify that all the entries in the (<i>n</i> &#x2212; 1)st row are 1. (The correspondingbinomial numbers are odd.) Use your pictures to explain why this is true.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_38">
<label>38</label>
<p role="noindent">Lucas<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref> proved the following general result relating to Exercise 37. If<i>p</i> is
any prime number, then
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
can be found as follows: Expand<i>n</i>
and<i>j</i> in base<i>p</i> as
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>=</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mn>0</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>p</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><msup><mi>p</mi><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><msup><mi>p</mi><mi>k</mi></msup>
</mrow>
</math>
and
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mn>0</mn></msub>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>p</mi>
<mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><msup><mi>p</mi><mn>2</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>+</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><msup><mi>p</mi><mi>k</mi></msup>
</mrow>
</math>,
respectively. (Here<i>k</i> is chosen large enough to represent all
numbers from 0 to<i>n</i> in base<i>p</i> using<i>k</i> digits.) Let
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mi>s</mi><mo>=</mo>
<mo>(</mo><msub><mi>s</mi><mn>0</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<mo>&#x2026;</mo><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>s</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
and
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo>
<mo>(</mo><msub><mi>r</mi><mn>0</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>,</mo>
<mo>&#x2026;</mo><mo>,</mo>
<msub><mi>r</mi><mi>k</mi></msub><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>. Then</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>j</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<munderover>
<mo>&#x220F;</mo>
<mrow><mi>i</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow>
<mi>k</mi>
</munderover>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><msub><mi>s</mi><mi>i</mi></msub><msub><mi>r</mi><mi>i</mi></msub></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">For example, if<i>p</i> = 7,<i>n</i> = 12, and<i>j</i> = 9, then</p>
<math display="block">
<mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>12</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd>
<mn>5</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><msup><mn>7</mn><mn>0</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><msup><mn>7</mn><mn>1</mn></msup>
<mo>,</mo>
</mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mn>9</mn></mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd>
<mn>2</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><msup><mn>7</mn><mn>0</mn></msup>
<mo>+</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>&#x22C5;</mo><msup><mn>7</mn><mn>1</mn></msup>
<mo>,</mo>
</mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
<p role="indent">so that</p>
<math display="block">
<mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mtr>
<mtd><mi>s</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd><mo>(</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>,</mo></mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd><mi>r</mi></mtd>
<mtd><mo>=</mo></mtd>
<mtd><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>,</mo></mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
<p role="indent">and this result states that</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mn>12</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mi>p</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>1</mn></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mn>7</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Since
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac><mn>12</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></mfenced>
<mo>=</mo><mn>220</mn><mo>=</mo><mn>3</mn>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mn>7</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>,
and
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mfenced>
<mo>=</mo><mn>10</mn><mo>=</mo><mn>3</mn>
<mo>(</mo><mi>mod</mi><mspace width="0.25em"/><mn>7</mn><mo>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>,
we see that the result is correct for this example.</p>
<p role="indent">Show that this result implies that, for<i>p</i> = 2, the (<i>p</i><sup><i>k</i></sup> &#x2212; 1)st row of your trianglein Exercise 37 has no zeros.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_39">
<label>39</label>
<p role="noindent">Prove that the probability of exactly<i>n</i> heads in 2<i>n</i> tosses of a fair coin isgiven by the product of the odd numbers up to 2<i>n</i> &#x2212; 1 divided by the productof the even numbers up to 2<i>n</i>.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_40">
<label>40</label>
<p role="noindent">Let<i>n</i> be a positive integer, and assume that<i>j</i> is a positive integer not exceeding
<i>n</i>/2. Show that in Theorem 3.5, if one alternates the multiplications anddivisions, then all of the intermediate values in the calculation are integers.Show also that none of these intermediate values exceed the final value.</p>
</exercise>
<fn id="fn27">
<label>27</label>
<p>E. Lucas, &#x201C;Th&#xe9;orie des Functions Num&#xe9;riques Simplement Periodiques,&#x201D;
<i>American J. Math.</i>, vol. 1 (1878), pp. 184&#x2013;240, 289&#x2013;321.</p>
</fn>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_3_3">
<label>3.3</label>
<title>Card Shuffling</title>
<p role="noindent">Much of this section is based upon an article by Brad Mann,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref> which is an expositionof an article by David Bayer and Persi Diaconis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref></p>
<sec id="sec_riffle_shuffles">
<title>Riffle Shuffles</title>
<p role="noindent">Given a deck of<i>n</i> cards, how many times must we shuffle it to make it &#x201C;random&#x201D;?Of course, the answer depends upon the method of shuffling which is used and whatwe mean by &#x201C;random.&#x201D; We shall begin the study of this question by considering astandard model for the riffle shuffle.</p>
<p role="indent">We begin with a deck of<i>n</i> cards, which we will assume are labelled in increasingorder with the integers from 1 to<i>n</i>. A riffle shuffle consists of a cut of the deck intotwo stacks and an interleaving of the two stacks. For example, if<i>n</i> = 6, the initialordering is (1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6), and a cut might occur between cards 2 and 3. This givesrise to two stacks, namely (1, 2) and (3, 4, 5, 6). These are interleaved to form anew ordering of the deck. For example, these two stacks might form the ordering(1, 3, 4, 2, 5, 6). In order to discuss such shuffles, we need to assign a probabilitydistribution to the set of all possible shuffles. There are several reasonable ways inwhich this can be done. We will give several different assignment strategies, andshow that they are equivalent. (This does not mean that this assignment is theonly reasonable one.) First, we assign the binomial probability<i>b</i>(<i>n</i>, 1/2,<i>k</i>) to theevent that the cut occurs after the<i>k</i>th card. Next, we assume that all possibleinterleavings, given a cut, are equally likely. Thus, to complete the assignmentof probabilities, we need to determine the number of possible interleavings of twostacks of cards, with<i>k</i> and<i>n</i> &#x2212;<i>k</i> cards, respectively.</p>
<p role="indent">We begin by writing the second stack in a line, with spaces in between eachpair of consecutive cards, and with spaces at the beginning and end (so there are<i>n</i> &#x2212;<i>k</i> + 1 spaces). We choose, with replacement,<i>k</i> of these spaces, and place thecards from the first stack in the chosen spaces. This can be done in</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>k</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">ways. Thus, the probability of a given interleaving should be</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>k</mi></mfrac></mfenced>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">Next, we note that if the new ordering is not the identity ordering, it is theresult of a unique cut-interleaving pair. If the new ordering is the identity, it is theresult of any one of<i>n</i> + 1 cut-interleaving pairs.</p>
<p role="indent">We define a<i>rising sequence</i> in an ordering to be a maximal subsequence ofconsecutive integers in increasing order. For example, in the ordering</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo>
<mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>7</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>)</mo>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_121">121</target>
<p role="indent">there are 4 rising sequences; they are (1), (2, 3, 4), (5, 6), and (7). It is easy to seethat an ordering is the result of a riffle shuffle applied to the identity ordering ifand only if it has no more than two rising sequences. (If the ordering has two risingsequences, then these rising sequences correspond to the two stacks induced by thecut, and if the ordering has one rising sequence, then it is the identity ordering.)hus, the sample space of orderings obtained by applying a riffle shuffle to theidentity ordering is naturally described as the set of all orderings with at most tworising sequences.</p>
<p role="indent">It is now easy to assign a probability distribution to this sample space. Eachordering with two rising sequences is assigned the value</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>b</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>k</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>k</mi></mfrac></mfenced>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<msup><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></msup>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and the identity ordering is assigned the value</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<msup><mn>2</mn><mi>n</mi></msup>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">There is another way to view a riffle shuffle. We can imagine starting with adeck cut into two stacks as before, with the same probabilities assignment as beforei.e., the binomial distribution. Once we have the two stacks, we take cards, one byone, off of the bottom of the two stacks, and place them onto one stack. If thereare<i>k</i><sub>1</sub> and<i>k</i><sub>2</sub> cards, respectively, in the two stacks at some point in this process,then we make the assumption that the probabilities that the next card to be takencomes from a given stack is proportional to the current stack size. This implies thathe probability that we take the next card from the first stack equals</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<msub><mi>k</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<mrow><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>+</mo><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></msub></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">and the corresponding probability for the second stack is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<msub><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></msub>
<mrow><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>+</mo><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></msub></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">We shall now show that this process assigns the uniform probability to each of thepossible interleavings of the two stacks.</p>
<p role="indent">Suppose, for example, that an interleaving came about as the result of choosingcards from the two stacks in some order. The probability that this result occurredis the product of the probabilities at each point in the process, since the choiceof card at each point is assumed to be independent of the previous choices. Eachfactor of this product is of the form</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<msub><mi>k</mi><mi>i</mi></msub>
<mrow><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mo>+</mo><msub><mi>k</mi><mn>2</mn></msub></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">where<i>i</i> = 1 or 2, and the denominator of each factor equals the number of cards leftto be chosen. Thus, the denominator of the probability is just<i>n</i>!. At the momentwhen a card is chosen from a stack that has<i>i</i> cards in it, the numerator of the</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_122">122</target>
<p role="indent">corresponding factor in the probability is<i>i</i>, and the number of cards in this stackdecreases by 1. Thus, the numerator is seen to be<i>k</i>!(<i>n</i> &#x2212;<i>k</i>)!, since all cards in bothstacks are eventually chosen. Therefore, this process assigns the probability</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mfenced open="(" close=")"><mfrac><mi>n</mi><mi>k</mi></mfrac></mfenced>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">to each possible interleaving.</p>
<p role="indent">We now turn to the question of what happens when we riffle shuffle<i>s</i> times. Itshould be clear that if we start with the identity ordering, we obtain an orderingwith at most 2<sup><i>s</i></sup> rising sequences, since a riffle shuffle creates at most two risingsequences from every rising sequence in the starting ordering. In fact, it is not hardto see that each such ordering is the result of<i>s</i> riffle shuffles. The question becomes,then, in how many ways can an ordering with<i>r</i> rising sequences come about byapplying<i>s</i> riffle shuffles to the identity ordering? In order to answer this question,we turn to the idea of an<i>a</i>-shuffle.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_a_shuffles">
<title><i>a</i>-Shuffles</title>
<p role="noindent">There are several ways to visualize an<i>a</i>-shuffle. One way is to imagine a creaturewith<i>a</i> hands who is given a deck of cards to riffle shuffle. The creature naturallycuts the deck into<i>a</i> stacks, and then riffles them together. (Imagine that!) Thus,the ordinary riffle shuffle is a 2-shuffle. As in the case of the ordinary 2-shuffle, weallow some of the stacks to have 0 cards. Another way to visualize an<i>a</i>-shuffle isto think about its inverse, called an<i>a</i>-unshuffle. This idea is described in the proofof the next theorem.</p>
<p role="indent">We will now show that an<i>a</i>-shuffle followed by a<i>b</i>-shuffle is equivalent to an<i>ab</i>-shuffle. This means, in particular, that<i>s</i> riffle shuffles in succession are equivalentto one 2<sup><i>s</i></sup>-shuffle. This equivalence is made precise by the following theorem.</p>
<theorem id="thm_3_9">
<label>Theorem 3.9</label>
<p role="noindent">Let<i>a</i> and<i>b</i> be two positive integers. Let<i>S</i><sub><i>a</i>,<i>b</i></sub> be the set of all orderedpairs in which the first entry is an<i>a</i>-shuffle and the second entry is a<i>b</i>-shuffle. Let<i>S</i><sub><i>ab</i></sub> be the set of all<i>ab</i>-shuffles. Then there is a 1-1 correspondence between<i>S</i><sub><i>a</i>,<i>b</i></sub>and<i>S</i><sub><i>ab</i></sub> with the following property. Suppose that (<i>T</i><sub>1</sub>,<i>T</i><sub>2</sub>) corresponds to<i>T</i><sub>3</sub>. If<i>T</i><sub>1</sub> is applied to the identity ordering, and<i>T</i><sub>2</sub> is applied to the resulting ordering,then the final ordering is the same as the ordering that is obtained by applying<i>T</i><sub>3</sub>to the identity ordering.</p>
<proof>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">The easiest way to describe the required correspondence is through the ideaof an unshuffle. An<i>a</i>-unshuffle begins with a deck of<i>n</i> cards. One by one, cards aretaken from the top of the deck and placed, with equal probability, on the bottomof any one of<i>a</i> stacks, where the stacks are labelled from 0 to<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1. After all of thecards have been distributed, we combine the stacks to form one stack by placingstack<i>i</i> on top of stack<i>i</i> + 1, for 0 &#x2264;<i>i</i> &#x2264;<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1. It is easy to see that if one starts witha deck, there is exactly one way to cut the deck to obtain the<i>a</i> stacks generated bythe<i>a</i>-unshuffle, and with these<i>a</i> stacks, there is exactly one way to interleave them</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_123">123</target>
<p role="indent">to obtain the deck in the order that it was in before the unshuffle was performed.Thus, this<i>a</i>-unshuffle corresponds to a unique<i>a</i>-shuffle, and this<i>a</i>-shuffle is theinverse of the original<i>a</i>-unshuffle.</p>
<p role="indent">If we apply an<i>ab</i>-unshuffle<i>U</i><sub>3</sub> to a deck, we obtain a set of<i>ab</i> stacks, whichare then combined, in order, to form one stack. We label these stacks with orderedpairs of integers, where the first coordinate is between 0 and<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1, and the secondcoordinate is between 0 and<i>b</i> &#x2212; 1. Then we label each card with the label of itsstack. The number of possible labels is<i>ab</i>, as required. Using this labelling, wecan describe how to find a<i>b</i>-unshuffle and an<i>a</i>-unshuffle, such that if these twounshuffles are applied in this order to the deck, we obtain the same set of<i>ab</i> stacksas were obtained by the<i>ab</i>-unshuffle.</p>
<p role="indent">To obtain the<i>b</i>-unshuffle<i>U</i><sub>2</sub>, we sort the deck into<i>b</i> stacks, with the<i>i</i>th stackcontaining all of the cards with second coordinate<i>i</i>, for 0 &#x2264;<i>i</i> &#x2264;<i>b</i> &#x2212; 1. Then thesestacks are combined to form one stack. The<i>a</i>-unshuffle<i>U</i><sub>1</sub> proceeds in the samemanner, except that the first coordinates of the labels are used. The resulting<i>a</i>stacks are then combined to form one stack.</p>
<p role="indent">The above description shows that the cards ending up on top are all thoselabelled (0, 0). These are followed by those labelled (0, 1), (0, 2), . . . , (0,<i>b</i> &#x2212;1), (1, 0), (1, 1), . . . , (<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1,<i>b</i> &#x2212; 1). Furthermore, the relative order of any pairof cards with the same labels is never altered. But this is exactly the same as an
<i>ab</i>-unshuffle, if, at the beginning of such an unshuffle, we label each of the cardswith one of the labels (0, 0), (0, 1), . . . , (0,<i>b</i> &#x2212; 1), (1, 0), (1, 1), . . . , (<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1,<i>b</i> &#x2212; 1).This completes the proof. &#x25A1;</p>
</proof>
</theorem>
<p role="indent">In Figure 3.11, we show the labels for a 2-unshuffle of a deck with 10 cards.There are 4 cards with the label 0 and 6 cards with the label 1, so if the 2-unshuffleis performed, the first stack will have 4 cards and the second stack will have 6 cards.When this unshuffle is performed, the deck ends up in the identity ordering.</p>
<p role="indent">In Figure 3.12, we show the labels for a 4-unshuffle of the same deck (becausethere are four labels being used). This figure can also be regarded as an example ofa pair of 2-unshuffles, as described in the proof above. The first 2-unshuffle will usethe second coordinate of the labels to determine the stacks. In this case, the twostacks contain the cards whose values are</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>{</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>7</mn><mo>}</mo>
<mspace width="1em"/>
<mtext>and</mtext>
<mspace width="1em"/>
<mo>{</mo><mn>8</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>9</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>10</mn><mo>}</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">After this 2-unshuffle has been performed, the deck is in the order shown in Figure 3.11, as the reader should check. If we wish to perform a 4-unshuffle on thedeck, using the labels shown, we sort the cards lexicographically, obtaining the fourstacks</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mo>{</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>}</mo><mo>,</mo>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mo>{</mo><mn>3</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>}</mo><mo>,</mo>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mo>{</mo><mn>5</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>6</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>7</mn><mo>}</mo><mo>,</mo>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mtext>and</mtext>
<mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mo>{</mo><mn>8</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>9</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>10</mn><mo>}</mo>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">When these stacks are combined, we once again obtain the identity ordering of thedeck. The point of the above theorem is that both sorting procedures always leadto the same initial ordering.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_124">124</target>
<fig id="fig_3_11">
<label>Figure 3.11</label>
<caption><p>Before a 2-unshuffle.</p></caption>
</fig>
<fig id="fig_3_12">
<label>Figure 3.12</label>
<caption><p>Before a 4-unshuffle.</p></caption>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_125">125</target>
<theorem id="thm_3_10">
<label>Theorem 3.10</label>
<p role="noindent">If<i>D</i> is any ordering that is the result of applying an<i>a</i>-shuffle andthen a<i>b</i>-shuffle to the identity ordering, then the probability assigned to<i>D</i> by thispair of operations is the same as the probability assigned to<i>D</i> by the process ofapplying an<i>ab</i>-shuffle to the identity ordering.</p>
<proof>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">Call the sample space of<i>a</i>-shuffles<i>S</i><sub><i>a</i></sub>. If we label the stacks by the integersfrom 0 to<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1, then each cut-interleaving pair, i.e., shuffle, corresponds to exactlyone<i>n</i>-digit base<i>a</i> integer, where the<i>i</i>th digit in the integer is the stack of whichthe<i>i</i>th card is a member. Thus, the number of cut-interleaving pairs is equal tothe number of<i>n</i>-digit base<i>a</i> integers, which is<i>a</i><sup><i>n</i></sup>. Of course, not all of thesepairs leads to different orderings. The number of pairs leading to a given orderingwill be discussed later. For our purposes it is enough to point out that it is thecut-interleaving pairs that determine the probability assignment.</p>
<p role="indent">The previous theorem shows that there is a 1-1 correspondence between<i>S</i><sub><i>a</i>,<i>b</i></sub> and
<i>S</i><sub><i>ab</i></sub>. Furthermore, corresponding elements give the same ordering when applied tothe identity ordering. Given any ordering<i>D</i>, let<i>m</i><sub>1</sub> be the number of elementsof<i>S</i><sub><i>a</i>,<i>b</i></sub> which, when applied to the identity ordering, result in<i>D</i>. Let<i>m</i><sub>2</sub> be thenumber of elements of<i>S</i><sub><i>ab</i></sub> which, when applied to the identity ordering, result in<i>D</i>.The previous theorem implies that<i>m</i><sub>1</sub> =<i>m</i><sub>2</sub>. Thus, both sets assign the probability</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<msub><mi>m</mi><mn>1</mn></msub>
<msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>a</mi><mi>b</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mi>n</mi></msup>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">to<i>D</i>. This completes the proof. &#x25A1;</p>
</proof>
</theorem>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_birthday_problem">
<title>Connection with the Birthday Problem</title>
<p role="noindent">There is another point that can be made concerning the labels given to the cardsby the successive unshuffles. Suppose that we 2-unshuffle an<i>n</i>-card deck until thelabels on the cards are all different. It is easy to see that this process produceseach permutation with the same probability, i.e., this is a random process. To see this, note that if the labels become distinct on the<i>s</i>th 2-unshuffle, then one canthink of this sequence of 2-unshuffles as one 2<sup><i>s</i></sup>-unshuffle, in which all of the stacksdetermined by the unshuffle have at most one card in them (remember, the stackscorrespond to the labels). If each stack has at most one card in it, then given anywo cardsin the deck, i is equally likely that the first card has a lower or a higherlabel than the second card. Thus, each possible ordering is equally likely to resultfrom this 2<sup><i>s</i></sup>-unshuffle.</p>
<p role="indent">Let<i>T</i> be the random variable that counts the number of 2-unshuffles until alllabels are distinct. One can think of<i>T</i> as giving a measure of how long it takes inthe unshuffling process until randomness is reached. Since shuffling and unshuffling
are inverse processes,<i>T</i> also measures the number of shuffles necessary to achieverandomness. Suppose that we have an<i>n</i>-card deck, and we ask for<i>P</i>(<i>T</i> &#x2264;<i>s</i>). Thiequals 1 &#x2212;<i>P</i>(<i>T</i> &gt;<i>s</i>). But<i>T</i> &gt;<i>s</i> if and only if it is the case that not all of thelabels after<i>s</i> 2-unshuffles are distinct. This is just the birthday problem; we areasking for the probability that at least two people have the same birthday, given</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_126">126</target>
<p role="indent">that we have<i>n</i> people and there are 2<sup><i>s</i></sup> possible birthdays. Using our formula from
Example 3.3, we find that</p>
<math display="block" id="eq_3_4">
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>&gt;</mo><mi>s</mi><mo>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo>
<mn>1</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac><msup><mn>2</mn><mi>s</mi></msup><mi>n</mi></mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
<msup><mn>2</mn><mrow><mi>s</mi><mi>n</mi></mrow></msup>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<label>(3.4)</label>
<p role="indent">In Chapter 6, we will define the average value of a random variable. Using thisidea, and the above equation, one can calculate the average value of the randomvariable<i>T</i> (see Exercise 6.1.41). For example, if<i>n</i> = 52, then the average value of
<i>T</i> is about 11.7. This means that, on the average, about 12 riffle shuffles are neededfor the process to be considered random.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_cut_interleaving">
<title>Cut-Interleaving Pairs and Orderings</title>
<p role="noindent">As was noted in the proof of Theorem 3.10, not all of the cut-interleaving pairs leadto different orderings. However, there is an easy formula which gives the number ofsuch pairs that lead to a given ordering.</p>
<theorem id="thm_3_11">
<label>Theorem 3.11</label>
<p role="noindent">If an ordering of length<i>n</i> has<i>r</i> rising sequences, then the numberof cut-interleaving pairs under an<i>a</i>-shuffle of the identity ordering which lead tothe ordering is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<proof>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">To see why this is true, we need to count the number of ways in which thecut in an<i>a</i>-shuffle can be performed which will lead to a given ordering with<i>r</i> risingsequences. We can disregard the interleavings, since once a cut has been made, atmost one interleaving will lead to a given ordering. Since the given ordering has
<i>r</i> rising sequences,<i>r</i> &#x2212; 1 of the division points in the cut are determined. Theremaining<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1 &#x2212; (<i>r</i> &#x2212; 1) =<i>a</i> &#x2212;<i>r</i> division points can be placed anywhere. Thenumber of places to put these remaining division points is<i>n</i> + 1 (which is thenumber of spaces between the consecutive pairs of cards, including the positions atthe beginning and the end of the deck). These places are chosen with repetitionallowed, so the number of ways to make these choices is</p>
<math display="block">
<mrow>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mrow><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>=</mo>
<mfenced open="(" close=")">
<mfrac>
<mrow><mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mfenced>
<mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
<p role="indent">In particular, this means that if<i>D</i> is an ordering that is the result of applyingan<i>a</i>-shuffle to the identity ordering, and if<i>D</i> has<i>r</i> rising sequences, then theprobability assigned to<i>D</i> by this process is</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mtable columnalign='left' equalrows='true' equalcolumns='true'>
<mtr columnalign='left'>
<mtd columnalign='left'>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo><munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>a</mi>
</munderover>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>a</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><munderover>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</munderover>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>=</mo><mn>1.</mn></mrow>
</mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr columnalign='left'>
<mtd columnalign='left'>
<mrow></mrow>
</mtd>
</mtr>
 
</mtable></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">This completes the proof. &#x25A1;</p>
</proof>
</theorem>
<target target-type="page" id="page_127">127</target>
<p role="indent">The above theorem shows that the essential information about the probabilityassigned to an ordering under an<i>a</i>-shuffle is just the number of rising sequences inthe ordering. Thus, if we determine the number of orderings which contain exactly
<i>r</i> rising sequences, for each<i>r</i> between 1 and<i>n</i>, then we will have determined thedistribution function of the random variable which consists of applying a random<i>a</i>-shuffle to the identity ordering.</p>
<p role="indent">The number of orderings of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>} with<i>r</i> rising sequences is denoted by
<i>A</i>(<i>n</i>,<i>r</i>), and is called an<i>Eulerian number</i>. There are many ways to calculate thevalues of these numbers; the following theorem gives one recursive method whichfollows immediately from what we already know about<i>a</i>-shuffles.</p>
<theorem id="thm_3_12">
<label>Theorem 3.12</label>
<p role="noindent">Let<i>a</i> and<i>n</i> be positive integers. Then</p>
<math display='block'>
<mtable columnalign='left'>
<mtr>
<mtd>
<msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>=</mo><munderover>
<mstyle mathsize='140%' displaystyle='true'><mo>&#x2211;</mo></mstyle>
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>a</mi>
</munderover >
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>a</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><munderover>
<mstyle mathsize='140%' displaystyle='true'><mo>&#x2211;</mo></mstyle>
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</munderover >
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>&#xFFFD;</mi><mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>=</mo><mn>1.</mn>
</mtd>
</mtr>
<mtr>
<mtd>
<mrow></mrow>
</mtd>
</mtr>
</mtable>
 
</math>

<proof>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">The second equation can be used to calculate the values of the Euleriannumbers, and follows immediately from the Equation 3.5. The last equation isa consequence of the fact that the only ordering of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>} with one risingsequence is the identity ordering. Thus, it remains to prove Equation 3.5. We willcount the set of<i>a</i>-shuffles of a deck with<i>n</i> cards in two ways. First, we know thatthere are<i>a</i><sup><i>n</i></sup> such shuffles (this was noted in the proof of Theorem 3.10). But thereare<i>A</i>(<i>n</i>,<i>r</i>) orderings of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>} with<i>r</i> rising sequences, and Theorem 3.11states that for each such ordering, there are exactly</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">cut-interleaving pairs that lead to the ordering. Therefore, the right-hand side ofEquation 3.5 counts the set of<i>a</i>-shuffles of an<i>n</i>-card deck. This completes theproof. &#x25A1;</p>
</proof>
</theorem>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_random_orderings">
<title>Random Orderings and Random Processes</title>
<p role="noindent">We now turn to the second question that was asked at the beginning of this section:What do we mean by a &#x201C;random&#x201D; ordering? It is somewhat misleading to thinkabout a given ordering as being random or not random. If we want to choose arandom ordering from the set of all orderings of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>}, we mean that we every ordering to be chosen with the same probability, i.e., any ordering is as&#x201C;random&#x201D; as any other.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_128">128</target>
<p role="indent">The word &#x201C;random&#x201D; should really be used to describe a process. We will say thata process that produces an object from a (finite) set of objects is a random processif each object in the set is produced with the same probability by the process. Inthe present situation, the objects are the orderings, and the process which producesthese objects is the shuffling process. It is easy to see that no<i>a</i>-shuffle is really arandom process, since if<i>T</i><sub>1</sub> and<i>T</i><sub>2</sub> are two orderings with a different number ofrising sequences, then they are produced by an<i>a</i>-shuffle, applied to the identityordering, with different probabilities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_variation_distance">
<title>Variation Distance</title>
<p role="noindent">Instead of requiring that a sequence of shuffles yield a process which is random, wewill define a measure that describes how far away a given process is from a randomprocess. Let<i>X</i> be any process which produces an ordering of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>}. Define<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub>(&#x03C0;) be the probability that<i>X</i> produces the ordering &#x03C0;. (Thus,<i>X</i> can be thoughtof as a random variable with distribution function<i>f</i>.) Let &#x03A9;<sub><i>n</i></sub> be the set of allorderings of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>}. Finally, let<i>u</i>(&#x03C0;) = 1/|&#x03A9;<sub><i>n</i></sub>| for all &#x03C0; &#x2208; &#x03A9;<sub><i>n</i></sub>. The function<i>u</i> is the distribution function of a process which produces orderings and which israndom. For each ordering &#x03C0; &#x2208; &#x03A9;<sub><i>n</i></sub>, the quantity</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mfenced close="|" open="|">
<mrow>
<msub>
<mi>f</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mfenced>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi>
</mfenced><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>u</mi><mfenced>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi>
</mfenced></mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">is the difference between the actual and desired probabilities that<i>X</i> produces &#x03C0;. Ifwe sum this over all orderings &#x03C0; and call this sum<i>S</i>, we see that<i>S</i> = 0 if and onlyif<i>X</i> is random, and otherwise<i>S</i> is positive. It is easy to show that the maximumvalue of<i>S</i> is 2, so we will multiply the sum by 1/2 so that the value falls in theinterval [0, 1]. Thus, we obtain the following sum as the formula for the<i>variationdistance</i> between the two processes:</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2225;</mo><msub>
<mi>f</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>u</mi><mo>&#x2225;</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mn>2</mn>
</mfrac>
<munder>
<mstyle mathsize='140%' displaystyle='true'><mo>&#x2211;</mo></mstyle>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>&#x2208;</mo><msub>
<mi>&#x03A9;</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msub>
</mrow>
</munder>
<mfenced close="|" open="|">
<mrow>
<msub>
<mi>f</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mfenced>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi>
</mfenced><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>u</mi><mfenced>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi>
</mfenced></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Now we apply this idea to the case of shuffling. We let<i>X</i> be the process of<i>s</i>successive riffle shuffles applied to the identity ordering. We know that it is alsopossible to think of<i>X</i> as one 2<sup><i>s</i></sup>-shuffle. We also know that<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub> is constant on theset of all orderings with<i>r</i> rising sequences, where<i>r</i> is any positive integer. Finally,we know the value of<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub> on an ordering with<i>r</i> rising sequences, and we know howmany such orderings there are. Thus, in this specific case, we have</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2225;</mo><msub>
<mi>f</mi>
<mi>X</mi>
</msub>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>u</mi><mo>&#x2225;</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mn>2</mn>
</mfrac>
<munderover>
<mstyle mathsize='140%' displaystyle='true'><mo>&#x2211;</mo></mstyle>
<mrow>
<mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</munderover >
<mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mfenced close="|" open="|">
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mn>2</mn>
<mi>s</mi>
</msup>
<mo>+</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mo>/</mo><msup>
<mn>2</mn>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mi>s</mi></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><mfrac>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>!</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Since this sum has only<i>n</i> summands, it is easy to compute this for moderate sizedvalues of<i>n</i>. For<i>n</i> = 52, we obtain the list of values given in Table 3.14.</p>
<p role="indent">To help in understanding these data, they are shown in graphical form in Figure 3.13. The program<bold>VariationList</bold> produces the data shown in both Table 3.14and Figure 3.13. One sees that until 5 shuffles have occurred, the output of<i>X</i> is</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_129">129</target>
<table-wrap id="table_3_14">
<label>Table 3.14</label>
<caption><p>Distance to the random process.</p></caption>
<table>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Number of Riffle Shuffles</entry>
<entry>Variation Distance</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry></row>
<row><entry>2</entry><entry>1</entry></row>
<row><entry>3</entry><entry>1</entry></row>
<row><entry>4</entry><entry>0.9999995334</entry></row>
<row><entry>5</entry><entry>0.9237329294</entry></row>
<row><entry>6</entry><entry>0.6135495966</entry></row>
<row><entry>7</entry><entry>0.3340609995</entry></row>
<row><entry>8</entry><entry>0.1671586419</entry></row>
<row><entry>9</entry><entry>0.0854201934</entry></row>
<row><entry>10</entry><entry>0.0429455489</entry></row>
<row><entry>11</entry><entry>0.0215023760</entry></row>
<row><entry>12</entry><entry>0.0107548935</entry></row>
<row><entry>13</entry><entry>0.0053779101</entry></row>
<row><entry>14</entry><entry>0.0026890130</entry></row>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig_3_13">
<label>Figure 3.13</label>
<caption><p>Distance to the random process.</p></caption>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_130">130</target>
<p role="indent">very far from random. After 5 shuffles, the distance from the random process isessentially halved each time a shuffle occurs.</p>
<p role="indent">Given the distribution functions<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub>(&#x03C0;) and<i>u</i>(&#x03C0;) as above, there is anotherway to view the variation distance &#x2225;<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub> &#x2212;<i>u</i> &#x2225;. Given any event<i>T</i> (which is asubset of<i>S</i><sub><i>n</i></sub>), we can calculate its probability under the process<i>X</i> and under theuniform process. For example, we can imagine that<i>T</i> represents the set of allpermutations in which the first player in a 7-player poker game is dealt a straightflush (five consecutive cards in the same suit). It is interesting to consider howmuch the probability of this event after a certain number of shuffles differs from theprobability of this event if all permutations are equally likely. This difference canbe thought of as describing how close the process<i>X</i> is to the random process withrespect to the event<i>T</i>.</p>
<p role="indent">Now consider the event<i>T</i> such that the absolute value of the difference betweenthese two probabilities is as large as possible. It can be shown that this absolutevalue is the variation distance between the process<i>X</i> and the uniform process. (Thereader is asked to prove this fact in Exercise 4.)</p><p role="indent">We have just seen that, for a deck of 52 cards, the variation distance betweenthe 7-riffle shuffle process and the random process is about .334. It is of interestto find an event<i>T</i> such that the difference between the probabilities that the twoprocesses produce<i>T</i> is close to .334. An event with this property can be describedin terms of the game called New-Age Solitaire.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_new_age_solitaire">
<title>New-Age Solitaire</title>
<p role="noindent">This game was invented by Peter Doyle. It is played with a standard 52-card deck.We deal the cards face up, one at a time, onto a discard pile. If an ace is encountered,say the ace of Hearts, we use it to start a Heart pile. Each suit pile must be builtup in order, from ace to king, using only subsequently dealt cards. Once we havedealt all of the cards, we pick up the discard pile and continue. We define the Yinsuits to be Hearts and Clubs, and the Yang suits to be Diamonds and Spades. Thegame ends when either both Yin suit piles have been completed, or both Yang suitpiles have been completed. It is clear that if the ordering of the deck is producedby the random process, then the probability that the Yin suit piles are completedfirst is exactly 1/2.</p>
<p role="indent">Now suppose that we buy a new deck of cards, break the seal on the package,and riffle shuffle the deck 7 times. If one tries this, one finds that the Yin suits winabout 75% of the time. This is 25% more than we would get if the deck were intruly random order. This deviation is reasonably close to the theoretical maximumof 33.4% obtained above.</p>
<p role="indent">Why do the Yin suits win so often? In a brand new deck of cards, the suits arein the following order, from top to bottom: ace through king of Hearts, ace throughking of Clubs, king through ace of Diamonds, and king through ace of Spades. Notethat if the cards were not shuffled at all, then the Yin suit piles would be completedon the first pass, before any Yang suit cards are even seen. If we were to continueplaying the game until the Yang suit piles are completed, it would take 13 passes</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_131">131</target>
<p role="indent">through the deck to do this. Thus, one can see that in a new deck, the Yin suits arein the most advantageous order and the Yang suits are in the least advantageousorder. Under 7 riffle shuffles, the relative advantage of the Yin suits over the Yangsuits is preserved to a certain extent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec_3_3_exercises">
<title>Exercises</title>
<exercise id="ex_3_3_1">
<label>1</label>
<p role="noindent">Given any ordering &#x03C3; of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>}, we can define &#x03C3;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, the inverse orderingof &#x03C3;, to be the ordering in which the<i>i</i>th element is the position occupied by
<i>i</i> in &#x03C3;. For example, if &#x03C3; = (1, 3, 5, 2, 4, 7, 6), then &#x03C3;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> = (1, 4, 2, 5, 3, 7, 6). (Ifone thinks of these orderings as permutations, then &#x03C3;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> is the inverse of &#x03C3;.)</p>
<p role="indent">A<i>fall</i> occurs between two positions in an ordering if the left position is occupied by a larger number than the right position. It will be convenient to saythat every ordering has a fall after the last position. In the above example,&#x03C3;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> has four falls. They occur after the second, fourth, sixth, and seventhpositions. Prove that the number of rising sequences in an ordering &#x03C3; equalsthe number of falls in &#x03C3;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_3_3_2">
<label>2</label>
<p role="noindent">Show that if we start with the identity ordering of {1, 2, . . .,<i>n</i>}, then the probability that an<i>a</i>-shuffle leads to an ordering with exactly<i>r</i> rising<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
<mi>n</mi>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
</mrow>
</mfrac>
<mi>A</mi><mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>r</mi></mrow>
</mfenced><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>r</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>a</mi></mrow>
</math>
.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_3_3_3">
<label>3</label>
<p role="noindent">Let<i>D</i> be a deck of<i>n</i> cards. We have seen that there are<i>a</i><sup><i>n</i></sup><i>a</i>-shuffles of<i>D</i>.A coding of the set of<i>a</i>-unshuffles was given in the proof of Theorem 3.9. Wewill now give a coding of the<i>a</i>-shuffles which corresponds to the coding ofthe<i>a</i>-unshuffles. Let<i>S</i> be the set of all<i>n</i>-tuples of integers, each between 0and<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1. Let<i>M</i> = (<i>m</i><sub>1</sub>,<i>m</i><sub>2</sub>, . . .,<i>m</i><sub><i>n</i></sub>) be any element of<i>S</i>. Let<i>n</i><sub><i>i</i></sub> be thenumber of<i>i</i>&#x2019;s in<i>M</i>, for 0 &#x2264;<i>i</i> &#x2264;<i>a</i> &#x2212; 1. Suppose that we start with the deckin increasing order (i.e., the cards are numbered from 1 to<i>n</i>). We label thefirst<i>n</i><sub>0</sub> cards with a 0, the next<i>n</i><sub>1</sub> cards with a 1, etc. Then the<i>a</i>-shufflecorresponding to<i>M</i> is the shuffle which results in the ordering in which thecards labelled<i>i</i> are placed in the positions in<i>M</i> containing the label<i>i</i>. Thecards with the same label are placed in these positions in increasing order oftheir numbers. For example, if<i>n</i> = 6 and<i>a</i> = 3, let<i>M</i> = (1, 0, 2, 2, 0, 2).Then<i>n</i><sub>0</sub> = 2,<i>n</i><sub>1</sub> = 1, and<i>n</i><sub>2</sub> = 3. So we label cards 1 and 2 with a 0, card3 with a 1, and cards 4, 5, and 6 with a 2. Then cards 1 and 2 are placedin positions 2 and 5, card 3 is placed in position 1, and cards 4, 5, and 6 areplaced in positions 3, 4, and 6, resulting in the ordering (3, 1, 4, 5, 2, 6).</p>
<p role="indent">(a) Using this coding, show that the probability that in an<i>a</i>-shuffle, thefirst card (i.e., card number 1) moves to the<i>i</i>th position, is given by thefollowing expression:</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>i</mi></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>+</mo><msup>
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<msup>
<mrow>
<mfenced>
<mrow>
<mi>a</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</mfenced></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>i</mi></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>+</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>+</mo><msup>
<mn>1</mn>
<mrow>
<mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<msup>
<mn>2</mn>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>i</mi></mrow>
</msup>
</mrow>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mi>a</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msup>
</mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_132">132</target>
<p role="indent">(b) Give an accurate estimate for the probability that in three riffle shufflesof a 52-card deck, the first card ends up in one of the first 26 positions.Using a computer, accurately estimate the probability of the same eventafter seven riffle shuffles.</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_3_3_4">
<label>4</label>
<p role="noindent">Let<i>X</i> denote a particular process that produces elements of<i>S</i><sub><i>n</i></sub>, and let<i>U</i>denote the uniform process. Let the distribution functions of these processesbe denoted by<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub> and<i>u</i>, respectively. Show that the variation distance&#x2225;<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub> &#x2212;<i>u</i> &#x2225; is equal to</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<msubsup>
<mrow></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>T</mi><mo>&#x2282;</mo><msub>
<mi>S</mi>
<mi>n</mi>
</msub>
</mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>max</mi></mrow>
</msubsup>
<munder>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>&#x2208;</mo><mi>T</mi></mrow>
</munder>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>f</mi><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>u</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="indent">Hint: Write the permutations in<i>S</i><sub><i>n</i></sub> in decreasing order of the difference
<i>f</i><sub><i>X</i></sub>(&#x03C0;) &#x2212;<i>u</i>(&#x03C0;).</p>
</exercise>
<exercise id="ex_3_3_5">
<label>5</label>
<p role="noindent">Consider the process described in the text in which an<i>n</i>-card deck is repeatedly labelled and 2-unshuffled, in the manner described in the proof ofTheorem 3.9. (See Figures 3.10 and 3.13.) The process continues until thelabels are all different. Show that the process never terminates until at least
<math display="inline">
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2308;</mo><msub><mi>log</mi><mn>2</mn></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>&#x2309;</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
unshuffles have been done.</p>
</exercise>
</sec>
</sec>
</chapter>


<chapter id ="chap5">
<label>Chapter 5</label>
<title>Important Distributions and Densities</title>
<target target-type="page" id="page_183">183</target>
<sec id="5.1">
<label>5.1</label>
<title>Important Distributions</title>
<p role="noindent">In this chapter, we describe the discrete probability distributions and the continuous probability densities that occur most often in the analysis of experiments. We will also show how one simulates these distributions and densities on a computer.</p>
<sec>
<title>Discrete Uniform Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">In Chapter 1, we saw that in many cases, we assume that all outcomes of an experiment are equally likely. If X is a random variable which represents the outcome of an experiment of this type, then we say that X is uniformly distributed. If the sample space S is of size n, where 0 &lt; n &lt; &#x221E;, then the distribution function m(&#x03C9;) is defined to be 1/n for all &#x03C9; &#x2208; S. As is the case with all of the discrete probability distributions discussed in this chapter, this experiment can be simulated on a computer using the program GeneralSimulation. However, in this case, a faster algorithm can be used instead. (This algorithm was described in Chapter 1; we repeat the description here for completeness.) The expression</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mo stretchy='false'>[</mo><mi>n</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>]</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">takes on as a value each integer between 1 and n with probability 1/n (the notation &#x230A;x&#x230B; denotes the greatest integer not exceeding x). Thus, if the possible outcomes of the experiment are labelled &#x03C9;<sub>1</sub> &#x03C9;<sub>2</sub>, . . ., &#x03C9;<sub>n</sub>, then we use the above expression to represent the subscript of the output of the experiment.</p>
<p role="noindent">If the sample space is a countably infinite set, such as the set of positive integers, then it is not possible to have an experiment which is uniform on this set (see Exercise 3). If the sample space is an uncountable set, with positive, finite length, such as the interval [0, 1], then we use continuous density functions (see Section 5.2).</p>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_184">184</target>
<sec>
<title>Binomial Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">The binomial distribution with parameters n, p, and k was defined in Chapter 3. It is the distribution of the random variable which counts the number of heads which occur when a coin is tossed n times, assuming that on any one toss, the probability that a head occurs is p. The distribution function is given by the formula</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>b</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>k</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>k</mi><mi>p</mi><mi>k</mi><mi>q</mi><mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>k</mi></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">where q = 1 &#x2212; p.</p>
<p role="noindent">One straightforward way to simulate a binomial random variable X is to compute the sum of n independent 0&#x2212;1 random variables, each of which take on the value 1 with probability p. This method requires n calls to a random number generator to obtain one value of the random variable. When n is relatively large (say at least 30), the Central Limit Theorem (see Chapter 9) implies that the binomial distribution is well-approximated by the corresponding normal density function (which is defined in Section 5.2) with parameters &#x03BC; = np and &#x03C3; =<inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>npq</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, in this case we can compute a value Y of a normal random variable with these parameters, and if &#x2212;1/2 &#x2264; Y &lt; n + 1/2, we can use the value</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo stretchy='false'>[</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>]</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">to represent the random variable X. If Y &lt; &#x2212;1/2 or Y &gt; n + 1/2, we reject Y and compute another value. We will see in the next section how we can quickly simulate normal random variables.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Geometric Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">Consider a Bernoulli trials process continued for an infinite number of trials; for example, a coin tossed an infinite sequence of times. We showed in Section 2.2 how to assign a probability distribution to the infinite tree. Thus, we can determine the distribution for any random variable X relating to the experiment provided P(X = a) can be computed in terms of a finite number of trials. For example, let T be the number of trials up to and including the first success. Then</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>q</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>3</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>q</mi><mn>2</mn><mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">and in general,</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>n</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>n</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mi>p</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">To show that this is a distribution, we must show that</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>q</mi><mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mn>2</mn>
</msup>
<mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><mo>&#x22EF;</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1.</mn></mrow>
</math>

<target target-type="page" id="page_185">185</target>
<fig id="fig_5_1">
<label>Figure 5.1</label>
<caption>Geometric distributions.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">The left-hand expression is just a geometric series with first term p and common ratio q, so its sum is</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>p</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>q</mi></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">which equals 1.</p>
<p role="noindent">In Figure 5.1 we have plotted this distribution using the program<bold>GeometricPlot</bold> for the cases p = .5 and p = .2. We see that as p decreases we are more likely to get large values for T, as would be expected. In both cases, the most probable value for T is 1. This will always be true since</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mfrac>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo></mrow>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo></mrow>
</mfrac>
<mo>=</mo><mi>q</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">In general, if 0 &lt; p &lt; 1, and q = 1 &#x2212; p, then we say that the random variable T has a geometric distribution if</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mi>p</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">for j = 1, 2, 3, . . . .</p>
<p role="noindent">To simulate the geometric distribution with parameter p, we can simply compute a sequence of random numbers in [0, 1), stopping when an entry does not exceed p. However, for small values of p, this is time-consuming (taking, on the average, 1/p steps). We now describe a method whose running time does not depend upon the size of p. Define Y to be the smallest integer satisfying the inequality</p>

<label>(5.1)</label>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mi>Y</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2265;</mo><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">Then we have</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>j</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mi>j</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2265;</mo><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mi>j</mi>
</msup>
<mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>q</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>j</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mi>p</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<target target-type="page" id="page_186">186</target>
<p role="noindent">Thus, Y is geometrically distributed with parameter p. To generate Y, all we have to do is solve Equation 5.1 for Y. We obtain</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>Y</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>q</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">where the notation &#x2308;x&#x2309; means the least integer which is greater than or equal to x. Since log(1&#x2212;rnd) and log(rnd) are identically distributed, Y can also be generated using the equation</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>Y</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow>
</math>


<label>Example 5.1</label>
<p role="noindent">The geometric distribution plays an important role in the theory of queues, or waiting lines. For example, suppose a line of customers waits for service at a counter. It is often assumed that, in each small time unit, either 0 or 1 new customers arrive at the counter. The probability that a customer arrives is p and that no customer arrives is q = 1 &#x2212; p. Then the time T until the next arrival has a geometric distribution. It is natural to ask for the probability that no customer arrives in the next k time units, that is, for P(T &gt; k). This is given by</p>
<p role="noindent">P(T>k)=∑j=k+1∞qj−1p=qk(p+qp+q2p+⋯)=qk.</p>
<p role="noindent">This probability can also be found by noting that we are asking for no successes (i.e., arrivals) in a sequence of k consecutive time units, where the probability of a success in any one time unit is p. Thus, the probability is just q<sup>k</sup>, since arrivals in any two time units are independent events.</p>
<p role="noindent">It is often assumed that the length of time required to service a customer also has a geometric distribution but with a different value for p. This implies a rather special property of the service time. To see this, let us compute the conditional probability</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mi>r</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>s</mi><mo>&#x007C;</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mi>r</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mi>r</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>s</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>T</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mi>r</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>q</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>s</mi><mi>q</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>q</mi><mi>s</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">Thus, the probability that the customer&#x2019;s service takes s more time units is independent of the length of time r that the customer has already been served. Because of this interpretation, this property is called the &#x201C;memoryless&#x201D; property, and is also obeyed by the exponential distribution. (Fortunately, not too many service stations have this property.) &#x25A1;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<title>Negative Binomial Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">Suppose we are given a coin which has probability p of coming up heads when it is tossed. We fix a positive integer k, and toss the coin until the kth head appears. We</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_187">187</target>
<p role="noindent">let X represent the number of tosses. When k = 1, X is geometrically distributed. For a general k, we say that X has a negative binomial distribution. We now calculate the probability distribution of X. If X = x, then it must be true that there were exactly k &#x2212; 1 heads thrown in the first x &#x2212; 1 tosses, and a head must have been thrown on the xth toss. There are</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>/</mo><mi>k</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">sequences of length x with these properties, and each of them is assigned the same probability, namely</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<msup>
<mi>p</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>k</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow>
</msup>
<mo>/</mo><msup>
<mi>q</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>k</mi></mrow>
</msup>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">Therefore, if we define</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>u</mi>
<mo stretchy='false'>
  (</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>k</mi><mo>,</mo><mi>p</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo>
<mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">then</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-negbinom-formula">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">One can simulate this on a computer by simulating the tossing of a coin. The following algorithm is, in general, much faster. We note that X can be understood as the sum of k outcomes of a geometrically distributed experiment with parameter p. Thus, we can use the following sum as a means of generating X:</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo><mi>j</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mi>k</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>d</mi><mi>j</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>q</mi></mrow>
</math>

<label>Example 5.2</label>
<p role="noindent">A fair coin is tossed until the second time a head turns up. The distribution for the number of tosses is u(x, 2, p). Thus the probability that x tosses are needed to obtain two heads is found by letting k = 2 in the above formula. We obtain</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-example5.2">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">for x = 2, 3, . . . .</p>
<p role="noindent">In Figure 5.2 we give a graph of the distribution for k = 2 and p = .25. Note that the distribution is quite asymmetric, with a long tail reflecting the fact that large values of x are possible. &#x25A1;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<title>Poisson Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">The Poisson distribution arises in many situations. It is safe to say that it is one of the three most important discrete probability distributions (the other two being the uniform and the binomial distributions). The Poisson distribution can be viewed as arising from the binomial distribution or from the exponential density. We shall now explain its connection with the former; its connection with the latter will be explained in the next section.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_188">188</target>
<fig id="fig_5_2">
<label>Figure 5.2</label>
<caption>Negative binomial distribution with k = 2 and p = .25.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we have a situation in which a certain kind of occurrence happens at random over a period of time. For example, the occurrences that we are interested in might be incoming telephone calls to a police station in a large city. We want to model this situation so that we can consider the probabilities of events such as more than 10 phone calls occurring in a 5-minute time interval. Presumably, in our example, there would be more incoming calls between 6:00 and 7:00 P.M. than between 4:00 and 5:00 A.M., and this fact would certainly affect the above probability. Thus, to have a hope of computing such probabilities, we must assume that the average rate, i.e., the average number of occurrences per minute, is a constant. This rate we will denote by &#x03BB;. (Thus, in a given 5-minute time interval, we would expect about 5&#x03BB; occurrences.) This means that if we were to apply our model to the two time periods given above, we would simply use different rates for the two time periods, thereby obtaining two different probabilities for the given event.</p>
<p role="noindent">Our next assumption is that the number of occurrences in two non-overlapping time intervals are independent. In our example, this means that the events that there are j calls between 5:00 and 5:15 P.M. and k calls between 6:00 and 6:15 P.M. on the same day are independent.</p>
<p role="noindent">We can use the binomial distribution to model this situation. We imagine that a given time interval is broken up into n subintervals of equal length. If the subintervals are sufficiently short, we can assume that two or more occurrences happen in one subinterval with a probability which is negligible in comparison with the probability of at most one occurrence. Thus, in each subinterval, we are assuming that there is either 0 or 1 occurrence. This means that the sequence of subintervals can be thought of as a sequence of Bernoulli trials, with a success corresponding to an occurrence in the subinterval.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_189">189</target>
<p role="noindent">To decide upon the proper value of p, the probability of an occurrence in a given subinterval, we reason as follows. On the average, there are &#x03BB;t occurrences in a time interval of length t. If this time interval is divided into n subintervals, then we would expect, using the Bernoulli trials interpretation, that there should be np occurrences. Thus, we want</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mi>t</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>n</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">so</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>p</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mi>t</mi><mo>/</mo><mi>n</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">We now wish to consider the random variable X, which counts the number of occurrences in a given time interval. We want to calculate the distribution of X. For ease of calculation, we will assume that the time interval is of length 1; for time intervals of arbitrary length t, see Exercise 11. We know that</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-poisson-px0">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">For large n, this is approximately e<sup>&#x2212;&#x03BB;</sup>. It is easy to calculate that for any fixed k, we have</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-poisson-ratio">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>kq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">which, for large n (and therefore small p) is approximately &#x03BB;/k. Thus, we have</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-poisson-px1">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">and in general,</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-5.2">
<label>(5.2)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">The above distribution is the Poisson distribution. We note that it must be checked that the distribution given in Equation 5.2 really is a distribution, i.e., that its values are non-negative and sum to 1. (See Exercise 12.)</p>
<p role="noindent">The Poisson distribution is used as an approximation to the binomial distribution when the parameters n and p are large and small, respectively (see Examples 5.3 and 5.4). However, the Poisson distribution also arises in situations where it may not be easy to interpret or measure the parameters n and p (see Example 5.5).</p>

<label>Example 5.3</label>
<p role="noindent">A typesetter makes, on the average, one mistake per 1000 words. Assume that he is setting a book with 100 words to a page. Let S<sub>100</sub> be the number of mistakes that he makes on a single page. Then the exact probability distribution for S<sub>100</sub> would be obtained by considering S<sub>100</sub> as a result of 100 Bernoulli trials with p = 1/1000. The expected value of S<sub>100</sub> is &#x03BB; = 100(1/1000) = .1. The exact probability that S<sub>100</sub> = j is b(100, 1/1000, j), and the Poisson approximation is</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-example5.3-poisson">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">In Table 5.1 we give, for various values of n and p, the exact values computed by the binomial distribution and the Poisson approximation. &#x25A1;</p>

<target target-type="page" id="page_190">190</target>
<table-wrap id="table_5_1">
<label>Table 5.1</label>
<caption>Poisson approximation to the binomial distribution.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th><th>Poisson</th><th>Binomial</th><th>Poisson</th><th>Binomial</th><th>Poisson</th><th>Binomial</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th></th><th></th><th>n = 100</th><th></th><th>n = 100</th><th></th><th>n = 1000</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>j</th><th>&#x03BB; = .1</th><th>p = .001</th><th>&#x03BB; = 1</th><th>p = .01</th><th>&#x03BB; = 10</th><th>p = .01</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>.9048</td>
<td>.9048</td>
<td>.3679</td>
<td>.3660</td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.0000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>.0905</td>
<td>.0905</td>
<td>.3679</td>
<td>.3697</td>
<td>.0005</td>
<td>.0004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>.0045</td>
<td>.0045</td>
<td>.1839</td>
<td>.1849</td>
<td>.0023</td>
<td>.0022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>.0613</td>
<td>.0610</td>
<td>.0076</td>
<td>.0074</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.0153</td>
<td>.0149</td>
<td>.0189</td>
<td>.0186</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0031</td>
<td>.0029</td>
<td>.0378</td>
<td>.0374</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0005</td>
<td>.0005</td>
<td>.0631</td>
<td>.0627</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0001</td>
<td>.0001</td>
<td>.0901</td>
<td>.0900</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.1126</td>
<td>.1128</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.1251</td>
<td>.1256</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.1251</td>
<td>.1257</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>11</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.1137</td>
<td>.1143</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>12</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0948</td>
<td>.0952</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>13</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0729</td>
<td>.0731</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>14</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0521</td>
<td>.0520</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0347</td>
<td>.0345</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0217</td>
<td>.0215</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0128</td>
<td>.0126</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0071</td>
<td>.0069</td></tr>
<tr><td>19</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td>
<td>.0037</td>
<td>.0036</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0019</td>
<td>.0018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0009</td>
<td>.0009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0004</td>
<td>.0004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0002</td>
<td>.0002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0001</td>
<td>.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>.0000</td>
<td>.0000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<target target-type="page" id="page_191">191</target>

<label>Example 5.4</label>
<p role="noindent">In his book, Feller discusses the statistics of flying bomb hits in the south of London during the Second World War.</p>
<p role="noindent">Assume that you live in a district of size 10 blocks by 10 blocks so that the total district is divided into 100 small squares. How likely is it that the square in which you live will receive no hits if the total area is hit by 400 bombs?</p>
<p role="noindent">We assume that a particular bomb will hit your square with probability 1/100. Since there are 400 bombs, we can regard the number of hits that your square receives as the number of successes in a Bernoulli trials process with n = 400 and p = 1/100. Thus we can use the Poisson distribution with &#x03BB; = 400 &#x00B7; 1/100 = 4 to approximate the probability that your square will receive j hits. This probability is p(j) = e<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>4<sup>j</sup>/j!. The expected number of squares that receive exactly j hits is then 100 &#x00B7; p(j). It is easy to write a program<bold>LondonBombs</bold> to simulate this situation and compare the expected number of squares with j hits with the observed number. In Exercise 26 you are asked to compare the actual observed data with that predicted by the Poisson distribution.</p>
<p role="noindent">In Figure 5.3, we have shown the simulated hits, together with a spike graph showing both the observed and predicted frequencies. The observed frequencies are shown as squares, and the predicted frequencies are shown as dots. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="noindent">If the reader would rather not consider flying bombs, he is invited to instead consider an analogous situation involving cookies and raisins. We assume that we have made enough cookie dough for 500 cookies. We put 600 raisins in the dough, and mix it thoroughly. One way to look at this situation is that we have 500 cookies, and after placing the cookies in a grid on the table, we throw 600 raisins at the cookies. (See Exercise 22.)</p>

<label>Example 5.5</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that in a certain fixed amount A of blood, the average human has 40 white blood cells. Let X be the random variable which gives the number of white blood cells in a random sample of size A from a random individual. We can think of X as binomially distributed with each white blood cell in the body representing a trial. If a given white blood cell turns up in the sample, then the trial corresponding to that blood cell was a success. Then p should be taken as the ratio of A to the total amount of blood in the individual, and n will be the number of white blood cells in the individual. Of course, in practice, neither of these parameters is very easy to measure accurately, but presumably the number 40 is easy to measure. But for the average human, we then have 40 = np, so we can think of X as being Poisson distributed, with parameter &#x03BB; = 40. In this case, it is easier to model the situation using the Poisson distribution than the binomial distribution. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="noindent">To simulate a Poisson random variable on a computer, a good way is to take advantage of the relationship between the Poisson distribution and the exponential density. This relationship and the resulting simulation algorithm will be described in the next section.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_192">192</target>
<fig id="fig_5_3">
<label>Figure 5.3</label>
<caption>Flying bomb hits.</caption>
</fig>
<target target-type="page" id="page_193">193</target>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Hypergeometric Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we have a set of N balls, of which k are red and N &#x2212; k are blue. We choose n of these balls, without replacement, and define X to be the number of red balls in our sample. The distribution of X is called the hypergeometric distribution. We note that this distribution depends upon three parameters, namely N, k, and n. There does not seem to be a standard notation for this distribution; we will use the notation h(N, k, n, x) to denote P(X = x). This probability can be found by noting that there are</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-hyper-choose">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">different samples of size n, and the number of such samples with exactly x red balls is obtained by multiplying the number of ways of choosing x red balls from the set of k red balls and the number of ways of choosing n &#x2212; x blue balls from the set of N &#x2212; k blue balls. Hence, we have</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-hypergeometric">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">This distribution can be generalized to the case where there are more than two types of objects. (See Exercise 40.)</p>
<p role="noindent">If we let N and k tend to &#x221E;, in such a way that the ratio k/N remains fixed, then the hypergeometric distribution tends to the binomial distribution with parameters n and p = k/N. This is reasonable because if N and k are much larger than n, then whether we choose our sample with or without replacement should not affect the probabilities very much, and the experiment consisting of choosing with replacement yields a binomially distributed random variable (see Exercise 44).</p>
<p role="noindent">An example of how this distribution might be used is given in Exercises 36 and 37. We now give another example involving the hypergeometric distribution. It illustrates a statistical test called Fisher&#x2019;s Exact Test.</p>
<label>Example 5.6</label>
<p role="noindent">It is often of interest to consider two traits, such as eye color and hair color, and to ask whether there is an association between the two traits. Two traits are associated if knowing the value of one of the traits for a given person allows us to predict the value of the other trait for that person. The stronger the association, the more accurate the predictions become. If there is no association between the traits, then we say that the traits are independent. In this example, we will use the traits of gender and political party, and we will assume that there are only two possible genders, female and male, and only two possible political parties, Democratic and Republican.</p>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we have collected data concerning these traits. To test whether there is an association between the traits, we first assume that there is no association between the two traits. This gives rise to an &#x201C;expected&#x201D; data set, in which knowledge of the value of one trait is of no help in predicting the value of the other trait. Our collected data set usually differs from this expected data set. If it differs by quite a bit, then we would tend to reject the assumption of independence of the traits. To</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_194">194</target>
<table-wrap id="table_5_2">
<label>Table 5.2</label>
<caption>Observed data.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr><th></th><th>Democrat</th><th>Republican</th><th></th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Female</td><td>24</td><td>4</td><td>28</td></tr>
<tr><td>Male</td><td>8</td><td>14</td><td>22</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>32</td><td>18</td><td>50</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table_5_3">
<label>Table 5.3</label>
<caption>General data table.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr><th></th><th>Democrat</th><th>Republican</th><th></th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Female</td><td>s<sub>11</sub></td><td>s<sub>12</sub></td><td>t<sub>11</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td>Male</td><td>s<sub>21</sub></td><td>s<sub>22</sub></td><td>t<sub>12</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>t<sub>21</sub></td><td>t<sub>22</sub></td><td>n</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="noindent">nail down what is meant by &#x201C;quite a bit,&#x201D; we decide which possible data sets differ from the expected data set by at least as much as ours does, and then we compute the probability that any of these data sets would occur under the assumption of independence of traits. If this probability is small, then it is unlikely that the difference between our collected data set and the expected data set is due entirely to chance.</p>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we have collected the data shown in Table 5.2. The row and column sums are called marginal totals, or marginals. In what follows, we will denote the row sums by t<sub>11</sub> and t<sub>12</sub>, and the column sums by t<sub>21</sub> and t<sub>22</sub>. The ijth entry in the table will be denoted by s<sub>ij</sub>. Finally, the size of the data set will be denoted by n. Thus, a general data table will look as shown in Table 5.3. We now explain the model which will be used to construct the &#x201C;expected&#x201D; data set. In the model, we assume that the two traits are independent. We then put t<sub>21</sub> yellow balls and t<sub>22</sub> green balls, corresponding to the Democratic and Republican marginals, into an urn. We draw t<sub>11</sub> balls, without replacement, from the urn, and call these balls females. The t<sub>12</sub> balls remaining in the urn are called males. In the specific case under consideration, the probability of getting the actual data under this model is given by the expression</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-fisher-exact">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>32</mml:mn><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">i.e., a value of the hypergeometric distribution.</p>
<p role="noindent">We are now ready to construct the expected data set. If we choose 28 balls out of 50, we should expect to see, on the average, the same percentage of yellow balls in our sample as in the urn. Thus, we should expect to see, on the average, 28(32/50) = 17.92 &#x2248; 18 yellow balls in our sample. (See Exercise 36.) The other expected values are computed in exactly the same way. Thus, the expected data set is shown in Table 5.4. We note that the value of s<sub>11</sub> determines the other three values in the table, since the marginals are all fixed. Thus, in considering the possible data sets that could appear in this model, it is enough to consider the various possible values of s<sub>11</sub>. In the specific case at hand, what is the probability</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_195">195</target>
<table-wrap id="table_5_4">
<label>Table 5.4</label>
<caption>Expected data.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr><th></th><th>Democrat</th><th>Republican</th><th></th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Female</td><td>18</td><td>10</td><td>28</td></tr>
<tr><td>Male</td><td>14</td><td>8</td><td>22</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>32</td><td>18</td><td>50</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p role="noindent">of drawing exactly a yellow balls, i.e., what is the probability that s<sub>11</sub> = a? It is</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-5.3">
<label>(5.3)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>32</mml:mn><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">We are now ready to decide whether our actual data differs from the expected data set by an amount which is greater than could be reasonably attributed to chance alone. We note that the expected number of female Democrats is 18, but the actual number in our data is 24. The other data sets which differ from the expected data set by more than ours correspond to those where the number of female Democrats equals 25, 26, 27, or 28. Thus, to obtain the required probability, we sum the expression in (5.3) from a = 24 to a = 28. We obtain a value of .000395. Thus, we should reject the hypothesis that the two traits are independent. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="noindent">Finally, we turn to the question of how to simulate a hypergeometric random variable X. Let us assume that the parameters for X are N, k, and n. We imagine that we have a set of N balls, labelled from 1 to N. We decree that the first k of these balls are red, and the rest are blue. Suppose that we have chosen m balls, and that j of them are red. Then there are k &#x2212; j red balls left, and N &#x2212; m balls left. Thus, our next choice will be red with probability</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-hyper-sim">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">So at this stage, we choose a random number in [0, 1], and report that a red ball has been chosen if and only if the random number does not exceed the above expression. Then we update the values of m and j, and continue until n balls have been chosen.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Benford Distribution</title>
<p role="noindent">Our next example of a distribution comes from the study of leading digits in data sets. It turns out that many data sets that occur &#x201C;in real life&#x201D; have the property that the first digits of the data are not uniformly distributed over the set {1, 2, . . ., 9}. Rather, it appears that the digit 1 is most likely to occur, and that the distribution is monotonically decreasing on the set of possible digits. The Benford distribution appears, in many cases, to fit such data. Many explanations have been given for the occurrence of this distribution. Possibly the most convincing explanation is that this distribution is the only one that is invariant under a change of scale. If one thinks of certain data sets as somehow &#x201C;naturally occurring,&#x201D; then the distribution should be unaffected by which units are chosen in which to represent the data, i.e., the distribution should be invariant under change of scale.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_196">196</target>
<fig id="fig_5_4">
<label>Figure 5.4</label>
<caption>Leading digits in President Clinton&#x2019;s tax returns.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">Theodore Hill gives a general description of the Benford distribution, when one considers the first d digits of integers in a data set. We will restrict our attention to the first digit. In this case, the Benford distribution has distribution function</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-benford">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">for 1 &#x2264; k &#x2264; 9.</p>
<p role="noindent">Mark Nigrini has advocated the use of the Benford distribution as a means of testing suspicious financial records such as bookkeeping entries, checks, and tax returns. His idea is that if someone were to &#x201C;make up&#x201D; numbers in these cases, the person would probably produce numbers that are fairly uniformly distributed, while if one were to use the actual numbers, the leading digits would roughly follow the Benford distribution. As an example, Nigrini analyzed President Clinton&#x2019;s tax returns for a 13-year period. In Figure 5.4, the Benford distribution values are shown as squares, and the President&#x2019;s tax return data are shown as circles. One sees that in this example, the Benford distribution fits the data very well.</p>
<p role="noindent">This distribution was discovered by the astronomer Simon Newcomb who stated the following in his paper on the subject: &#x201C;That the ten digits do not occur with equal frequency must be evident to anyone making use of logarithm tables, and noticing how much faster the first pages wear out than the last ones. The first significant figure is oftener 1 than any other digit, and the frequency diminishes up to 9.&#x201D;</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_197">197</target>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol>
<li><p role="noindent">For which of the following random variables would it be appropriate to assign a uniform distribution? (a) Let X represent the roll of one die. (b) Let X represent the number of heads obtained in three tosses of a coin. (c) A roulette wheel has 38 possible outcomes: 0, 00, and 1 through 36. Let X represent the outcome when a roulette wheel is spun. (d) Let X represent the birthday of a randomly chosen person. (e) Let X represent the number of tosses of a coin necessary to achieve a head for the first time.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let n be a positive integer. Let S be the set of integers between 1 and n. Consider the following process: We remove a number from S at random and write it down. We repeat this until S is empty. The result is a permutation of the integers from 1 to n. Let X denote this permutation. Is X uniformly distributed?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable which can take on countably many values. Show that X cannot be uniformly distributed.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose we are attending a college which has 3000 students. We wish to choose a subset of size 100 from the student body. Let X represent the subset, chosen using the following possible strategies. For which strategies would it be appropriate to assign the uniform distribution to X? If it is appropriate, what probability should we assign to each outcome? (a) Take the first 100 students who enter the cafeteria to eat lunch. (b) Ask the Registrar to sort the students by their Social Security number, and then take the first 100 in the resulting list. (c) Ask the Registrar for a set of cards, with each card containing the name of exactly one student, and with each student appearing on exactly one card. Throw the cards out of a third-story window, then walk outside and pick up the first 100 cards that you find.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Under the same conditions as in the preceding exercise, can you describe a procedure which, if used, would produce each possible outcome with the same probability? Can you describe such a procedure that does not rely on a computer or a calculator?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, . . . , X<sub>n</sub> be n mutually independent random variables, each of which is uniformly distributed on the integers from 1 to k. Let Y denote the minimum of the X<sub>i</sub>&#x2019;s. Find the distribution of Y.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A die is rolled until the first time T that a six turns up. (a) What is the probability distribution for T?</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_198">198</target>
<li><p role="noindent">(b) Find P(T &gt; 3). (c) Find P(T &gt; 6|T &gt; 3).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">If a coin is tossed a sequence of times, what is the probability that the first head will occur after the fifth toss, given that it has not occurred in the first two tosses?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A worker for the Department of Fish and Game is assigned the job of estimating the number of trout in a certain lake of modest size. She proceeds as follows: She catches 100 trout, tags each of them, and puts them back in the lake. One month later, she catches 100 more trout, and notes that 10 of them have tags. (a) Without doing any fancy calculations, give a rough estimate of the number of trout in the lake. (b) Let N be the number of trout in the lake. Find an expression, in terms of N, for the probability that the worker would catch 10 tagged trout out of the 100 trout that she caught the second time. (c) Find the value of N which maximizes the expression in part (b). This value is called the maximum likelihood estimate for the unknown quantity N. Hint: Consider the ratio of the expressions for successive values of N.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A census in the United States is an attempt to count everyone in the country. It is inevitable that many people are not counted. The U. S. Census Bureau proposed a way to estimate the number of people who were not counted by the latest census. Their proposal was as follows: In a given locality, let N denote the actual number of people who live there. Assume that the census counted n<sub>1</sub> people living in this area. Now, another census was taken in the locality, and n<sub>2</sub> people were counted. In addition, n<sub>12</sub> people were counted both times. (a) Given N, n<sub>1</sub>, and n<sub>2</sub>, let X denote the number of people counted both times. Find the probability that X = k, where k is a fixed positive integer between 0 and n<sub>2</sub>. (b) Now assume that X = n<sub>12</sub>. Find the value of N which maximizes the expression in part (a). Hint: Consider the ratio of the expressions for successive values of N.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose that X is a random variable which represents the number of calls coming in to a police station in a one-minute interval. In the text, we showed that X could be modelled using a Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB;, where this parameter represents the average number of incoming calls per minute. Now suppose that Y is a random variable which represents the number of incoming calls in an interval of length t. Show that the distribution of Y is given by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-ex11-poisson-t">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_199">199</target>
<li><p role="noindent">i.e., Y is Poisson with parameter &#x03BB;t. Hint: Suppose a Martian were to observe the police station. Let us also assume that the basic time interval used on Mars is exactly t Earth minutes. Finally, we will assume that the Martian understands the derivation of the Poisson distribution in the text. What would she write down for the distribution of Y?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Show that the values of the Poisson distribution given in Equation 5.2 sum to 1.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">The Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; = .3 has been assigned for the outcome of an experiment. Let X be the outcome function. Find P(X = 0), P(X = 1), and P(X &gt; 1).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">On the average, only 1 person in 1000 has a particular rare blood type. (a) Find the probability that, in a city of 10,000 people, no one has this blood type. (b) How many people would have to be tested to give a probability greater than 1/2 of finding at least one person with this blood type?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Write a program for the user to input n, p, j and have the program print out the exact value of b(n, p, k) and the Poisson approximation to this value.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Assume that, during each second, a Dartmouth switchboard receives one call with probability .01 and no calls with probability .99. Use the Poisson approximation to estimate the probability that the operator will miss at most one call if she takes a 5-minute coffee break.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">The probability of a royal flush in a poker hand is p = 1/649,740. How large must n be to render the probability of having no royal flush in n hands smaller than 1/e?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A baker blends 600 raisins and 400 chocolate chips into a dough mix and, from this, makes 500 cookies. (a) Find the probability that a randomly picked cookie will have no raisins. (b) Find the probability that a randomly picked cookie will have exactly two chocolate chips. (c) Find the probability that a randomly chosen cookie will have at least two bits (raisins or chips) in it.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">The probability that, in a bridge deal, one of the four hands has all hearts is approximately 6.3 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;12</sup>. In a city with about 50,000 bridge players the resident probability expert is called on the average once a year (usually late at night) and told that the caller has just been dealt a hand of all hearts. Should she suspect that some of these callers are the victims of practical jokes?</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_200">200</target>
<li><p role="noindent">An advertiser drops 10,000 leaflets on a city which has 2000 blocks. Assume that each leaflet has an equal chance of landing on each block. What is the probability that a particular block will receive no leaflets?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">In a class of 80 students, the professor calls on 1 student chosen at random for a recitation in each class period. There are 32 class periods in a term. (a) Write a formula for the exact probability that a given student is called upon j times during the term. (b) Write a formula for the Poisson approximation for this probability. Using your formula estimate the probability that a given student is called upon more than twice.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Assume that we are making raisin cookies. We put a box of 600 raisins into our dough mix, mix up the dough, then make from the dough 500 cookies. We then ask for the probability that a randomly chosen cookie will have 0, 1, 2, . . . raisins. Consider the cookies as trials in an experiment, and let X be the random variable which gives the number of raisins in a given cookie. Then we can regard the number of raisins in a cookie as the result of n = 600 independent trials with probability p = 1/500 for success on each trial. Since n is large and p is small, we can use the Poisson approximation with &#x03BB; = 600(1/500) = 1.2. Determine the probability that a given cookie will have at least five raisins.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">For a certain experiment, the Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; = m has been assigned. Show that a most probable outcome for the experiment is the integer value k such that m &#x2212; 1 &#x2264; k &#x2264; m. Under what conditions will there be two most probable values? Hint: Consider the ratio of successive probabilities.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">When John Kemeny was chair of the Mathematics Department at Dartmouth College, he received an average of ten letters each day. On a certain weekday he received no mail and wondered if it was a holiday. To decide this he computed the probability that, in ten years, he would have at least 1 day without any mail. He assumed that the number of letters he received on a given day has a Poisson distribution. What probability did he find? Hint: Apply the Poisson distribution twice. First, to find the probability that, in 3000 days, he will have at least 1 day without mail, assuming each year has about 300 days on which mail is delivered.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Reese Prosser never puts money in a 10-cent parking meter in Hanover. He assumes that there is a probability of .05 that he will be caught. The first offense costs nothing, the second costs 2 dollars, and subsequent offenses cost 5 dollars each. Under his assumptions, how does the expected cost of parking 100 times without paying the meter compare with the cost of paying the meter each time?</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_201">201</target>
<li><p role="noindent">Feller discusses the statistics of flying bomb hits in an area in the south of London during the Second World War. The area in question was divided into 24 &#x00D7; 24 = 576 small areas. The total number of hits was 537. There were 229 squares with 0 hits, 211 with 1 hit, 93 with 2 hits, 35 with 3 hits, 7 with 4 hits, and 1 with 5 or more. Assuming the hits were purely random, use the Poisson approximation to find the probability that a particular square would have exactly k hits. Compute the expected number of squares that would have 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 or more hits and compare this with the observed results.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Assume that the probability that there is a significant accident in a nuclear power plant during one year&#x2019;s time is .001. If a country has 100 nuclear plants, estimate the probability that there is at least one such accident during a given year.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">An airline finds that 4 percent of the passengers that make reservations on a particular flight will not show up. Consequently, their policy is to sell 100 reserved seats on a plane that has only 98 seats. Find the probability that every person who shows up for the flight will find a seat available.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">The king&#x2019;s coinmaster boxes his coins 500 to a box and puts 1 counterfeit coin in each box. The king is suspicious, but, instead of testing all the coins in 1 box, he tests 1 coin chosen at random out of each of 500 boxes. What is the probability that he finds at least one fake? What is it if the king tests 2 coins from each of 250 boxes?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">(From Kemeny) Show that, if you make 100 bets on the number 17 at roulette at Monte Carlo (see Example 6.13), you will have a probability greater than 1/2 of coming out ahead. What is your expected winning?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">In one of the first studies of the Poisson distribution, von Bortkiewicz considered the frequency of deaths from kicks in the Prussian army corps. From the study of 14 corps over a 20-year period, he obtained the data shown in Table 5.5. Fit a Poisson distribution to this data and see if you think that the Poisson distribution is appropriate.</p>
<table-wrap id="table_5_5">
<label>Table 5.5</label>
<caption>Mule kicks.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr><th>Number of deaths</th><th>Number of corps with x deaths in a given year</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>144</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_202">202</target>
<li><p role="noindent">It is often assumed that the auto traffic that arrives at the intersection during a unit time period has a Poisson distribution with expected value m. Assume that the number of cars X that arrive at an intersection from the north in unit time has a Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; = m and the number Y that arrive from the west in unit time has a Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; =<overline>m</overline>. If X and Y are independent, show that the total number X + Y that arrive at the intersection in unit time has a Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; = m +<overline>m</overline>.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Cars coming along Magnolia Street come to a fork in the road and have to choose either Willow Street or Main Street to continue. Assume that the number of cars that arrive at the fork in unit time has a Poisson distribution with parameter &#x03BB; = 4. A car arriving at the fork chooses Main Street with probability 3/4 and Willow Street with probability 1/4. Let X be the random variable which counts the number of cars that, in a given unit of time, pass by Joe&#x2019;s Barber Shop on Main Street. What is the distribution of X?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">In the appeal of the People v. Collins case (see Exercise 4.1.28), the counsel for the defense argued as follows: Suppose, for example, there are 5,000,000 couples in the Los Angeles area and the probability that a randomly chosen couple fits the witnesses&#x2019; description is 1/12,000,000. Then the probability that there are two such couples given that there is at least one is not at all small. Find this probability. (The California Supreme Court overturned the initial guilty verdict.)</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A manufactured lot of brass turnbuckles has S items of which D are defective. A sample of s items is drawn without replacement. Let X be a random variable that gives the number of defective items in the sample. Let p(d) = P(X = d). (a) Show that</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-ex35-hyper">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Thus, X is hypergeometric. (b) Prove the following identity, known as Euler&#x2019;s formula:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-euler-formula">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</li>
<li><p role="noindent">A bin of 1000 turnbuckles has an unknown number D of defectives. A sample of 100 turnbuckles has 2 defectives. The maximum likelihood estimate for D is the number of defectives which gives the highest probability for obtaining the number of defectives observed in the sample. Guess this number D and then write a computer program to verify your guess.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">There are an unknown number of moose on Isle Royale (a National Park in Lake Superior). To estimate the number of moose, 50 moose are captured and</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_203">203</target>
<li><p role="noindent">tagged. Six months later 200 moose are captured and it is found that 8 of these were tagged. Estimate the number of moose on Isle Royale from these data, and then verify your guess by computer program (see Exercise 36).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A manufactured lot of buggy whips has 20 items, of which 5 are defective. A random sample of 5 items is chosen to be inspected. Find the probability that the sample contains exactly one defective item (a) if the sampling is done with replacement. (b) if the sampling is done without replacement.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose that N and k tend to &#x221E; in such a way that k/N remains fixed. Show that</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-ex39">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</li>
<li><p role="noindent">A bridge deck has 52 cards with 13 cards in each of four suits: spades, hearts, diamonds, and clubs. A hand of 13 cards is dealt from a shuffled deck. Find the probability that the hand has (a) a distribution of suits 4, 4, 3, 2 (for example, four spades, four hearts, three diamonds, two clubs). (b) a distribution of suits 5, 3, 3, 2.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Write a computer algorithm that simulates a hypergeometric random variable with parameters N, k, and n.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">You are presented with four different dice. The first one has two sides marked 0 and four sides marked 4. The second one has a 3 on every side. The third one has a 2 on four sides and a 6 on two sides, and the fourth one has a 1 on three sides and a 5 on three sides. You allow your friend to pick any of the four dice he wishes. Then you pick one of the remaining three and you each roll your die. The person with the largest number showing wins a dollar. Show that you can choose your die so that you have probability 2/3 of winning no matter which die your friend picks.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">The students in a certain class were classified by hair color and eye color. The conventions used were: Brown and black hair were considered dark, and red and blonde hair were considered light; black and brown eyes were considered dark, and blue and green eyes were considered light. They collected the data shown in Table 5.6. Are these traits independent? (See Example 5.6.)</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose that in the hypergeometric distribution, we let N and k tend to &#x221E; in such a way that the ratio k/N approaches a real number p between 0 and 1. Show that the hypergeometric distribution tends to the binomial distribution with parameters n and p.</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_204">204</target>
<li><p role="noindent">(a) Compute the leading digits of the first 100 powers of 2, and see how well these data fit the Benford distribution. (b) Multiply each number in the data set of part (a) by 3, and compare the distribution of the leading digits with the Benford distribution.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">In the Powerball lottery, contestants pick 5 different integers between 1 and 45, and in addition, pick a bonus integer from the same range (the bonus integer can equal one of the first five integers chosen). Some contestants choose the numbers themselves, and others let the computer choose the numbers. The data shown in Table 5.7 are the contestant-chosen numbers in a certain state on May 3, 1996. A spike graph of the data is shown in Figure 5.5. The goal of this problem is to check the hypothesis that the chosen numbers are uniformly distributed. To do this, compute the value v of the random variable &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> given in Example 5.6. In the present case, this random variable has 44 degrees of freedom. One can find, in a &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> table, the value v<sub>0</sub> = 59.43, which represents a number with the property that a &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup>-distributed random variable takes on values that exceed v<sub>0</sub> only 5% of the time. Does your computed value of v exceed v<sub>0</sub>? If so, you should reject the hypothesis that the contestants&#x2019; choices are uniformly distributed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table_5_6">
<label>Table 5.6</label>
<caption>Observed data.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Dark Eyes</th>
<th>Light Eyes</th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Dark Hair</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Light Hair</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>37</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig_5_5">
<label>Figure 5.5</label>
<caption>Distribution of choices in the Powerball lottery.</caption>
</fig>
</li>
</ol>
</sec>
<target target-type="page" id="page_205">205</target>
<table-wrap id="table_5_7">
<label>Table 5.7</label>
<caption>Numbers chosen by contestants in the Powerball lottery.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Integer</th>
<th>Times Chosen</th>
<th>Integer</th>
<th>Times Chosen</th>
<th>Integer</th>
<th>Times Chosen</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>2646</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2934</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3352</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>3000</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3357</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>2892</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>3657</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>3025</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>3362</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>2985</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3138</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3043</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>2690</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2423</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>2556</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>2456</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>2479</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>2276</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>2304</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>1971</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>2543</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td>2678</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>2729</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>2414</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>2616</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>2426</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>2381</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>2059</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>2039</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>2298</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31</td>
<td>2081</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>1508</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>1887</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>34</td>
<td>1463</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>1594</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>1354</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>37</td>
<td>1049</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>1165</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>1248</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>1493</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>1322</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>1423</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>43</td>
<td>1207</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>1259</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>1224</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="5.2">
<label>5.2</label>
<title>Important Densities</title>
<p role="noindent">In this section, we will introduce some important probability density functions and give some examples of their use. We will also consider the question of how one simulates a given density using a computer.</p>
<sec>
<title>Continuous Uniform Density</title>
<p role="noindent">The simplest density function corresponds to the random variable U whose value represents the outcome of the experiment consisting of choosing a real number at random from the interval [a, b].</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-uniform-density">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close=""><mml:mtable columnalign="left left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03C9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>otherwise.</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">It is easy to simulate this density on a computer. We simply calculate the expression</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-uniform-sim2">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>rnd</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Exponential and Gamma Densities</title>
<p role="noindent">The exponential density function is defined by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-exponential-density">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close=""><mml:mtable columnalign="left left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x221E;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>otherwise.</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Here &#x03BB; is any positive constant, depending on the experiment. The reader has seen this density in Example 2.17. In Figure 5.6 we show graphs of several exponential densities for different choices of &#x03BB;. The exponential density is often used to</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_206">206</target>
<fig id="fig_5_6">
<label>Figure 5.6</label>
<caption>Exponential densities.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">describe experiments involving a question of the form: How long until something happens? For example, the exponential density is often used to study the time between emissions of particles from a radioactive source.</p>
<p role="noindent">The cumulative distribution function of the exponential density is easy to compute. Let T be an exponentially distributed random variable with parameter &#x03BB;. If x &#x2265; 0, then we have</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-exp-cdf">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x222B;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>dt</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Both the exponential density and the geometric distribution share a property known as the &#x201C;memoryless&#x201D; property. This property was introduced in Example 5.1; it says that</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-memoryless-exp">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">This can be demonstrated to hold for the exponential density by computing both sides of this equation. The right-hand side is just</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-exp-rhs">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">while the left-hand side is</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-exp-lhs">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<target target-type="page" id="page_207">207</target>
<disp-formula id="eq-exp-lhs2">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">There is a very important relationship between the exponential density and the Poisson distribution. We begin by defining X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, . . . to be a sequence of independent exponentially distributed random variables with parameter &#x03BB;. We might think of X<sub>i</sub> as denoting the amount of time between the ith and (i + 1)st emissions of a particle by a radioactive source. (As we shall see in Chapter 6, we can think of the parameter &#x03BB; as representing the reciprocal of the average length of time between emissions. This parameter is a quantity that might be measured in an actual experiment of this type.)</p>
<p role="noindent">We now consider a time interval of length t, and we let Y denote the random variable which counts the number of emissions that occur in the time interval. We would like to calculate the distribution function of Y (clearly, Y is a discrete random variable). If we let S<sub>n</sub> denote the sum X<sub>1</sub> + X<sub>2</sub> + &#x22EF; + X<sub>n</sub>, then it is easy to see that</p>
</sec></sec><disp-formula id="eq-poisson-exp-yn">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext> and</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Since the event S<sub>n+1</sub> &#x2264; t is a subset of the event S<sub>n</sub> &#x2264; t, the above probability is seen to be equal to</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-5.4">
<label>(5.4)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">We will show in Chapter 7 that the density of S<sub>n</sub> is given by the following formula:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-gamma-density">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close=""><mml:mtable columnalign="left left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>otherwise.</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">This density is an example of a gamma density with parameters &#x03BB; and n. The general gamma density allows n to be any positive real number. We shall not discuss this general density.</p>
<p role="noindent">It is easy to show by induction on n that the cumulative distribution function of S<sub>n</sub> is given by:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-gamma-cdf">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close=""><mml:mtable columnalign="left left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x22EF;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>otherwise.</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Using this expression, the quantity in (5.4) is easy to compute; we obtain</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-poisson-from-gamma">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">which the reader will recognize as the probability that a Poisson-distributed random variable, with parameter &#x03BB;t, takes on the value n.</p>
<p role="noindent">The above relationship will allow us to simulate a Poisson distribution, once we have found a way to simulate an exponential density. The following random variable does the job:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-5.5">
<label>(5.5)</label>
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>rnd</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<target target-type="page" id="page_208">208</target>
<p role="noindent">Using Corollary 5.2 (below), one can derive the above expression (see Exercise 3). We content ourselves for now with a short calculation that should convince the reader that the random variable Y has the required property. We have</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-exp-sim-verify">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>rnd</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>rnd</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2265;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>rnd</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2265;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">This last expression is seen to be the cumulative distribution function of an exponentially distributed random variable with parameter &#x03BB;.</p>
<p role="noindent">To simulate a Poisson random variable W with parameter &#x03BB;, we simply generate a sequence of values of an exponentially distributed random variable with the same parameter, and keep track of the subtotals S<sub>k</sub> of these values. We stop generating the sequence when the subtotal first exceeds &#x03BB;. Assume that we find that</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-poisson-sim">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Then the value n is returned as a simulated value for W.</p>
<example id="example-5.7">
<label>Example 5.7</label>
<title>(Queues)</title>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that customers arrive at random times at a service station with one server, and suppose that each customer is served immediately if no one is ahead of him, but must wait his turn in line otherwise. How long should each customer expect to wait? (We define the waiting time of a customer to be the length of time between the time that he arrives and the time that he begins to be served.)</p>
<p role="noindent">Let us assume that the interarrival times between successive customers are given by random variables X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, . . . , X<sub>n</sub> that are mutually independent and identically distributed with an exponential cumulative distribution function given by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-queue-fx">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BB;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Let us assume, too, that the service times for successive customers are given by random variables Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, . . . , Y<sub>n</sub> that again are mutually independent and identically distributed with another exponential cumulative distribution function given by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-queue-fy">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">The parameters &#x03BB; and &#x03BC; represent, respectively, the reciprocals of the average time between arrivals of customers and the average service time of the customers. Thus, for example, the larger the value of &#x03BB;, the smaller the average time between arrivals of customers. We can guess that the length of time a customer will spend in the queue depends on the relative sizes of the average interarrival time and the average service time.</p>
<p role="noindent">It is easy to verify this conjecture by simulation. The program<bold>Queue</bold> simulates this queueing process. Let N(t) be the number of customers in the queue at time t.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_209">209</target>
<fig id="fig_5_7">
<label>Figure 5.7</label>
<caption>Queue sizes.</caption>
</fig>
<fig id="fig_5_8">
<label>Figure 5.8</label>
<caption>Waiting times.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">Then we plot N(t) as a function of t for different choices of the parameters &#x03BB; and &#x03BC; (see Figure 5.7).</p>
<p role="noindent">We note that when &#x03BB; &lt; &#x03BC;, then 1/&#x03BB; &gt; 1/&#x03BC;, so the average interarrival time is greater than the average service time, i.e., customers are served more quickly, on average, than new ones arrive. Thus, in this case, it is reasonable to expect that N(t) remains small. However, if &#x03BB; &gt; &#x03BC; then customers arrive more quickly than they are served, and, as expected, N(t) appears to grow without limit.</p>
<p role="noindent">We can now ask: How long will a customer have to wait in the queue for service? To examine this question, we let W<sub>i</sub> be the length of time that the ith customer has to remain in the system (waiting in line and being served). Then we can present these data in a bar graph, using the program Queue, to give some idea of how the W<sub>i</sub> are distributed (see Figure 5.8). (Here &#x03BB; = 1 and &#x03BC; = 1.1.)</p>
<p role="noindent">We see that these waiting times appear to be distributed exponentially. This is always the case when &#x03BB; &lt; &#x03BC;. The proof of this fact is too complicated to give here, but we can verify it by simulation for different choices of &#x03BB; and &#x03BC;, as above. &#x25A1;</p>

<target target-type="page" id="page_210">210</target>
</sec>
<sec >
<title>Functions of a Random Variable</title>
<p role="noindent">Before continuing our list of important densities, we pause to consider random variables which are functions of other random variables. We will prove a general theorem that will allow us to derive expressions such as Equation 5.5.</p>

<label>Theorem 5.1</label>
<p role="noindent">Let X be a continuous random variable, and suppose that &#x03C6;(x) is a strictly increasing function on the range of X. Define Y = &#x03C6;(X). Suppose that X and Y have cumulative distribution functions F<sub>X</sub> and F<sub>Y</sub> respectively. Then these functions are related by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-thm5.1-inc">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">If &#x03C6;(x) is strictly decreasing on the range of X, then</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-thm5.1-dec">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">Since &#x03C6; is a strictly increasing function on the range of X, the events (X &#x2264; &#x03C6;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(y)) and (&#x03C6;(X) &#x2264; y) are equal. Thus, we have</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mi>Y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mn>..</mn><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">If &#x03C6;(x) is strictly decreasing on the range of X, then we have</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mi>Y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2265;</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C6;</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">This completes the proof. &#x25A1;</p>


<label>Corollary 5.1</label>
<p role="noindent">Let X be a continuous random variable, and suppose that &#x03C6;(x) is a strictly increasing function on the range of X. Define Y = &#x03C6;(X). Suppose that the density functions of X and Y are f<sub>X</sub> and f<sub>Y</sub>, respectively. Then these functions are related by</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-cor5.1-inc">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>dy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">If &#x03C6;(x) is strictly decreasing on the range of X, then</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-cor5.1-dec">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>dy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<target target-type="page" id="page_211">211</target>
<title>Proof.</title>
<p role="noindent">This result follows from Theorem 5.1 by using the Chain Rule. &#x25A1;</p>
<p role="noindent">If the function &#x03C6; is neither strictly increasing nor strictly decreasing, then the situation is somewhat more complicated but can be treated by the same methods. For example, suppose that Y = X<sup>2</sup>, Then &#x03C6;(x) = x<sup>2</sup>, and</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-yx2-cdf">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">Moreover,</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-yx2-pdf">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mtable columnalign="right center left">
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>dy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>dy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">We see that in order to express F<sub>Y</sub> in terms of F<sub>X</sub> when Y = &#x03C6;(X), we have to express P(Y &#x2264; y) in terms of P(X &#x2264; x), and this process will depend in general upon the structure of &#x03C6;.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Simulation</title>
<p role="noindent">Theorem 5.1 tells us, among other things, how to simulate on the computer a random variable Y with a prescribed cumulative distribution function F. We assume that F(y) is strictly increasing for those values of y where 0 &lt; F(y) &lt; 1. For this purpose, let U be a random variable which is uniformly distributed on [0, 1]. Then U has cumulative distribution function F<sub>U</sub>(u) = u. Now, if F is the prescribed cumulative distribution function for Y, then to write Y in terms of U we first solve the equation</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-sim-fy-u">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">for y in terms of u. We obtain y = F<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(u). Note that since F is an increasing function this equation always has a unique solution (see Figure 5.9). Then we set Z = F<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(U) and obtain, by Theorem 5.1,</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-sim-fz">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">since F<sub>U</sub>(u) = u. Therefore, Z and Y have the same cumulative distribution function. Summarizing, we have the following.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_212">212</target>
<fig id="fig_5_9">
<label>Figure 5.9</label>
<caption>Converting a uniform distribution F<sub>U</sub> into a prescribed distribution F<sub>Y</sub>.</caption>
</fig>
<label>Corollary 5.2</label>
<p role="noindent">If F(y) is a given cumulative distribution function that is strictly increasing when 0 &lt; F(y) &lt; 1 and if U is a random variable with uniform distribution on [0, 1], then</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-cor5.2">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">has the cumulative distribution F(y). &#x25A1;</p>

<p role="noindent">Thus, to simulate a random variable with a given cumulative distribution F we need only set Y = F<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(rnd).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="normal-density">
<title>Normal Density</title>
<p role="noindent">We now come to the most important density function, the normal density function. We have seen in Chapter 3 that the binomial distribution functions are bell-shaped, even for moderate size values of n. We recall that a binomially-distributed random variable with parameters n and p can be considered to be the sum of n mutually independent 0-1 random variables. A very important theorem in probability theory, called the Central Limit Theorem, states that under very general conditions, if we sum a large number of mutually independent random variables, then the distribution of the sum can be closely approximated by a certain specific continuous density, called the normal density. This theorem will be discussed in Chapter 9.</p>
<p role="noindent">The normal density function with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3; is defined as follows:</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-normal-density">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x03C0;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mi>&#x03C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x03C3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">The parameter &#x03BC; represents the &#x201C;center&#x201D; of the density (and in Chapter 6, we will show that it is the average, or expected, value of the density). The parameter &#x03C3; is a measure of the &#x201C;spread&#x201D; of the density, and thus it is assumed to be positive. (In Chapter 6, we will show that &#x03C3; is the standard deviation of the density.) We note that it is not at all obvious that the above function is a density, i.e., that its</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_213">213</target>
<fig id="fig_5_10">
<label>Figure 5.10</label>
<caption>Normal density for two sets of parameter values.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">integral over the real line equals 1. The cumulative distribution function is given by the formula</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x222B;</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x221E;</mi><mi>x</mi><mn>12</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mi>e</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>u</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2</mn><mi>d</mi><mi>u</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">In Figure 5.10 we have included for comparison a plot of the normal density for the cases &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1, and &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 2.</p>
<p role="noindent">One cannot write F<sub>X</sub> in terms of simple functions. This leads to several problems. First of all, values of F<sub>X</sub> must be computed using numerical integration. Extensive tables exist containing values of this function (see Appendix A). Secondly, we cannot write F<sup>&#x2212;1</sup><sub>X</sub> in closed form, so we cannot use Corollary 5.2 to help us simulate a normal random variable. For this reason, special methods have been developed for simulating a normal distribution. One such method relies on the fact that if U and V are independent random variables with uniform densities on [0, 1], then the random variables</p>
<disp-formula id="eq-box-muller-x">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>cos</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x03C0;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<p role="noindent">and</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>Y</mi><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>l</mi><mi>o</mi><mi>g</mi><mi>U</mi><mi>s</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>V</mi></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">are independent, and have normal density functions with parameters &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1. (This is not obvious, nor shall we prove it here. See Box and Muller.)</p>
<p role="noindent">Let Z be a normal random variable with parameters &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1. A normal random variable with these parameters is said to be a standard normal random variable. It is an important and useful fact that if we write</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>X</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mi>Z</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">then X is a normal random variable with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;. To show this, we will use Theorem 5.1. We have &#x03C6;(z) = &#x03C3;z + &#x03BC;, &#x03C6;<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(x) = (x &#x2212; &#x03BC;)/&#x03C3;, and</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>
<target target-type="page" id="page_214">214</target>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>f</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>f</mi><mi>Z</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x00B7;</mo><mn>1</mn><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>12</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mi>e</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mn>2.</mn></mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent">The reader will note that this last expression is the density function with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;, as claimed.</p>
<p role="noindent">We have seen above that it is possible to simulate a standard normal random variable Z. If we wish to simulate a normal random variable X with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;, then we need only transform the simulated values for Z using the equation X = &#x03C3;Z + &#x03BC;.</p>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we wish to calculate the value of a cumulative distribution function for the normal random variable X, with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;. We can reduce this calculation to one concerning the standard normal random variable Z as follows:</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mi>Z</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent">This last expression can be found in a table of values of the cumulative distribution function for a standard normal random variable. Thus, we see that it is unnecessary to make tables of normal distribution functions with arbitrary &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;.</p>
<p role="noindent">The process of changing a normal random variable to a standard normal random variable is known as standardization. If X has a normal distribution with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3; and if</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>Z</mi><mo>=</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi><mi>&#x03C3;</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent">then Z is said to be the standardized version of X.</p>
<p role="noindent">The following example shows how we use the standardized version of a normal random variable X to compute specific probabilities relating to X.</p>

<label>Example 5.8</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that X is a normally distributed random variable with parameters &#x03BC; = 10 and &#x03C3; = 3. Find the probability that X is between 4 and 16.</p>
<p role="noindent">To solve this problem, we note that Z = (X &#x2212; 10)/3 is the standardized version of X. So, we have</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>4</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>16</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>16</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>4</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>16</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>4</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mn>16</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>103</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mn>4</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>103</mn><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>F</mi><mi>Z</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<target target-type="page" id="page_215">215</target>
<fig id="fig_5_11">
<label>Figure 5.11</label>
<caption>Distribution of dart distances in 1000 drops.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">This last expression can be evaluated by using tabulated values of the standard normal distribution function (see 11.5); when we use this table, we find that F<sub>Z</sub>(2) = .9772 and F<sub>Z</sub>(&#x2212;2) = .0228. Thus, the answer is .9544.</p>
<p role="noindent">In Chapter 6, we will see that the parameter &#x03BC; is the mean, or average value, of the random variable X. The parameter &#x03C3; is a measure of the spread of the random variable, and is called the standard deviation. Thus, the question asked in this example is of a typical type, namely, what is the probability that a random variable has a value within two standard deviations of its average value. &#x25A1;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<title>Maxwell and Rayleigh Densities</title>

<label>Example 5.9</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we drop a dart on a large table top, which we consider as the xy-plane, and suppose that the x and y coordinates of the dart point are independent and have a normal distribution with parameters &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1. How is the distance of the point from the origin distributed?</p>
<p role="noindent">This problem arises in physics when it is assumed that a moving particle in R<sup>n</sup> has components of the velocity that are mutually independent and normally distributed and it is desired to find the density of the speed of the particle. The density in the case n = 3 is called the Maxwell density.</p>
<p role="noindent">The density in the case n = 2 (i.e. the dart board experiment described above) is called the Rayleigh density. We can simulate this case by picking independently a pair of coordinates (x, y), each from a normal distribution with &#x03BC; = 0 and &#x03C3; = 1 on (&#x2212;&#x221E;, &#x221E;), calculating the distance r =<inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula> of the point (x, y) from the origin, repeating this process a large number of times, and then presenting the results in a bar graph. The results are shown in Figure 5.11.</p>

<target target-type="page" id="page_216">216</target>
<table>
<label>Table 5.8</label>
<caption>Calculus class data.</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Female</th>
<th>Male</th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Below C</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>152</td>
<td>167</td>
<td>319</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table_5_9">
<label>Table 5.9</label>
<caption>Expected data.</caption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Female</th>
<th>Male</th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A</td>
<td>44.3</td>
<td>48.7</td>
<td>93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B</td>
<td>58.6</td>
<td>64.4</td>
<td>123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>47.1</td>
<td>90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Below C</td>
<td>6.2</td>
<td>6.8</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>152</td>
<td>167</td>
<td>319</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p role="noindent">We have also plotted the theoretical density</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>f</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>r</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>r</mi><mi>e</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>r</mi><mn>2</mn><mo>/</mo><mn>2.</mn></mrow>
</math>
<p role="noindent">This will be derived in Chapter 7; see Example 7.7. &#x25A1;</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Chi-Squared Density</title>
<p role="noindent">We return to the problem of independence of traits discussed in Example 5.6. It is frequently the case that we have two traits, each of which have several different values. As was seen in the example, quite a lot of calculation was needed even in the case of two values for each trait. We now give another method for testing independence of traits, which involves much less calculation.</p>
<label>Example 5.10</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that we have the data shown in Table 5.8 concerning grades and gender of students in a Calculus class. We can use the same sort of model in this situation as was used in Example 5.6. We imagine that we have an urn with 319 balls of two colors, say blue and red, corresponding to females and males, respectively. We now draw 93 balls, without replacement, from the urn. These balls correspond to the grade of A. We continue by drawing 123 balls, which correspond to the grade of B. When we finish, we have four sets of balls, with each ball belonging to exactly one set. (We could have stipulated that the balls were of four colors, corresponding to the four possible grades. In this case, we would draw a subset of size 152, which would correspond to the females. The balls remaining in the urn would correspond to the males. The choice does not affect the final determination of whether we should reject the hypothesis of independence of traits.)</p>
<p role="noindent">The expected data set can be determined in exactly the same way as in Example 5.6. If we do this, we obtain the expected values shown in Table 5.9. Even if</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_217">217</target>
<p role="noindent">the traits are independent, we would still expect to see some differences between the numbers in corresponding boxes in the two tables. However, if the differences are large, then we might suspect that the two traits are not independent. In Example 5.6, we used the probability distribution of the various possible data sets to compute the probability of finding a data set that differs from the expected data set by at least as much as the actual data set does. We could do the same in this case, but the amount of computation is enormous.</p>
<p role="noindent">Instead, we will describe a single number which does a good job of measuring how far a given data set is from the expected one. To quantify how far apart the two sets of numbers are, we could sum the squares of the differences of the corresponding numbers. (We could also sum the absolute values of the differences, but we would not want to sum the differences.) Suppose that we have data in which we expect to see 10 objects of a certain type, but instead we see 18, while in another case we expect to see 50 objects of a certain type, but instead we see 58. Even though the two differences are about the same, the first difference is more surprising than the second, since the expected number of outcomes in the second case is quite a bit larger than the expected number in the first case. One way to correct for this is to divide the individual squares of the differences by the expected number for that box. Thus, if we label the values in the eight boxes in the first table by O<sub>i</sub> (for observed values) and the values in the eight boxes in the second table by E<sub>i</sub> (for expected values), then the following expression might be a reasonable one to use to measure how far the observed data is from what is expected:</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mo>&#x2211;</mo><mi>i</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>18</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>O</mi><mi>i</mi><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>E</mi><mi>i</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>E</mi><mi>i</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">This expression is a random variable, which is usually denoted by the symbol &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup>, pronounced &#x201C;ki-squared.&#x201D; It is called this because, under the assumption of independence of the two traits, the density of this random variable can be computed and is approximately equal to a density called the chi-squared density. We choose not to give the explicit expression for this density, since it involves the gamma function, which we have not discussed. The chi-squared density is, in fact, a special case of the general gamma density.</p>
<p role="noindent">In applying the chi-squared density, tables of values of this density are used, as in the case of the normal density. The chi-squared density has one parameter n, which is called the number of degrees of freedom. The number n is usually easy to determine from the problem at hand. For example, if we are checking two traits for independence, and the two traits have a and b values, respectively, then the number of degrees of freedom of the random variable &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> is (a&#x2212;1)(b&#x2212;1). So, in the example at hand, the number of degrees of freedom is 3.</p>
<p role="noindent">We recall that in this example, we are trying to test for independence of the two traits of gender and grades. If we assume these traits are independent, then the ball-and-urn model given above gives us a way to simulate the experiment. Using a computer, we have performed 1000 experiments, and for each one, we have calculated a value of the random variable &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup>. The results are shown in Figure 5.12, together with the chi-squared density function with three degrees of freedom.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_218">218</target>
<fig id="fig_5_12">
<label>Figure 5.12</label>
<caption>Chi-squared density with three degrees of freedom.</caption>
</fig>
<p role="noindent">As we stated above, if the value of the random variable &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> is large, then we would tend not to believe that the two traits are independent. But how large is large? The actual value of this random variable for the data above is 4.13. In Figure 5.12, we have shown the chi-squared density with 3 degrees of freedom. It can be seen that the value 4.13 is larger than most of the values taken on by this random variable.</p>
<p role="noindent">Typically, a statistician will compute the value v of the random variable &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup>, just as we have done. Then, by looking in a table of values of the chi-squared density, a value v<sub>0</sub> is determined which is only exceeded 5% of the time. If v &#x2265; v<sub>0</sub>, the statistician rejects the hypothesis that the two traits are independent. In the present case, v<sub>0</sub> = 7.815, so we would not reject the hypothesis that the two traits are independent. &#x25A1;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<title>Cauchy Density</title>
<p role="noindent">The following example is from Feller.</p>

<label>Example 5.11</label>
<p role="noindent">Suppose that a mirror is mounted on a vertical axis, and is free to revolve about that axis. The axis of the mirror is 1 foot from a straight wall of infinite length. A pulse of light is shown onto the mirror, and the reflected ray hits the wall. Let &#x03C6; be the angle between the reflected ray and the line that is perpendicular to the wall and that runs through the axis of the mirror. We assume that &#x03C6; is uniformly distributed between &#x2212;&#x03C0;/2 and &#x03C0;/2. Let X represent the distance between the point on the wall that is hit by the reflected ray and the point on the wall that is closest to the axis of the mirror. We now determine the density of X.</p>
<p role="noindent">Let B be a fixed positive quantity. Then X &#x2265; B if and only if tan(&#x03C6;) &#x2265; B, which happens if and only if &#x03C6; &#x2265; arctan(B). This happens with probability</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>a</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>c</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>a</mi><mi>n</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<target target-type="page" id="page_219">219</target>
<p role="noindent">Thus, for positive B, the cumulative distribution function of X is</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mo stretchy='false'>
  (</mo><mi>B</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)
</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn>
<mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>a</mi><mi>r</mi>
<mi>c</mi><mi>t</mi>
<mi>a</mi><mi>n</mi>
<mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo>
<mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo>.</mo>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">Therefore, the density function for positive B is</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>f</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>B</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>1</mn><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mi>B</mi><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">Since the physical situation is symmetric with respect to &#x03C6; = 0, it is easy to see that the above expression for the density is correct for negative values of B as well.</p>
<p role="noindent">The Law of Large Numbers, which we will discuss in Chapter 8, states that in many cases, if we take the average of independent values of a random variable, then the average approaches a specific number as the number of values increases. It turns out that if one does this with a Cauchy-distributed random variable, the average does not approach any specific number. &#x25A1;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<title>Exercises</title>
<ol>
<li><p role="noindent">Choose a number U from the unit interval [0, 1] with uniform distribution. Find the cumulative distribution and density for the random variables (a) Y = U + 2. (b) Y = U<sup>3</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Choose a number U from the interval [0, 1] with uniform distribution. Find the cumulative distribution and density for the random variables (a) Y = 1/(U + 1). (b) Y = log(U + 1).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Use Corollary 5.2 to derive the expression for the random variable given in Equation 5.5. Hint: The random variables 1 &#x2212; rnd and rnd are identically distributed.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose we know a random variable Y as a function of the uniform random variable U: Y = &#x03C6;(U), and suppose we have calculated the cumulative distribution function F<sub>Y</sub>(y) and thence the density f<sub>Y</sub>(y). How can we check whether our answer is correct? An easy simulation provides the answer: Make a bar graph of Y = &#x03C6;(rnd) and compare the result with the graph of f<sub>Y</sub>(y). These graphs should look similar. Check your answers to Exercises 1 and 2 by this method.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Choose a number U from the interval [0, 1] with uniform distribution. Find the cumulative distribution and density for the random variables (a) Y = |U &#x2212; 1/2|. (b) Y = (U &#x2212; 1/2)<sup>2</sup>.</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_220">220</target>
<li><p role="noindent">Check your results for Exercise 5 by simulation as described in Exercise 4.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Explain how you can generate a random variable whose cumulative distribution function is</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>x</mi><mn>2</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x003E;</mo><mn>1.</mn></mrow>
</math>

</li>
<li><p role="noindent">Write a program to generate a sample of 1000 random outcomes each of which is chosen from the distribution given in Exercise 7. Plot a bar graph of your results and compare this empirical density with the density for the cumulative distribution given in Exercise 7.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let U, V be random numbers chosen independently from the interval [0, 1] with uniform distribution. Find the cumulative distribution and density of each of the variables (a) Y = U + V. (b) Y = |U &#x2212; V|.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let U, V be random numbers chosen independently from the interval [0, 1]. Find the cumulative distribution and density for the random variables (a) Y = max(U, V). (b) Y = min(U, V).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Write a program to simulate the random variables of Exercises 9 and 10 and plot a bar graph of the results. Compare the resulting empirical density with the density found in Exercises 9 and 10.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A number U is chosen at random in the interval [0, 1]. Find the probability that (a) R = U<sup>2</sup> &lt; 1/4. (b) S = U(1 &#x2212; U) &lt; 1/4. (c) T = U/(1 &#x2212; U) &lt; 1/4.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Find the cumulative distribution function F and the density function f for each of the random variables R, S, and T in Exercise 12.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A point P in the unit square has coordinates X and Y chosen at random in the interval [0, 1]. Let D be the distance from P to the nearest edge of the square, and E the distance to the nearest corner. What is the probability that (a) D &lt; 1/4? (b) E &lt; 1/4?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">In Exercise 14 find the cumulative distribution F and density f for the random variable D.</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_221">221</target>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with density function</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>f</mi><mi>X</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mi>c</mi><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>o</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>h</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>w</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>s</mi><mi>e</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">(a) What is the value of c? (b) What is the cumulative distribution function F<sub>X</sub> for X? (c) What is the probability that X &lt; 1/4?</p>
</li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with cumulative distribution function</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>F</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>s</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>n</mi><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>&#x03C0;</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>2</mn><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>&#x2264;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mi>i</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>&#x00A0;</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mi>x</mi><mo>.</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">(a) What is the density function f<sub>X</sub> for X? (b) What is the probability that X &lt; 1/4?</p>
</li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with cumulative distribution function F<sub>X</sub>, and let Y = X + b, Z = aX, and W = aX + b, where a and b are any constants. Find the cumulative distribution functions F<sub>Y</sub>, F<sub>Z</sub>, and F<sub>W</sub>. Hint: The cases a &gt; 0, a = 0, and a &lt; 0 require different arguments.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with density function f<sub>X</sub>, and let Y = X + b, Z = aX, and W = aX + b, where a &#x2260; 0. Find the density functions f<sub>Y</sub>, f<sub>Z</sub>, and f<sub>W</sub>. (See Exercise 18.)</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable uniformly distributed over [c, d], and let Y = aX + b. For what choice of a and b is Y uniformly distributed over [0, 1]?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with cumulative distribution function F strictly increasing on the range of X. Let Y = F(X). Show that Y is uniformly distributed in the interval [0, 1]. (The formula X = F<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>(Y) then tells us how to construct X from a uniform random variable Y.)</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with cumulative distribution function F. The median of X is the value m for which F(m) = 1/2. Then X &lt; m with probability 1/2 and X &gt; m with probability 1/2. Find m if X is (a) uniformly distributed over the interval [a, b]. (b) normally distributed with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;. (c) exponentially distributed with parameter &#x03BB;.</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with density function f<sub>X</sub>. The mean of X is the value &#x03BC; =<inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x222B;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>dx</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then &#x03BC; gives an average value for X (see Section 6.3). Find &#x03BC; if X is distributed uniformly, normally, or exponentially, as in Exercise 22.</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_222">222</target>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable with density function f<sub>X</sub>. The mode of X is the value M for which f(M) is maximum. Then values of X near M are most likely to occur. Find M if X is distributed normally or exponentially, as in Exercise 22. What happens if X is distributed uniformly?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let X be a random variable normally distributed with parameters &#x03BC; = 70, &#x03C3; = 10. Estimate (a) P(X &gt; 50). (b) P(X &lt; 60). (c) P(X &gt; 90). (d) P(60 &lt; X &lt; 80).</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Bridies&#x2019; Bearing Works manufactures bearing shafts whose diameters are normally distributed with parameters &#x03BC; = 1, &#x03C3; = .002. The buyer&#x2019;s specifications require these diameters to be 1.000 &#x00B1; .003 cm. What fraction of the manufacturer&#x2019;s shafts are likely to be rejected? If the manufacturer improves her quality control, she can reduce the value of &#x03C3;. What value of &#x03C3; will ensure that no more than 1 percent of her shafts are likely to be rejected?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">A final examination at Podunk University is constructed so that the test scores are approximately normally distributed, with parameters &#x03BC; and &#x03C3;. The instructor assigns letter grades to the test scores as shown in Table 5.10 (this is the process of &#x201C;grading on the curve&#x201D;). What fraction of the class gets A, B, C, D, F?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">An expert witness in a paternity suit testifies that the length (in days) of a pregnancy, from conception to delivery, is approximately normally distributed, with parameters &#x03BC; = 270, &#x03C3; = 10. The defendant in the suit is able to prove that he was out of the country during the period from 290 to 240 days before the birth of the child. What is the probability that the defendant was in the country when the child was conceived?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose that the time (in hours) required to repair a car is an exponentially distributed random variable with parameter &#x03BB; = 1/2. What is the probability that the repair time exceeds 4 hours? If it exceeds 4 hours what is the probability that it exceeds 8 hours?</p></li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_223">223</target>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose that the number of years a car will run is exponentially distributed with parameter &#x03BC; = 1/4. If Prosser buys a used car today, what is the probability that it will still run after 4 years?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Let U be a uniformly distributed random variable on [0, 1]. What is the probability that the equation x<sup>2</sup> + 4Ux + 1 = 0 has two distinct real roots x<sub>1</sub> and x<sub>2</sub>?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Write a program to simulate the random variables whose densities are given by the following, making a suitable bar graph of each and comparing the exact density with the bar graph. (a) f<sub>X</sub>(x) = e<sup>&#x2212;x</sup> on [0, &#x221E;) (but just do it on [0, 10]). (b) f<sub>X</sub>(x) = 2x on [0, 1]. (c) f<sub>X</sub>(x) = 3x<sup>2</sup> on [0, 1]. (d) f<sub>X</sub>(x) = 4|x &#x2212; 1/2| on [0, 1].</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Suppose we are observing a process such that the time between occurrences is exponentially distributed with &#x03BB; = 1/30 (i.e., the average time between occurrences is 30 minutes). Suppose that the process starts at a certain time and we start observing the process 3 hours later. Write a program to simulate this process. Let T denote the length of time that we have to wait, after we start our observation, for an occurrence. Have your program keep track of T. What is an estimate for the average value of T?</p></li>
<li><p role="noindent">Jones puts in two new lightbulbs: a 60 watt bulb and a 100 watt bulb. It is claimed that the lifetime of the 60 watt bulb has an exponential density with average lifetime 200 hours (&#x03BB; = 1/200). The 100 watt bulb also has an exponential density but with average lifetime of only 100 hours (&#x03BB; = 1/100). Jones wonders what is the probability that the 100 watt bulb will outlast the 60 watt bulb. If X and Y are two independent random variables with exponential densities f(x) = &#x03BB;e<sup>&#x2212;&#x03BB;x</sup> and g(x) = &#x03BC;e<sup>&#x2212;&#x03BC;x</sup>, respectively, then the probability that X is less than Y is given by</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>&#x222B;</mo><mn>0</mn><mi>&#x221E;</mi><mi>f</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>&#x2212;</mo><mi>G</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi><mo>,</mo></mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">where G(x) is the cumulative distribution function for g(x). Explain why this is the case. Use this to show that</p>
<math display='block'>
<mrow>
<mi>P</mi><mo stretchy='false'>(</mo><mi>X</mi><mo>&#x003C;</mo><mi>Y</mi><mo stretchy='false'>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac>
<mi>&#x03BB;</mi>
<mrow>
<mi>&#x03BB;</mi><mo>+</mo><mi>&#x03BC;</mi></mrow>
</mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>

<p role="noindent">and to answer Jones&#x2019;s question.</p>
</li>
<target target-type="page" id="page_224">224</target>
<li>
<p role="noindent">Consider the simple queueing process of Example 5.7. Suppose that you watch the size of the queue. If there are j people in the queue the next time the queue size changes it will either decrease to j &#x2212; 1 or increase to j + 1. Use the result of Exercise 34 to show that the probability that the queue size decreases to j &#x2212; 1 is &#x03BC;/(&#x03BC; + &#x03BB;) and the probability that it increases to j + 1 is &#x03BB;/(&#x03BC; + &#x03BB</p>
</li>
</ol>
</sec>
</example>
</chapter>