<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter26">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXVI</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The external relations of Alexey Alexandrovitch and his wife had remained unchanged. The sole difference lay in the fact that he was more busily occupied than ever. As in former years, at the beginning of the spring he had gone to a foreign watering-place for the sake of his health, deranged by the winter's work that every year grew heavier. And just as always he returned in July and at once fell to work as usual with increased energy. As usual, too, his wife had moved for the summer to a villa out of town, while he remained in Petersburg. From the date of their conversation after the party at Princess Tverskaya's he had never spoken again to Anna of his suspicions and his jealousies, and that habitual tone of his bantering mimicry was the most convenient tone possible for his present attitude to his wife. He was a little colder to his wife. He simply seemed to be slightly displeased with her for that first midnight conversation, which she had repelled. In his attitude to her there was a shade of vexation, but nothing more. "You would not be open with me," he seemed to say, mentally addressing her; "so much the worse for you. Now you may beg as you please, but I won't be open with you. So much the worse for you!" he said mentally, like a man who, after vainly attempting to extinguish a fire, should fly in a rage with his vain efforts and say, "Oh, very well then! you shall burn for this!" This man, so subtle and astute in official life, did not realize all the senselessness of such an attitude to his <target target-type="page" id="page_400">400</target>wife. He did not realize it, because it was too terrible to him to realize his actual position, and he shut down and locked and sealed up in his heart that secret place where lay hid his feelings towards his family, that is, his wife and son. He who had been such a careful father, had from the end of that winter become peculiarly frigid to his son, and adopted to him just the same bantering tone he used with his wife. "Aha, young man!" was the greeting with which he met him.</p>
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch asserted and believed that he had never in any previous year had so much official business as that year. But he was not aware that he sought work for himself that year, that this was one of the means for keeping shut that secret place where lay hid his feelings towards his wife and son and his thoughts about them, which became more terrible the longer they lay there. If anyone had had the right to ask Alexey Alexandrovitch what he thought of his wife's behavior, the mild and peaceable Alexey Alexandrovitch would have made no answer, but he would have been greatly angered with any man who should question him on that subject. For this reason there positively came into Alexey Alexandrovitch's face a look of haughtiness and severity whenever anyone inquired after his wife's health. Alexey Alexandrovitch did not want to think at all about his wife's behavior, and he actually succeeded in not thinking about it at all.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_401">401</target>
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch's permanent summer villa was in Peterhof, and the Countess Lidia Ivanovna used as a rule to spend the summer there, close to Anna, and constantly seeing her. That year Countess Lidia Ivanovna declined to settle in Peterhof, was not once at Anna Arkadyevna's, and in conversation with Alexey Alexandrovitch hinted at the unsuitability of Anna's close intimacy with Betsy and Vronsky. Alexey Alexandrovitch sternly cut her short, roundly declaring his wife to be above suspicion, and from that time began to avoid Countess Lidia Ivanovna. He did not want to see, and did not see, that many people in society cast dubious glances on his wife; he did not want to understand, and did not understand, why his wife had so particularly insisted on staying at Tsarskoe, where Betsy was staying, and not far from the camp of Vronsky's regiment. He did not allow himself to think about it, and he did not think about it; but all the same though he never admitted it to himself, and had no proofs, not even suspicious evidence, in the bottom of his heart he knew beyond all doubt that he was a deceived husband, and he was profoundly miserable about it.</p>     
<p role="noindent">How often during those eight years of happy life with his wife Alexey Alexandrovitch had looked at other men's faithless wives and other deceived husbands and asked himself: "How can people descend to that? how is it they don't put an end to such a hideous position?" But now, when the misfortune had come upon himself, he was so far from thinking of putting an end to <target target-type="page" id="page_402">402</target>the position that he would not recognize it at all, would not recognize it just because it was too awful, too unnatural.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Since his return from abroad Alexey Alexandrovitch had twice been at their country villa. Once he dined there, another time he spent the evening there with a party of friends, but he had not once stayed the night there, as it had been his habit to do in previous years.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The day of the races had been a very busy day for Alexey Alexandrovitch; but when mentally sketching out the day in the morning, he made up his mind to go to their country house to see his wife immediately after dinner, and from there to the races, which all the Court were to witness, and at which he was bound to be present. He was going to see his wife, because he had determined to see her once a week to keep up appearances. And besides, on that day, as it was the fifteenth, he had to give his wife some money for her expenses, according to their usual arrangement.</p>     
<p role="noindent">With his habitual control over his thoughts, though he thought all this about his wife, he did not let his thoughts stray further in regard to her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">That morning was a very full one for Alexey Alexandrovitch. The evening before, Countess Lidia Ivanovna had sent him a pamphlet by a celebrated traveler in China, who was staying in <target target-type="page" id="page_403">403</target>Petersburg, and with it she enclosed a note begging him to see the traveler himself, as he was an extremely interesting person from various points of view, and likely to be useful. Alexey Alexandrovitch had not had time to read the pamphlet through in the evening, and finished it in the morning. Then people began arriving with petitions, and there came the reports, interviews, appointments, dismissals, apportionment of rewards, pensions, grants, notes, the workaday round, as Alexey Alexandrovitch called it, that always took up so much time. Then there was private business of his own, a visit from the doctor and the steward who managed his property. The steward did not take up much time. He simply gave Alexey Alexandrovitch the money he needed together with a brief statement of the position of his affairs, which was not altogether satisfactory, as it had happened that during that year, owing to increased expenses, more had been paid out than usual, and there was a deficit. But the doctor, a celebrated Petersburg doctor, who was an intimate acquaintance of Alexey Alexandrovitch, took up a great deal of time. Alexey Alexandrovitch had not expected him that day, and was surprised at his visit, and still more so when the doctor questioned him very carefully about his health, listened to his breathing, and tapped at his liver. Alexey Alexandrovitch did not know that his friend Lidia Ivanovna, noticing that he was not as well as usual that year, had begged the doctor to go and examine him. "Do this for my sake," the Countess Lidia Ivanovna had said to him.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_404">404</target>
<p role="noindent">"I will do it for the sake of Russia, countess," replied the doctor. "A priceless man!" said the Countess Lidia Ivanovna.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The doctor was extremely dissatisfied with Alexey Alexandrovitch. He found the liver considerably enlarged, and the digestive powers weakened, while the course of mineral waters had been quite without effect. He prescribed more physical exercise as far as possible, and as far as possible less mental strain, and above all no worry—in other words, just what was as much out of Alexey Alexandrovitch's power as abstaining from breathing. Then he withdrew, leaving in Alexey Alexandrovitch an unpleasant sense that something was wrong with him, and that there was no chance of curing it.</p>     
<p role="noindent">As he was coming away, the doctor chanced to meet on the staircase an acquaintance of his, Sludin, who was secretary of Alexey Alexandrovitch's department. They had been comrades at the university, and though they rarely met, they thought highly of each other and were excellent friends, and so there was no one to whom the doctor would have given his opinion of a patient so freely as to Sludin.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"How glad I am you've been seeing him!" said Sludin. "He's not well, and I fancy Well, what do you think of him?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I'll tell you," said the doctor, beckoning over Sludin's head to his coachman to bring the carriage round. "It's just this," said <target target-type="page" id="page_405">405</target>the doctor, taking a finger of his kid glove in his white hands and pulling it, "if you don't strain the strings, and then try to break them, you'll find it a difficult job; but strain a string to its very utmost, and the mere weight of one finger on the strained string will snap it. And with his close assiduity, his conscientious devotion to his work, he's strained to the utmost; and there's some outside burden weighing on him, and not a light one," concluded the doctor, raising his eyebrows significantly. "Will you be at the races?" he added, as he sank into his seat in the carriage.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, yes, to be sure; it does waste a lot of time," the doctor responded vaguely to some reply of Sludin's he had not caught.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Directly after the doctor, who had taken up so much time, came the celebrated traveler, and Alexey Alexandrovitch, by means of the pamphlet he had only just finished reading and his previous acquaintance with the subject, impressed the traveler by the depth of his knowledge of the subject and the breadth and enlightenment of his view of it.</p>     
<p role="noindent">At the same time as the traveler there was announced a provincial marshal of nobility on a visit to Petersburg, with whom Alexey Alexandrovitch had to have some conversation. After his departure, he had to finish the daily routine of business with his secretary, and then he still had to drive round to call on a certain great personage on a matter of grave and serious import. Alexey Alexandrovitch only just managed to be back by five o'clock, his dinner-hour, and after dining with his secretary, <target target-type="page" id="page_406">406</target>he invited him to drive with him to his country villa and to the races.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Though he did not acknowledge it to himself, Alexey Alexandrovitch always tried nowadays to secure the presence of a third person in his interviews with his wife. <target target-type="page" id="page_407">407</target></p>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter27">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXVII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Anna was upstairs, standing before the looking glass, and, with Annushka's assistance, pinning the last ribbon on her gown when she heard carriage wheels crunching the gravel at the entrance.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"It's too early for Betsy," she thought, and glancing out of the window she caught sight of the carriage and the black hat of Alexey Alexandrovitch, and the ears that she knew so well sticking up each side of it. "How unlucky! Can he be going to stay the night?" she wondered, and the thought of all that might come of such a chance struck her as so awful and terrible that, without dwelling on it for a moment, she went down to meet him with a bright and radiant face; and conscious of the presence of that spirit of falsehood and deceit in herself that she had come to know of late, she abandoned herself to that spirit and began talking, hardly knowing what she was saying.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Ah, how nice of you!" she said, giving her husband her hand, and greeting Sludin, who was like one of the family, with a smile. "You're staying the night, I hope?" was the first word the spirit of falsehood prompted her to utter; "and now we'll go together. Only it's a pity I've promised Betsy. She's coming for me."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch knit his brows at Betsy's name.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, I'm not going to separate the inseparables," he said in his usual bantering tone. "I'm going with Mihail Vassilievitch. I'm ordered <target target-type="page" id="page_408">408</target>exercise by the doctors too. I'll walk, and fancy myself at the springs again."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"There's no hurry," said Anna. "Would you like tea?" She rang.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Bring in tea, and tell Seryozha that Alexey Alexandrovitch is here. Well, tell me, how have you been? Mihail Vassilievitch, you've not been to see me before. Look how lovely it is out on the terrace," she said, turning first to one and then to the other.</p>     
<p role="noindent">She spoke very simply and naturally, but too much and too fast. She was the more aware of this from noticing in the inquisitive look Mihail Vassilievitch turned on her that he was, as it were, keeping watch on her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Mihail Vassilievitch promptly went out on the terrace. She sat down beside her husband.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"You don't look quite well," she said.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes," he said; "the doctor's been with me today and wasted an hour of my time. I feel that some one of our friends must have sent him: my health's so precious, it seems."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No; what did he say?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">She questioned him about his health and what he had been doing, and tried to persuade him to take a rest and come out to her.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_409">409</target>
<p role="noindent">All this she said brightly, rapidly, and with a peculiar brilliance in her eyes. But Alexey Alexandrovitch did not now attach any special significance to this tone of hers. He heard only her words and gave them only the direct sense they bore. And he answered simply, though jestingly. There was nothing remarkable in all this conversation, but never after could Anna recall this brief scene without an agonizing pang of shame.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Seryozha came in preceded by his governess. If Alexey Alexandrovitch had allowed himself to observe he would have noticed the timid and bewildered eyes with which Seryozha glanced first at his father and then at his mother. But he would not see anything, and he did not see it.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Ah, the young man! He's grown. Really, he's getting quite a man. How are you, young man?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">And he gave his hand to the scared child. Seryozha had been shy of his father before, and now, ever since Alexey Alexandrovitch had taken to calling him young man, and since that insoluble question had occurred to him whether Vronsky were a friend or a foe, he avoided his father. He looked round towards his mother as though seeking shelter. It was only with his mother that he was at ease. Meanwhile, Alexey Alexandrovitch was holding his son by the shoulder while he was speaking to the governess, and Seryozha was so miserably uncomfortable that Anna saw he was on the point of tears.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_410">410</target>
<p role="noindent">Anna, who had flushed a little the instant her son came in, noticing that Seryozha was uncomfortable, got up hurriedly, took Alexey Alexandrovitch's hand from her son's shoulder, and kissing the boy, led him out onto the terrace, and quickly came back.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"It's time to start, though," said she, glancing at her watch. "How is it Betsy doesn't come?..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes," said Alexey Alexandrovitch, and getting up, he folded his hands and cracked his fingers. "I've come to bring you some money, too, for nightingales, we know, can't live on fairy tales," he said. "You want it, I expect?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, I don't ... yes, I do," she said, not looking at him, and crimsoning to the roots of her hair. "But you'll come back here after the races, I suppose?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, yes!" answered Alexey Alexandrovitch. "And here's the glory of Peterhof, Princess Tverskaya," he added, looking out of the window at the elegant English carriage with the tiny seats placed extremely high. "What elegance! Charming! Well, let us be starting too, then."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Princess Tverskaya did not get out of her carriage, but her groom, in high boots, a cape, and black hat, darted out at the entrance.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_411">411</target>
<p role="noindent">"I'm going; good-bye!" said Anna, and kissing her son, she went up to Alexey Alexandrovitch and held out her hand to him. "It was ever so nice of you to come."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch kissed her hand.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Well, au revoir, then! You'll come back for some tea; that's delightful!" she said, and went out, gay and radiant. But as soon as she no longer saw him, she was aware of the spot on her hand that his lips had touched, and she shuddered with repulsion. </p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_412">412</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter28">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXVIII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">When Alexey Alexandrovitch reached the race-course, Anna was already sitting in the pavilion beside Betsy, in that pavilion where all the highest society had gathered. She caught sight of her husband in the distance. Two men, her husband and her lover, were the two centers of her existence, and unaided by her external senses she was aware of their nearness. She was aware of her husband approaching a long way off, and she could not help following him in the surging crowd in the midst of which he was moving. She watched his progress towards the pavilion, saw him now responding condescendingly to an ingratiating bow, now exchanging friendly, nonchalant greetings with his equals, now assiduously trying to catch the eye of some great one of this world, and taking off his big round hat that squeezed the tips of his ears. All these ways of his she knew, and all were hateful to her. "Nothing but ambition, nothing but the desire to get on, that's all there is in his soul," she thought; "as for these lofty ideals, love of culture, religion, they are only so many tools for getting on."</p>     
<p role="noindent">From his glances towards the ladies' pavilion (he was staring straight at her, but did not distinguish his wife in the sea of muslin, ribbons, feathers, parasols and flowers) she saw that he was looking for her, but she purposely avoided noticing him.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_413">413</target>
<p role="noindent">"Alexey Alexandrovitch!" Princess Betsy called to him; "I'm sure you don't see your wife: here she is."</p>     
<p role="noindent">He smiled his chilly smile.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"There's so much splendor here that one's eyes are dazzled," he said, and he went into the pavilion. He smiled to his wife as a man should smile on meeting his wife after only just parting from her, and greeted the princess and other acquaintances, giving to each what was due—that is to say, jesting with the ladies and dealing out friendly greetings among the men. Below, near the pavilion, was standing an adjutant-general of whom Alexey Alexandrovitch had a high opinion, noted for his intelligence and culture. Alexey Alexandrovitch entered into conversation with him.</p>     
<p role="noindent">There was an interval between the races, and so nothing hindered conversation. The adjutant-general expressed his disapproval of races. Alexey Alexandrovitch replied defending them. Anna heard his high, measured tones, not losing one word, and every word struck her as false, and stabbed her ears with pain.</p>     
<p role="noindent">When the three-mile steeplechase was beginning, she bent forward and gazed with fixed eyes at Vronsky as he went up to his horse and mounted, and at the same time she heard that loathsome, never-ceasing voice of her husband. She was in an agony of terror for Vronsky, but a still greater agony was the <target target-type="page" id="page_414">414</target>never-ceasing, as it seemed to her, stream of her husband's shrill voice with its familiar intonations.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I'm a wicked woman, a lost woman," she thought; "but I don't like lying, I can't endure falsehood, while as for him (her husband) it's the breath of his life—falsehood. He knows all about it, he sees it all; what does he care if he can talk so calmly? If he were to kill me, if he were to kill Vronsky, I might respect him. No, all he wants is falsehood and propriety," Anna said to herself, not considering exactly what it was she wanted of her husband, and how she would have liked to see him behave. She did not understand either that Alexey Alexandrovitch's peculiar loquacity that day, so exasperating to her, was merely the expression of his inward distress and uneasiness. As a child that has been hurt skips about, putting all his muscles into movement to drown the pain, in the same way Alexey Alexandrovitch needed mental exercise to drown the thoughts of his wife that in her presence and in Vronsky's, and with the continual iteration of his name, would force themselves on his attention. And it was as natural for him to talk well and cleverly, as it is natural for a child to skip about. He was saying:</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Danger in the races of officers, of cavalry men, is an essential element in the race. If England can point to the most brilliant feats of cavalry in military history, it is simply owing to the fact that she has historically developed this force both in beasts and in men. Sport has, in my opinion, a great value, and as is always the case, we see nothing but what is most superficial."</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_415">415</target>
<p role="noindent">"It's not superficial," said Princess Tverskaya. "One of the officers, they say, has broken two ribs."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch smiled his smile, which uncovered his teeth, but revealed nothing more.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"We'll admit, princess, that that's not superficial," he said, "but internal. But that's not the point," and he turned again to the general with whom he was talking seriously; "we mustn't forget that those who are taking part in the race are military men, who have chosen that career, and one must allow that every calling has its disagreeable side. It forms an integral part of the duties of an officer. Low sports, such as prize-fighting or Spanish bullfights, are a sign of barbarity. But specialized trials of skill are a sign of development."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, I shan't come another time; it's too upsetting," said Princess Betsy. "Isn't it, Anna?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"It is upsetting, but one can't tear oneself away," said another lady. "If I'd been a Roman woman I should never have missed a single circus."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Anna said nothing, and keeping her opera glass up, gazed always at the same spot.</p>     
<p role="noindent">At that moment a tall general walked through the pavilion. Breaking off what he was saying, Alexey Alexandrovitch got up hurriedly, though with dignity, and bowed low to the general.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_416">416</target>
<p role="noindent">"You're not racing?" the officer asked, chaffing him.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"My race is a harder one," Alexey Alexandrovitch responded deferentially.</p>     
<p role="noindent">And though the answer meant nothing, the general looked as though he had heard a witty remark from a witty man, and fully relished la pointe de la sauce.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"There are two aspects," Alexey Alexandrovitch resumed: "those who take part and those who look on; and love for such spectacles is an unmistakable proof of a low degree of development in the spectator, I admit, but..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Princess, bets!" sounded Stepan Arkadyevitch's voice from below, addressing Betsy. "Who's your favorite?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Anna and I are for Kuzovlev," replied Betsy. "I'm for Vronsky. A pair of gloves?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Done!"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"But it is a pretty sight, isn't it?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch paused while there was talking about him, but he began again directly.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I admit that manly sports do not..." he was continuing.</p>     
<p role="noindent">But at that moment the racers started, and all conversation ceased. Alexey Alexandrovitch too was silent, and everyone stood up and turned towards the stream. Alexey Alexandrovitch <target target-type="page" id="page_417">417</target>took no interest in the race, and so he did not watch the racers, but fell listlessly to scanning the spectators with his weary eyes. His eyes rested upon Anna.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Her face was white and set. She was obviously seeing nothing and no one but one man. Her hand had convulsively clutched her fan, and she held her breath. He looked at her and hastily turned away, scrutinizing other faces.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"But here's this lady too, and others very much moved as well; it's very natural," Alexey Alexandrovitch told himself. He tried not to look at her, but unconsciously his eyes were drawn to her. He examined that face again, trying not to read what was so plainly written on it, and against his own will, with horror read on it what he did not want to know.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The first fall—Kuzovlev's, at the stream—agitated everyone, but Alexey Alexandrovitch saw distinctly on Anna's pale, triumphant face that the man she was watching had not fallen. When, after Mahotin and Vronsky had cleared the worst barrier, the next officer had been thrown straight on his head at it and fatally injured, and a shudder of horror passed over the whole public, Alexey Alexandrovitch saw that Anna did not even notice it, and had some difficulty in realizing what they were talking of about her. But more and more often, and with greater persistence, he watched her. Anna, wholly engrossed as she was with the race, became aware of her husband's cold eyes fixed upon her from one side.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_418">418</target>
<p role="noindent">She glanced round for an instant, looked inquiringly at him, and with a slight frown turned away again.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Ah, I don't care!" she seemed to say to him, and she did not once glance at him again.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The race was an unlucky one, and of the seventeen officers who rode in it more than half were thrown and hurt. Towards the end of the race everyone was in a state of agitation, which was intensified by the fact that the Tsar was displeased. </p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_419">419</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter29">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXIX</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Everyone was loudly expressing disapprobation, everyone was repeating a phrase some one had uttered—"The lions and gladiators will be the next thing," and everyone was feeling horrified; so that when Vronsky fell to the ground, and Anna moaned aloud, there was nothing very out of the way in it. But afterwards a change came over Anna's face which really was beyond decorum. She utterly lost her head. She began fluttering like a caged bird, at one moment would have got up and moved away, at the next turned to Betsy.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Let us go, let us go!" she said.</p>     
<p role="noindent">But Betsy did not hear her. She was bending down, talking to a general who had come up to her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch went up to Anna and courteously offered her his arm.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Let us go, if you like," he said in French, but Anna was listening to the general and did not notice her husband.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"He's broken his leg too, so they say," the general was saying.</p>
<p role="noindent">"This is beyond everything."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_420">420</target>
<p role="noindent">Without answering her husband, Anna lifted her opera glass and gazed towards the place where Vronsky had fallen; but it was so far off, and there was such a crowd of people about it, that she could make out nothing. She laid down the opera glass, and would have moved away, but at that moment an officer galloped up and made some announcement to the Tsar. Anna craned forward, listening.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Stiva! Stiva!" she cried to her brother.</p>     
<p role="noindent">But her brother did not hear her. Again she would have moved away. "Once more I offer you my arm if you want to be going," said Alexey Alexandrovitch, reaching towards her hand.</p>     
<p role="noindent">She drew back from him with aversion, and without looking in his face answered:</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, no, let me be, I'll stay."</p>     
<p role="noindent">She saw now that from the place of Vronsky's accident an officer was running across the course towards the pavilion. Betsy waved her handkerchief to him. The officer brought the news that the rider was not killed, but the horse had broken its back.</p>     
<p role="noindent">On hearing this Anna sat down hurriedly, and hid her face in her fan. Alexey Alexandrovitch saw that she was weeping, and could not control her tears, nor even the sobs that were shaking <target target-type="page" id="page_421">421/target>her bosom. Alexey Alexandrovitch stood so as to screen her, giving her time to recover herself.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"For the third time I offer you my arm," he said to her after a little time, turning to her. Anna gazed at him and did not know what to say. Princess Betsy came to her rescue.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, Alexey Alexandrovitch; I brought Anna and I promised to take her home," put in Betsy.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Excuse me, princess," he said, smiling courteously but looking her very firmly in the face, "but I see that Anna's not very well, and I wish her to come home with me."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Anna looked about her in a frightened way, got up submissively, and laid her hand on her husband's arm.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I'll send to him and find out, and let you know," Betsy whispered to her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">As they left the pavilion, Alexey Alexandrovitch, as always, talked to those he met, and Anna had, as always, to talk and answer; but she was utterly beside herself, and moved hanging on her husband's arm as though in a dream.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Is he killed or not? Is it true? Will he come or not? Shall I see him today?" she was thinking.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_422">422</target>
<p role="noindent">She took her seat in her husband's carriage in silence, and in silence drove out of the crowd of carriages. In spite of all he had seen, Alexey Alexandrovitch still did not allow himself to consider his wife's real condition. He merely saw the outward symptoms. He saw that she was behaving unbecomingly, and considered it his duty to tell her so. But it was very difficult for him not to say more, to tell her nothing but that. He opened his mouth to tell her she had behaved unbecomingly, but he could not help saying something utterly different.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"What an inclination we all have, though, for these cruel spectacles," he said. "I observe..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Eh? I don't understand," said Anna contemptuously.</p>     
<p role="noindent">He was offended, and at once began to say what he had meant to say. "I am obliged to tell you," he began.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"So now we are to have it out," she thought, and she felt frightened.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I am obliged to tell you that your behavior has been unbecoming today," he said to her in French.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"In what way has my behavior been unbecoming?" she said aloud, turning her head swiftly and looking him straight in the face, not with the bright expression that seemed covering something, but with a look of determination, under which she concealed with difficulty the dismay she was feeling.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_423">423</target>
<p role="noindent">"Mind," he said, pointing to the open window opposite the coachman.</p>     
<p role="noindent">He got up and pulled up the window.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"What did you consider unbecoming?" she repeated.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"The despair you were unable to conceal at the accident to one of the riders."</p>     
<p role="noindent">He waited for her to answer, but she was silent, looking straight before her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I have already begged you so to conduct yourself in society that even malicious tongues can find nothing to say against you. There was a time when I spoke of your inward attitude, but I am not speaking of that now. Now I speak only of your external attitude. You have behaved improperly, and I would wish it not to occur again."</p>     
<p role="noindent">She did not hear half of what he was saying; she felt panic-stricken before him, and was thinking whether it was true that Vronsky was not killed. Was it of him they were speaking when they said the rider was unhurt, but the horse had broken its back? She merely smiled with a pretense of irony when he finished, and made no reply, because she had not heard what he said. Alexey Alexandrovitch had begun to speak boldly, but as he realized plainly what he was speaking of, the dismay she <target target-type="page" id="page_424">424</target>was feeling infected him too. He saw the smile, and a strange misapprehension came over him.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"She is smiling at my suspicions. Yes, she will tell me directly what she told me before; that there is no foundation for my suspicions, that it's absurd."</p>     
<p role="noindent">At that moment, when the revelation of everything was hanging over him, there was nothing he expected so much as that she would answer mockingly as before that his suspicions were absurd and utterly groundless. So terrible to him was what he knew that now he was ready to believe anything. But the expression of her face, scared and gloomy, did not now promise even deception.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Possibly I was mistaken," said he. "If so, I beg your pardon."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, you were not mistaken," she said deliberately, looking desperately into his cold face. "You were not mistaken. I was, and I could not help being in despair. I hear you, but I am thinking of him. I love him, I am his mistress; I can't bear you; I'm afraid of you, and I hate you.... You can do what you like to me."</p>     
<p role="noindent">And dropping back into the corner of the carriage, she broke into sobs, hiding her face in her hands. Alexey Alexandrovitch did not stir, and kept looking straight before him. But his whole face suddenly bore the solemn rigidity of the dead, and his expression did not change during the whole time of the drive <target target-type="page" id="page_425">425</target>home. On reaching the house he turned his head to her, still with the same expression.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Very well! But I expect a strict observance of the external forms of propriety till such time"—his voice shook—"as I may take measures to secure my honor and communicate them to you."</p>     
<p role="noindent">He got out first and helped her to get out. Before the servants he pressed her hand, took his seat in the carriage, and drove back to Petersburg. Immediately afterwards a footman came from Princess Betsy and brought Anna a note.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I sent to Alexey to find out how he is, and he writes me he is quite well and unhurt, but in despair."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"So he will be here," she thought. "What a good thing I told him all!"</p>     
<p role="noindent">She glanced at her watch. She had still three hours to wait, and the memories of their last meeting set her blood in flame.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"My God, how light it is! It's dreadful, but I do love to see his face, and I do love this fantastic light.... My husband! Oh! yes.... Well, thank God! everything's over with him."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_426">426</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter30">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXX</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">In the little German watering-place to which the Shtcherbatskys had betaken themselves, as in all places indeed where people are gathered together, the usual process, as it were, of the crystallization of society went on, assigning to each member of that society a definite and unalterable place. Just as the particle of water in frost, definitely and unalterably, takes the special form of the crystal of snow, so each new person that arrived at the springs was at once placed in his special place.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Fürst Shtcherbatsky, sammt Gemahlin und Tochter, by the apartments they took, and from their name and from the friends they made, were immediately crystallized into a definite place marked out for them.</p>     
<p role="noindent">There was visiting the watering-place that year a real German Fürstin, in consequence of which the crystallizing process went on more vigorously than ever. Princess Shtcherbatskaya wished, above everything, to present her daughter to this German princess, and the day after their arrival she duly performed this rite. Kitty made a low and graceful curtsey in the very simple, that is to say, very elegant frock that had been ordered her from Paris. The German princess said, "I hope the roses will soon come back to this pretty little face," and for the Shtcherbatskys certain definite lines of existence were at once <target target-type="page" id="page_427">427</target>laid down from which there was no departing. The Shtcherbatskys made the acquaintance too of the family of an English Lady Somebody, and of a German countess and her son, wounded in the last war, and of a learned Swede, and of M. Canut and his sister. But yet inevitably the Shtcherbatskys were thrown most into the society of a Moscow lady, Marya Yevgenyevna Rtishtcheva and her daughter, whom Kitty disliked, because she had fallen ill, like herself, over a love affair, and a Moscow colonel, whom Kitty had known from childhood, and always seen in uniform and epaulets, and who now, with his little eyes and his open neck and flowered cravat, was uncommonly ridiculous and tedious, because there was no getting rid of him. When all this was so firmly established, Kitty began to be very much bored, especially as the prince went away to Carlsbad and she was left alone with her mother. She took no interest in the people she knew, feeling that nothing fresh would come of them. Her chief mental interest in the watering-place consisted in watching and making theories about the people she did not know. It was characteristic of Kitty that she always imagined everything in people in the most favorable light possible, especially so in those she did not know. And now as she made surmises as to who people were, what were their relations to one another, and what they were like, Kitty endowed them with <target target-type="page" id="page_428">428</target>the most marvelous and noble characters, and found confirmation of her idea in her observations.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Of these people the one that attracted her most was a Russian girl who had come to the watering-place with an invalid Russian lady, Madame Stahl, as everyone called her. Madame Stahl belonged to the highest society, but she was so ill that she could not walk, and only on exceptionally fine days made her appearance at the springs in an invalid carriage. But it was not so much from ill-health as from pride—so Princess Shtcherbatskaya interpreted it—that Madame Stahl had not made the acquaintance of anyone among the Russians there. The Russian girl looked after Madame Stahl, and besides that, she was, as Kitty observed, on friendly terms with all the invalids who were seriously ill, and there were many of them at the springs, and looked after them in the most natural way. This Russian girl was not, as Kitty gathered, related to Madame Stahl, nor was she a paid attendant. Madame Stahl called her Varenka, and other people called her "Mademoiselle Varenka." Apart from the interest Kitty took in this girl's relations with Madame Stahl and with other unknown persons, Kitty, as often happened, felt an inexplicable attraction to Mademoiselle Varenka, and was aware when their eyes met that she too liked her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Of Mademoiselle Varenka one would not say that she had passed her first youth, but she was, as it were, a creature without youth; she might have been taken for nineteen or for <target target-type="page" id="page_429">429</target>thirty. If her features were criticized separately, she was handsome rather than plain, in spite of the sickly hue of her face. She would have been a good figure, too, if it had not been for her extreme thinness and the size of her head, which was too large for her medium height. But she was not likely to be attractive to men. She was like a fine flower, already past its bloom and without fragrance, though the petals were still unwithered. Moreover, she would have been unattractive to men also from the lack of just what Kitty had too much of—of the suppressed fire of vitality, and the consciousness of her own attractiveness.</p>     
<p role="noindent">She always seemed absorbed in work about which there could be no doubt, and so it seemed she could not take interest in anything outside it. It was just this contrast with her own position that was for Kitty the great attraction of Mademoiselle Varenka. Kitty felt that in her, in her manner of life, she would find an example of what she was now so painfully seeking: interest in life, a dignity in life—apart from the worldly relations of girls with men, which so revolted Kitty, and appeared to her now as a shameful hawking about of goods in search of a purchaser. The more attentively Kitty watched her unknown friend, the more convinced she was this girl was the perfect creature she fancied her, and the more eagerly she wished to make her acquaintance.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_430">430</target>
<p role="noindent">The two girls used to meet several times a day, and every time they met, Kitty's eyes said: "Who are you? What are you? Are you really the exquisite creature I imagine you to be? But for goodness' sake don't suppose," her eyes added, "that I would force my acquaintance on you, I simply admire you and like you." "I like you too, and you're very, very sweet. And I should like you better still, if I had time," answered the eyes of the unknown girl. Kitty saw indeed, that she was always busy. Either she was taking the children of a Russian family home from the springs, or fetching a shawl for a sick lady, and wrapping her up in it, or trying to interest an irritable invalid, or selecting and buying cakes for tea for someone.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Soon after the arrival of the Shtcherbatskys there appeared in the morning crowd at the springs two persons who attracted universal and unfavorable attention. These were a tall man with a stooping figure, and huge hands, in an old coat too short for him, with black, simple, and yet terrible eyes, and a pockmarked, kind-looking woman, very badly and tastelessly dressed. Recognizing these persons as Russians, Kitty had already in her imagination begun constructing a delightful and touching romance about them. But the princess, having ascertained from the visitors' list that this was Nikolay Levin and Marya Nikolaevna, explained to Kitty what a bad man this Levin was, and all her fancies about these two people vanished. Not so much from what her mother told her, as from the fact that it was Konstantin's brother, this pair suddenly seemed to <target target-type="page" id="page_431">431</target>Kitty intensely unpleasant. This Levin, with his continual twitching of his head, aroused in her now an irrepressible feeling of disgust.</p>     
<p role="noindent">It seemed to her that his big, terrible eyes, which persistently pursued her, expressed a feeling of hatred and contempt, and she tried to avoid meeting him. </p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_432">432</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter31">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXXI</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">It was a wet day; it had been raining all the morning, and the invalids, with their parasols, had flocked into the arcades. Kitty was walking there with her mother and the Moscow colonel, smart and jaunty in his European coat, bought ready-made at Frankfort. They were walking on one side of the arcade, trying to avoid Levin, who was walking on the other side. Varenka, in her dark dress, in a black hat with a turn-down brim, was walking up and down the whole length of the arcade with a blind Frenchwoman, and, every time she met Kitty, they exchanged friendly glances.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Mamma, couldn't I speak to her?" said Kitty, watching her unknown friend, and noticing that she was going up to the spring, and that they might come there together.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, if you want to so much, I'll find out about her first and make her acquaintance myself," answered her mother. "What do you see in her out of the way? A companion, she must be. If you like, I'll make acquaintance with Madame Stahl; I used to know her belle-soeur," added the princess, lifting her head haughtily.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty knew that the princess was offended that Madame Stahl had seemed to avoid making her acquaintance. Kitty did not insist.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_433">433</target>
<p role="noindent">"How wonderfully sweet she is!" she said, gazing at Varenka just as she handed a glass to the Frenchwoman. "Look how natural and sweet it all is."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"It's so funny to see your engouements," said the princess. "No, we'd better go back," she added, noticing Levin coming towards them with his companion and a German doctor, to whom he was talking very noisily and angrily.</p>     
<p role="noindent">They turned to go back, when suddenly they heard, not noisy talk, but shouting. Levin, stopping short, was shouting at the doctor, and the doctor, too, was excited. A crowd gathered about them. The princess and Kitty beat a hasty retreat, while the colonel joined the crowd to find out what was the matter.</p>     
<p role="noindent">A few minutes later the colonel overtook them. "What was it?" inquired the princess.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Scandalous and disgraceful!" answered the colonel. "The one thing to be dreaded is meeting Russians abroad. That tall gentleman was abusing the doctor, flinging all sorts of insults at him because he wasn't treating him quite as he liked, and he began waving his stick at him. It's simply a scandal!"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, how unpleasant!" said the princess. "Well, and how did it end?" "Luckily at that point that ... the one in the mushroom hat ... intervened. A <target target-type="page" id="page_434">434</target>Russian lady, I think she is," said the colonel. "Mademoiselle Varenka?" asked Kitty.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, yes. She came to the rescue before anyone; she took the man by the arm and led him away."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"There, mamma," said Kitty; "you wonder that I'm enthusiastic about her."</p>     
<p role="noindent">The next day, as she watched her unknown friend, Kitty noticed that Mademoiselle Varenka was already on the same terms with Levin and his companion as with her other protégés. She went up to them, entered into conversation with them, and served as interpreter for the woman, who could not speak any foreign language.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty began to entreat her mother still more urgently to let her make friends with Varenka. And, disagreeable as it was to the princess to seem to take the first step in wishing to make the acquaintance of Madame Stahl, who thought fit to give herself airs, she made inquiries about Varenka, and, having ascertained particulars about her tending to prove that there could be no harm though little good in the acquaintance, she herself approached Varenka and made acquaintance with her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Choosing a time when her daughter had gone to the spring, while Varenka had stopped outside the baker's, the princess went up to her.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_435">435</target>
<p role="noindent">"Allow me to make your acquaintance," she said, with her dignified smile. "My daughter has lost her heart to you," she said. "Possibly you do not know me. I am..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"That feeling is more than reciprocal, princess," Varenka answered hurriedly.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"What a good deed you did yesterday to our poor compatriot!" said the princess.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Varenka flushed a little. "I don't remember. I don't think I did anything," she said.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Why, you saved that Levin from disagreeable consequences."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, sa compagne called me, and I tried to pacify him, he's very ill, and was dissatisfied with the doctor. I'm used to looking after such invalids."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, I've heard you live at Mentone with your aunt—I think—Madame Stahl: I used to know her belle-soeur."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, she's not my aunt. I call her mamma, but I am not related to her; I was brought up by her," answered Varenka, flushing a little again.</p>     
<p role="noindent">This was so simply said, and so sweet was the truthful and candid expression of her face, that the princess saw why Kitty had taken such a fancy to Varenka.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_436">436</target>
<p role="noindent">"Well, and what's this Levin going to do?" asked the princess. "He's going away," answered Varenka.</p>     
<p role="noindent">At that instant Kitty came up from the spring beaming with delight that her mother had become acquainted with her unknown friend.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Well, see, Kitty, your intense desire to make friends with Mademoiselle. ."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Varenka," Varenka put in smiling, "that's what everyone calls me."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty blushed with pleasure, and slowly, without speaking, pressed her new friend's hand, which did not respond to her pressure, but lay motionless in her hand. The hand did not respond to her pressure, but the face of Mademoiselle Varenka glowed with a soft, glad, though rather mournful smile, that showed large but handsome teeth.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I have long wished for this too," she said. "But you are so busy."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, no, I'm not at all busy," answered Varenka, but at that moment she had to leave her new friends because two little Russian girls, children of an invalid, ran up to her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Varenka, mamma's calling!" they cried. And Varenka went after them. </p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_437">437</target>
</body>
</book-part>

<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter32">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXXII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The particulars which the princess had learned in regard to Varenka's past and her relations with Madame Stahl were as follows: Madame Stahl, of whom some people said that she had worried her husband out of his life, while others said it was he who had made her wretched by his immoral behavior, had always been a woman of weak health and enthusiastic temperament. When, after her separation from her husband, she gave birth to her only child, the child had died almost immediately, and the family of Madame Stahl, knowing her sensibility, and fearing the news would kill her, had substituted another child, a baby born the same night and in the same house in Petersburg, the daughter of the chief cook of the Imperial Household. This was Varenka. Madame Stahl learned later on that Varenka was not her own child, but she went on bringing her up, especially as very soon afterwards Varenka had not a relation of her own living. Madame Stahl had now been living more than ten years continuously abroad, in the south, never leaving her couch. And some people said that Madame Stahl had made her social position as a philanthropic, highly religious woman; other people said she really was at heart the highly ethical being, living for nothing but the good of her <target target-type="page" id="page_438">438</target>fellow creatures, which she represented herself to be. No one knew what her faith was—Catholic, Protestant, or Orthodox. But one fact was indubitable—she was in amicable relations with the highest dignitaries of all the churches and sects.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Varenka lived with her all the while abroad, and everyone who knew Madame Stahl knew and liked Mademoiselle Varenka, as everyone called her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Having learned all these facts, the princess found nothing to object to in her daughter's intimacy with Varenka, more especially as Varenka's breeding and education were of the best—she spoke French and English extremely well—and what was of the most weight, brought a message from Madame Stahl expressing her regret that she was prevented by her ill health from making the acquaintance of the princess.</p>     
<p role="noindent">After getting to know Varenka, Kitty became more and more fascinated by her friend, and every day she discovered new virtues in her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The princess, hearing that Varenka had a good voice, asked her to come and sing to them in the evening.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Kitty plays, and we have a piano; not a good one, it's true, but you will give us so much pleasure," said the princess with her affected smile, which Kitty disliked particularly just then, because she noticed that Varenka had no inclination to sing. Varenka came, however, in the evening and brought a roll of <target target-type="page" id="page_439">439</target>music with her. The princess had invited Marya Yevgenyevna and her daughter and the colonel.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Varenka seemed quite unaffected by there being persons present she did not know, and she went directly to the piano. She could not accompany herself, but she could sing music at sight very well. Kitty, who played well, accompanied her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"You have an extraordinary talent," the princess said to her after Varenka had sung the first song extremely well.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Marya Yevgenyevna and her daughter expressed their thanks and admiration.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Look," said the colonel, looking out of the window, "what an audience has collected to listen to you." There actually was quite a considerable crowd under the windows.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I am very glad it gives you pleasure," Varenka answered simply.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty looked with pride at her friend. She was enchanted by her talent, and her voice, and her face, but most of all by her manner, by the way Varenka obviously thought nothing of her singing and was quite unmoved by their praises. She seemed only to be asking: "Am I to sing again, or is that enough?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"If it had been I," thought Kitty, "how proud I should have been! How delighted I should have been to see that crowd under the <target target-type="page" id="page_440">440</target>windows! But she's utterly unmoved by it. Her only motive is to avoid refusing and to please mamma. What is there in her? What is it gives her the power to look down on everything, to be calm independently of everything? How I should like to know it and to learn it of her!" thought Kitty, gazing into her serene face. The princess asked Varenka to sing again, and Varenka sang another song, also smoothly, distinctly, and well, standing erect at the piano and beating time on it with her thin, dark-skinned hand.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The next song in the book was an Italian one. Kitty played the opening bars, and looked round at Varenka.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Let's skip that," said Varenka, flushing a little. Kitty let her eyes rest on Varenka's face, with a look of dismay and inquiry.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Very well, the next one," she said hurriedly, turning over the pages, and at once feeling that there was something connected with the song.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No," answered Varenka with a smile, laying her hand on the music, "no, let's have that one." And she sang it just as quietly, as coolly, and as well as the others.</p>     
<p role="noindent">When she had finished, they all thanked her again, and went off to tea.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty and Varenka went out into the little garden that adjoined the house.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_441">441</target>
<p role="noindent">"Am I right, that you have some reminiscences connected with that song?" said Kitty. "Don't tell me," she added hastily, "only say if I'm right."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, why not? I'll tell you simply," said Varenka, and, without waiting for a reply, she went on: "Yes, it brings up memories, once painful ones. I cared for someone once, and I used to sing him that song."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty with big, wide-open eyes gazed silently, sympathetically at Varenka.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I cared for him, and he cared for me; but his mother did not wish it, and he married another girl. He's living now not far from us, and I see him sometimes. You didn't think I had a love story too," she said, and there was a faint gleam in her handsome face of that fire which Kitty felt must once have glowed all over her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I didn't think so? Why, if I were a man, I could never care for anyone else after knowing you. Only I can't understand how he could, to please his mother, forget you and make you unhappy; he had no heart."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, no, he's a very good man, and I'm not unhappy; quite the contrary, I'm very happy. Well, so we shan't be singing any more now," she added, turning towards the house.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_442">442</target>
<p role="noindent">"How good you are! how good you are!" cried Kitty, and stopping her, she kissed her. "If I could only be even a little like you!"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Why should you be like anyone? You're nice as you are," said Varenka, smiling her gentle, weary smile.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, I'm not nice at all. Come, tell me.... Stop a minute, let's sit down," said Kitty, making her sit down again beside her. "Tell me, isn't it humiliating to think that a man has disdained your love, that he hasn't cared for it?..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"But he didn't disdain it; I believe he cared for me, but he was a dutiful son..."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, but if it hadn't been on account of his mother, if it had been his own doing?..." said Kitty, feeling she was giving away her secret, and that her face, burning with the flush of shame, had betrayed her already.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"In that case he would have done wrong, and I should not have regretted him," answered Varenka, evidently realizing that they were now talking not of her, but of Kitty.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"But the humiliation," said Kitty, "the humiliation one can never forget, can never forget," she said, remembering her look at the last ball during the pause in the music.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Where is the humiliation? Why, you did nothing wrong?" "Worse than wrong—shameful."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Varenka shook her head and laid her hand on Kitty's hand.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_443">443</target>
<p role="noindent">"Why, what is there shameful?" she said. "You didn't tell a man, who didn't care for you, that you loved him, did you?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Of course not; I never said a word, but he knew it. No, no, there are looks, there are ways; I can't forget it, if I live a hundred years."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Why so? I don't understand. The whole point is whether you love him now or not," said Varenka, who called everything by its name.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"I hate him; I can't forgive myself." "Why, what for?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"The shame, the humiliation!"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh! if everyone were as sensitive as you are!" said Varenka. "There isn't a girl who hasn't been through the same. And it's all so unimportant."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Why, what is important?" said Kitty, looking into her face with inquisitive wonder.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, there's so much that's important," said Varenka, smiling. "Why, what?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Oh, so much that's more important," answered Varenka, not knowing what to say. But at that instant they heard the princess's voice from the window. "Kitty, it's cold! Either get a shawl, or come indoors."</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_444">444</target>
<p role="noindent">"It really is time to go in!" said Varenka, getting up. "I have to go on to Madame Berthe's; she asked me to."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty held her by the hand, and with passionate curiosity and entreaty her eyes asked her: "What is it, what is this of such importance that gives you such tranquillity? You know, tell me!" But Varenka did not even know what Kitty's eyes were asking her. She merely thought that she had to go to see Madame Berthe too that evening, and to make haste home in time for maman's tea at twelve o'clock. She went indoors, collected her music, and saying good-bye to everyone, was about to go.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Allow me to see you home," said the colonel.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, how can you go alone at night like this?" chimed in the princess. "Anyway, I'll send Parasha."</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty saw that Varenka could hardly restrain a smile at the idea that she needed an escort.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, I always go about alone and nothing ever happens to me," she said, taking her hat. And kissing Kitty once more, without saying what was important, she stepped out courageously with the music under her arm and vanished into the twilight of the summer night, bearing away with her her secret of what was important and what gave her the calm and dignity so much to be envied.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_445">445</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter33">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXXIII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Kitty made the acquaintance of Madame Stahl too, and this acquaintance, together with her friendship with Varenka, did not merely exercise a great influence on her, it also comforted her in her mental distress. She found this comfort through a completely new world being opened to her by means of this acquaintance, a world having nothing in common with her past, an exalted, noble world, from the height of which she could contemplate her past calmly. It was revealed to her that besides the instinctive life to which Kitty had given herself up hitherto there was a spiritual life. This life was disclosed in religion, but a religion having nothing in common with that one which Kitty had known from childhood, and which found expression in litanies and all-night services at the Widow's Home, where one might meet one's friends, and in learning by heart Slavonic texts with the priest. This was a lofty, mysterious religion connected with a whole series of noble thoughts and feelings, which one could do more than merely believe because one was told to, which one could love.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty found all this out not from words. Madame Stahl talked to Kitty as to a charming child that one looks on with pleasure as on the memory of one's youth, and only once she said in passing that in all human sorrows nothing gives comfort but love and faith, and that in the sight of Christ's compassion for us no sorrow is trifling—and immediately talked of other things.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_446">446</target>
<p role="noindent">But in every gesture of Madame Stahl, in every word, in every heavenly—as Kitty called it—look, and above all in the whole story of her life, which she heard from Varenka, Kitty recognized that something "that was important," of which, till then, she had known nothing.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Yet, elevated as Madame Stahl's character was, touching as was her story, and exalted and moving as was her speech, Kitty could not help detecting in her some traits which perplexed her. She noticed that when questioning her about her family, Madame Stahl had smiled contemptuously, which was not in accord with Christian meekness. She noticed, too, that when she had found a Catholic priest with her, Madame Stahl had studiously kept her face in the shadow of the lamp-shade and had smiled in a peculiar way. Trivial as these two observations were, they perplexed her, and she had her doubts as to Madame Stahl. But on the other hand Varenka, alone in the world, without friends or relations, with a melancholy disappointment in the past, desiring nothing, regretting nothing, was just that perfection of which Kitty dared hardly dream. In Varenka she realized that one has but to forget oneself and love others, and one will be calm, happy, and noble. And that was what Kitty longed to be. Seeing now clearly what was the most important, Kitty was not satisfied with being enthusiastic over it; she at once gave herself up with her whole soul to the new life that was opening to her. From Varenka's accounts of <target target-type="page" id="page_447">447</target>the doings of Madame Stahl and other people whom she mentioned, Kitty had already constructed the plan of her own future life. She would, like Madame Stahl's niece, Aline, of whom Varenka had talked to her a great deal, seek out those who were in trouble, wherever she might be living, help them as far as she could, give them the Gospel, read the Gospel to the sick, to criminals, to the dying. The idea of reading the Gospel to criminals, as Aline did, particularly fascinated Kitty. But all these were secret dreams, of which Kitty did not talk either to her mother or to Varenka.</p>     
<p role="noindent">While awaiting the time for carrying out her plans on a large scale, however, Kitty, even then at the springs, where there were so many people ill and unhappy, readily found a chance for practicing her new principles in imitation of Varenka.</p>     
<p role="noindent">At first the princess noticed nothing but that Kitty was much under the influence of her engouement, as she called it, for Madame Stahl, and still more for Varenka. She saw that Kitty did not merely imitate Varenka in her conduct, but unconsciously imitated her in her manner of walking, of talking, of blinking her eyes. But later on the princess noticed that, apart from this adoration, some kind of serious spiritual change was taking place in her daughter.</p>     
<p role="noindent">The princess saw that in the evenings Kitty read a French testament that Madame Stahl had given her—a thing she had never done before; that she avoided society acquaintances and associated with the sick people who were under Varenka's <target target-type="page" id="page_448">448</target>protection, and especially one poor family, that of a sick painter, Petrov. Kitty was unmistakably proud of playing the part of a sister of mercy in that family. All this was well enough, and the princess had nothing to say against it, especially as Petrov's wife was a perfectly nice sort of woman, and that the German princess, noticing Kitty's devotion, praised her, calling her an angel of consolation. All this would have been very well, if there had been no exaggeration. But the princess saw that her daughter was rushing into extremes, and so indeed she told her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Il ne faut jamais rien outrer," she said to her.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Her daughter made her no reply, only in her heart she thought that one could not talk about exaggeration where Christianity was concerned. What exaggeration could there be in the practice of a doctrine wherein one was bidden to turn the other cheek when one was smitten, and give one's cloak if one's coat were taken? But the princess disliked this exaggeration, and disliked even more the fact that she felt her daughter did not care to show her all her heart. Kitty did in fact conceal her new views and feelings from her mother. She concealed them not because she did not respect or did not love her mother, but simply because she was her mother. She would have revealed them to anyone sooner than to her mother.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_449">449</target>
<p role="noindent">"How is it Anna Pavlovna's not been to see us for so long?" the princess said one day of Madame Petrova. "I've asked her, but she seems put out about something."</p>     
<p role="noindent">"No, I've not noticed it, maman," said Kitty, flushing hotly. "Is it long since you went to see them?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"We're meaning to make an expedition to the mountains tomorrow," answered Kitty.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Well, you can go," answered the princess, gazing at her daughter's embarrassed face and trying to guess the cause of her embarrassment.</p>     
<p role="noindent">That day Varenka came to dinner and told them that Anna Pavlovna had changed her mind and given up the expedition for the morrow. And the princess noticed again that Kitty reddened.</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Kitty, haven't you had some misunderstanding with the Petrovs?" said the princess, when they were left alone. "Why has she given up sending the children and coming to see us?"</p>     
<p role="noindent">Kitty answered that nothing had happened between them, and that she could not tell why Anna Pavlovna seemed displeased with her. Kitty answered perfectly truly. She did not know the reason Anna Pavlovna had changed to her, but she guessed it. She guessed at something which she could not tell her mother, which she did not put into words to herself. It was one of those things which one knows but which one can never speak of even to oneself, so terrible and shameful would it be to be mistaken.</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_450">450</target>
<p role="noindent">Again and again she went over in her memory all her relations with the family. She remembered the simple delight expressed on the round, good-humored face of Anna Pavlovna at their meetings; she remembered their secret confabulations about the invalid, their plots to draw him away from the work which was forbidden him, and to get him out-of-doors; the devotion of the youngest boy, who used to call her "my Kitty," and would not go to bed without her. How nice it all was! Then she recalled the thin, terribly thin figure of Petrov, with his long neck, in his brown coat, his scant, curly hair, his questioning blue eyes that were so terrible to Kitty at first, and his painful attempts to seem hearty and lively in her presence. She recalled the efforts she had made at first to overcome the repugnance she felt for him, as for all consumptive people, and the pains it had cost her to think of things to say to him. She recalled the timid, softened look with which he gazed at her, and the strange feeling of compassion and awkwardness, and later of a sense of her own goodness, which she had felt at it. How nice it all was! But all that was at first. Now, a few days ago, everything was suddenly spoiled. Anna Pavlovna had met Kitty with affected cordiality, and had kept continual watch on her and on her husband.</p>     
<p role="noindent">Could that touching pleasure he showed when she came near be the cause of Anna Pavlovna's coolness?</p>     
<target target-type="page" id="page_415">451</target>
<p role="noindent">"Yes," she mused, "there was something unnatural about Anna Pavlovna, and utterly unlike her good nature, when she said angrily the day before yesterday: 'There, he will keep waiting for you; he wouldn't drink his coffee without you, though he's grown so dreadfully weak.'"</p>     
<p role="noindent">"Yes, perhaps, too, she didn't like it when I gave him the rug. It was all so simple, but he took it so awkwardly, and was so long thanking me, that I felt awkward too. And then that portrait of me he did so well. And most of all that look of confusion and tenderness! Yes, yes, that's it!" Kitty repeated to herself with horror. "No, it can't be, it oughtn't to be! He's so much to be pitied!" she said to herself directly after.</p>     
<p role="noindent">This doubt poisoned the charm of her new life.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_452">452</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter34">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXXIV</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Before the end of the course of drinking the waters, Prince Shtcherbatsky, who had gone on from Carlsbad to Baden and Kissingen to Russian friends—to get a breath of Russian air, as he said—came back to his wife and daughter.</p>
<p role="noindent">The views of the prince and of the princess on life abroad were completely opposed. The princess thought everything delightful, and in spite of her established position in Russian society, she tried abroad to be like a European fashionable lady, which she was not—for the simple reason that she was a typical Russian gentlewoman; and so she was affected, which did not altogether suit her. The prince, on the contrary, thought everything foreign detestable, got sick of European life, kept to his Russian habits, and purposely tried to show himself abroad less European than he was in reality.</p>
<p role="noindent">The prince returned thinner, with the skin hanging in loose bags on his cheeks, but in the most cheerful frame of mind. His good humor was even greater when he saw Kitty completely recovered. The news of Kitty’s friendship with Madame Stahl and Varenka, and the reports the princess gave him of some kind of change she had noticed in Kitty, troubled the prince and aroused his habitual feeling of jealousy of everything that drew his daughter away from him, and a dread that his daughter <target target-type="page" id="page_453">453</target> might have got out of the reach of his influence into regions inaccessible to him. But these unpleasant matters were all drowned in the sea of kindliness and good humor which was always within him, and more so than ever since his course of Carlsbad waters.</p>
<p role="noindent">The day after his arrival the prince, in his long overcoat, with his Russian wrinkles and baggy cheeks propped up by a starched collar, set off with his daughter to the spring in the greatest good humor.</p>
<p role="noindent">It was a lovely morning: the bright, cheerful houses with their little gardens, the sight of the red-faced, red-armed, beerdrinking German waitresses, working away merrily, did the heart good. But the nearer they got to the springs the oftener they met sick people; and their appearance seemed more pitiable than ever among the everyday conditions of prosperous German life. Kitty was no longer struck by this contrast. The bright sun, the brilliant green of the foliage, the strains of the music were for her the natural setting of all these familiar faces, with their changes to greater emaciation or to convalescence, for which she watched. But to the prince the brightness and gaiety of the June morning, and the sound of the orchestra playing a gay waltz then in fashion, and above all, the appearance of the healthy attendants, seemed something unseemly and monstrous, in conjunction with these slowly <target target-type="page" id="page_454">454</target>moving, dying figures gathered together from all parts of Europe. In spite of his feeling of pride and, as it were, of the return of youth, with his favorite daughter on his arm, he felt awkward, and almost ashamed of his vigorous step and his sturdy, stout limbs. He felt almost like a man not dressed in a crowd.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Present me to your new friends," he said to his daughter, squeezing her hand with his elbow. "I like even your horrid Soden for making you so well again. Only it’s melancholy, very melancholy here. Who’s that?"</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty mentioned the names of all the people they met, with some of whom she was acquainted and some not. At the entrance of the garden they met the blind lady, Madame Berthe, with her guide, and the prince was delighted to see the old Frenchwoman’s face light up when she heard Kitty’s voice. She at once began talking to him with French exaggerated politeness, applauding him for having such a delightful daughter, extolling Kitty to the skies before her face, and calling her a treasure, a pearl, and a consoling angel.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, she's the second angel, then," said the prince, smiling, "she calls Mademoiselle Varenka angel number one."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh! Mademoiselle Varenka, she's a real angel, allez," Madame Berthe assented.</p>
<p role="noindent">In the arcade they met Varenka herself. She was walking rapidly towards them carrying an elegant red bag.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_455">455</target>
<p role="noindent">"Here is papa come," Kitty said to her.</p>
<p role="noindent">Varenka made—simply and naturally as she did everything—a movement between a bow and a curtsey, and immediately began talking to the prince, without shyness, naturally, as she talked to everyone.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Of course I know you; I know you very well," the prince said to her with a smile, in which Kitty detected with joy that her father liked her friend. "Where are you off to in such haste?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Maman's here," she said, turning to Kitty. "She has not slept all night, and the doctor advised her to go out. I'm taking her her work."</p>
<p role="noindent">"So that's angel number one?" said the prince when Varenka had gone on.</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty saw that her father had meant to make fun of Varenka, but that he could not do it because he liked her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Come, so we shall see all your friends," he went on, "even Madame Stahl, if she deigns to recognize me."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Why, did you know her, papa?" Kitty asked apprehensively, catching the gleam of irony that kindled in the prince's eyes at the mention of Madame Stahl.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I used to know her husband, and her too a little, before she'd joined the Pietists."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_456">456</target>
<p role="noindent">"What is a Pietist, papa?" asked Kitty, dismayed to find that what she prized so highly in Madame Stahl had a name.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I don't quite know myself. I only know that she thanks God for everything, for every misfortune, and thanks God too that her husband died. And that's rather droll, as they didn't get on together."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Who's that? What a piteous face!" he asked, noticing a sick man of medium height sitting on a bench, wearing a brown overcoat and white trousers that fell in strange folds about his long, fleshless legs. This man lifted his straw hat, showed his scanty curly hair and high forehead, painfully reddened by the pressure of the hat.</p>
<p role="noindent">"That's Petrov, an artist," answered Kitty, blushing. "And that's his wife," she added, indicating Anna Pavlovna, who, as though on purpose, at the very instant they approached walked away after a child that had run off along a path.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Poor fellow! and what a nice face he has!" said the prince. "Why don't you go up to him? He wanted to speak to you."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, let us go, then," said Kitty, turning round resolutely. "How are you feeling today?" she asked Petrov.</p>
<p role="noindent">Petrov got up, leaning on his stick, and looked shyly at the prince. "This is my daughter," said the prince. "Let me introduce myself."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_457">457</target>
<p role="noindent">The painter bowed and smiled, showing his strangely dazzling white teeth.</p>
<p role="noindent">"We expected you yesterday, princess," he said to Kitty. He staggered as he said this, and then repeated the motion, trying to make it seem as if it had been intentional.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I meant to come, but Varenka said that Anna Pavlovna sent word you were not going."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Not going!" said Petrov, blushing, and immediately beginning to cough, and his eyes sought his wife. "Anita! Anita!" he said loudly, and the swollen veins stood out like cords on his thin white neck.</p>
<p role="noindent">Anna Pavlovna came up.</p>
<p role="noindent">"So you sent word to the princess that we weren't going!" he whispered to her angrily, losing his voice.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Good morning, princess," said Anna Pavlovna, with an assumed smile utterly unlike her former manner. "Very glad to make your acquaintance," she said to the prince. "You've long been expected, prince."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What did you send word to the princess that we weren't going for?" the artist whispered hoarsely once more, still more angrily, obviously exasperated that his voice failed him so that he could not give his words the expression he would have liked to.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_458">458</target>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, mercy on us! I thought we weren't going," his wife answered crossly. "What, when...." He coughed and waved his hand. The prince took off his hat and moved away with his daughter.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah! ah!" he sighed deeply. "Oh, poor things!"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, papa," answered Kitty. "And you must know they've three children, no servant, and scarcely any means. He gets something from the Academy," she went on briskly, trying to drown the distress that the queer change in Anna Pavlovna's manner to her had aroused in her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, here's Madame Stahl," said Kitty, indicating an invalid carriage, where, propped on pillows, something in gray and blue was lying under a sunshade. This was Madame Stahl. Behind her stood the gloomy, healthy- looking German workman who pushed the carriage. Close by was standing a flaxen-headed Swedish count, whom Kitty knew by name. Several invalids were lingering near the low carriage, staring at the lady as though she were some curiosity.</p>
<p role="noindent">The prince went up to her, and Kitty detected that disconcerting gleam of irony in his eyes. He went up to Madame Stahl, and addressed her with extreme courtesy and affability in that excellent French that so few speak nowadays.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_459">459</target>
<p role="noindent">"I don't know if you remember me, but I must recall myself to thank you for your kindness to my daughter," he said, taking off his hat and not putting it on again.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Prince Alexander Shtcherbatsky," said Madame Stahl, lifting upon him her heavenly eyes, in which Kitty discerned a look of annoyance. "Delighted! I have taken a great fancy to your daughter."</p>
<p role="noindent">"You are still in weak health?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes; I'm used to it," said Madame Stahl, and she introduced the prince to the Swedish count.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You are scarcely changed at all," the prince said to her. "It's ten or eleven years since I had the honor of seeing you."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes; God sends the cross and sends the strength to bear it. Often one wonders what is the goal of this life?... The other side!" she said angrily to Varenka, who had rearranged the rug over her feet not to her satisfaction.</p>
<p role="noindent">"To do good, probably," said the prince with a twinkle in his eye.</p>
<p role="noindent">"That is not for us to judge," said Madame Stahl, perceiving the shade of expression on the prince's face. "So you will send me that book, dear count? I'm very grateful to you," she said to the young Swede.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah!" cried the prince, catching sight of the Moscow colonel standing near, and with a bow to Madame Stahl he walked <target target-type="page" id="page_460">460</target>away with his daughter and the Moscow colonel, who joined them.</p>
<p role="noindent">"That's our aristocracy, prince!" the Moscow colonel said with ironical intention. He cherished a grudge against Madame Stahl for not making his acquaintance.</p>
<p role="noindent">"She's just the same," replied the prince.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Did you know her before her illness, prince—that's to say before she took to her bed?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes. She took to her bed before my eyes," said the prince. "They say it's ten years since she has stood on her feet."</p>
<p role="noindent">"She doesn't stand up because her legs are too short. She's a very bad figure."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Papa, it's not possible!" cried Kitty.</p>
<p role="noindent">"That's what wicked tongues say, my darling. And your Varenka catches it too," he added. "Oh, these invalid ladies!"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, no, papa!" Kitty objected warmly. "Varenka worships her. And then she does so much good! Ask anyone! Everyone knows her and Aline Stahl."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Perhaps so," said the prince, squeezing her hand with his elbow; "but it's better when one does good so that you may ask everyone and no one knows."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_461">461</target>
<p role="noindent">Kitty did not answer, not because she had nothing to say, but because she did not care to reveal her secret thoughts even to her father. But, strange to say, although she had so made up her mind not to be influenced by her father's views, not to let him into her inmost sanctuary, she felt that the heavenly image of Madame Stahl, which she had carried for a whole month in her heart, had vanished, never to return, just as the fantastic figure made up of some clothes thrown down at random vanishes when one sees that it is only some garment lying there. All that was left was a woman with short legs, who lay down because she had a bad figure, and worried patient Varenka for not arranging her rug to her liking. And by no effort of the imagination could Kitty bring back the former Madame Stahl.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_462">462</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter35">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XXXV</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The prince communicated his good humor to his own family and his friends, and even to the German landlord in whose rooms the Shtcherbatskys were staying.</p>
<p role="noindent">On coming back with Kitty from the springs, the prince, who had asked the colonel, and Marya Yevgenyevna, and Varenka all to come and have coffee with them, gave orders for a table and chairs to be taken into the garden under the chestnut tree, and lunch to be laid there. The landlord and the servants, too, grew brisker under the influence of his good spirits. They knew his open- handedness; and half an hour later the invalid doctor from Hamburg, who lived on the top floor, looked enviously out of the window at the merry party of healthy Russians assembled under the chestnut tree. In the trembling circles of shadow cast by the leaves, at a table, covered with a white cloth, and set with coffeepot, bread-and-butter, cheese, and cold game, sat the princess in a high cap with lilac ribbons, distributing cups and bread-and-butter. At the other end sat the prince, eating heartily, and talking loudly and merrily. The prince had spread out near him his purchases, carved boxes, and knick-knacks, paper-knives of all sorts, of which he bought a heap at every watering-place,<target target-type="page" id="page_470">470</target>and bestowed them upon everyone, including Lieschen, the servant girl, and the landlord, with whom he jested in his comically bad German, assuring him that it was not the water had cured Kitty, but his splendid cookery, especially his plum soup. The princess laughed at her husband for his Russian ways, but she was more lively and good-humored than she had been all the while she had been at the waters. The colonel smiled, as he always did, at the prince’s jokes, but as far as regards Europe, of which he believed himself to be making a careful study, he took the princess’s side. The simple-hearted Marya Yevgenyevna simply roared with laughter at everything absurd the prince said, and his jokes made Varenka helpless with feeble but infectious laughter, which was something Kitty had never seen before.</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty was glad of all this, but she could not be light-hearted. She could not solve the problem her father had unconsciously set her by his goodhumored view of her friends, and of the life that had so attracted her. To this doubt there was joined the change in her relations with the Petrovs, which had been so conspicuously and unpleasantly marked that morning. Everyone was good humored, but Kitty could not feel good humored, and this increased her distress. She felt a feeling such as she had known in childhood, when she had been shut in her room as a punishment, and had heard her sisters’ merry laughter outside.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, but what did you buy this mass of things for?" said the princess, smiling, and handing her husband a cup of coffee. <target target-type="page" id="page_470">470</target> "One goes for a walk, one looks in a shop, and they ask you to buy. ‘Erlaucht, Durchlaucht?’ Directly they say ‘Durchlaucht,’ I can’t hold out. I lose ten thalers."</p>
<p role="noindent">“It’s simply from boredom,” said the princess.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Of course it is. Such boredom, my dear, that one doesn’t know what to do with oneself.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“How can you be bored, prince? There’s so much that’s interesting now in Germany,” said Marya Yevgenyevna.</p>
<p role="noindent">“But I know everything that’s interesting: the plum soup I know, and the pea sausages I know. I know everything.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“No, you may say what you like, prince, there’s the interest of their institutions,” said the colonel.</p>
<p role="noindent">“But what is there interesting about it? They’re all as pleased as brass halfpence. They’ve conquered everybody, and why am I to be pleased at that? I haven’t conquered anyone; and I’m obliged to take off my own boots, yes, and put them away too; in the morning, get up and dress at once, and go to the</p>
<p role="noindent">dining room to drink bad tea! How different it is at home! You get up in no haste, you get cross, grumble a little, and come round again. You’ve time to think things over, and no hurry.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“But time’s money, you forget that,” said the colonel.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_465">465</target>
<p role="noindent">“Time, indeed, that depends! Why, there’s time one would give a month of for sixpence, and time you wouldn’t give half an hour of for any money. Isn’t that so, Katinka? What is it? why are you so depressed?”</p>
<p role="noindent">“I’m not depressed.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“Where are you off to? Stay a little longer,” he said to Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">“I must be going home,” said Varenka, getting up, and again she went off into a giggle. When she had recovered, she said good-bye, and went into the house to get her hat.</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty followed her. Even Varenka struck her as different. She was not worse, but different from what she had fancied her before.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Oh, dear! it’s a long while since I’ve laughed so much!” said Varenka, gathering up her parasol and her bag. “How nice he is, your father!”</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty did not speak.</p>
<p role="noindent">“When shall I see you again?” asked Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Mamma meant to go and see the Petrovs. Won’t you be there?” said Kitty, to try Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Yes,” answered Varenka. “They’re getting ready to go away, so I promised to help them pack.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“Well, I’ll come too, then.” “No, why should you?”</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_466">466</target>
<p role="noindent">“Why not? why not? why not?” said Kitty, opening her eyes wide, and clutching at Varenka’s parasol, so as not to let her go. “No, wait a minute; why not?”</p>
<p role="noindent">“Oh, nothing; your father has come, and besides, they will feel awkward at your helping.”</p>
<p role="noindent">“No, tell me why you don’t want me to be often at the Petrovs’. You don’t want me to—why not?”</p>
<p role="noindent">“I didn’t say that,” said Varenka quietly. “No, please tell me!”</p>
<p role="noindent">“Tell you everything?” asked Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Everything, everything!” Kitty assented.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Well, there’s really nothing of any consequence; only that Mihail Alexeyevitch” (that was the artist’s name) “had meant to leave earlier, and now he doesn’t want to go away,” said Varenka, smiling.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Well, well!” Kitty urged impatiently, looking darkly at Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">“Well, and for some reason Anna Pavlovna told him that he didn’t want to go because you are here. Of course, that was nonsense; but there was a dispute over it—over you. You know how irritable these sick people are.”</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty, scowling more than ever, kept silent, and Varenka went on speaking alone, trying to soften or soothe her, and seeing a storm coming—she did not know whether of tears or of words.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_467">467</target>
<p role="noindent">"So you’d better not go.... You understand; you won’t be offended?..." "And it serves me right! And it serves me right!" Kitty cried quickly,</p>
<p role="noindent">snatching the parasol out of Varenka’s hand, and looking past her friend’s face.</p>
<p role="noindent">Varenka felt inclined to smile, looking at her childish fury, but she was afraid of wounding her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"How does it serve you right? I don’t understand," she said.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It serves me right, because it was all sham; because it was all done on purpose, and not from the heart. What business had I to interfere with outsiders? And so it’s come about that I’m a cause of quarrel, and that I’ve done what nobody asked me to do. Because it was all a sham! a sham! a sham!..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"A sham! with what object?" said Varenka gently.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, it’s so idiotic! so hateful! There was no need whatever for me....</p>
<p role="noindent">Nothing but sham!" she said, opening and shutting the parasol.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But with what object?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"To seem better to people, to myself, to God; to deceive everyone. No! now I won’t descend to that. I’ll be bad; but anyway not a liar, a cheat."</p>
<p role="noindent">"But who is a cheat?" said Varenka reproachfully. "You speak as if "</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_468">468</target>
<p role="noindent">But Kitty was in one of her gusts of fury, and she would not let her finish. "I don’t talk about you, not about you at all. You’re perfection. Yes, yes, I</p>
<p role="noindent">know you’re all perfection; but what am I to do if I’m bad? This would never have been if I weren’t bad. So let me be what I am. I won’t be a sham. What have I to do with Anna Pavlovna? Let them go their way, and me go mine. I can’t be different And yet it’s not that, it’s not that."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What is not that?" asked Varenka in bewilderment.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Everything. I can’t act except from the heart, and you act from principle. I liked you simply, but you most likely only wanted to save me, to improve me."</p>
<p role="noindent">"You are unjust," said Varenka.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But I’m not speaking of other people, I’m speaking of myself."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Kitty," they heard her mother’s voice, "come here, show papa your necklace."</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty, with a haughty air, without making peace with her friend, took the necklace in a little box from the table and went to her mother.</p>
<p role="noindent">"What’s the matter? Why are you so red?" her mother and father said to her with one voice.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_469">469</target>
<p role="noindent">"Nothing," she answered. "I’ll be back directly," and she ran back.</p>
<p role="noindent">"She’s still here," she thought. "What am I to say to her? Oh, dear! what have I done, what have I said? Why was I rude to her? What am I to do? What am I to say to her?" thought Kitty, and she stopped in the doorway.</p>
<p role="noindent">Varenka in her hat and with the parasol in her hands was sitting at the table examining the spring which Kitty had broken. She lifted her head.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Varenka, forgive me, do forgive me," whispered Kitty, going up to her. "I don’t remember what I said. I..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I really didn’t mean to hurt you," said Varenka, smiling.</p>
<p role="noindent">Peace was made. But with her father’s coming all the world in which she had been living was transformed for Kitty. She did not give up everything she had learned, but she became aware that she had deceived herself in supposing she could be what she wanted to be. Her eyes were, it seemed, opened; she felt all the difficulty of maintaining herself without hypocrisy and self-conceit on the pinnacle to which she had wished to mount. Moreover, she became aware of all the dreariness of the world of sorrow, of sick and dying people, in which she had been living. The efforts she had made to like it seemed to her intolerable, and she felt a longing to get back quickly into the fresh air, to Russia, to Ergushovo, where, as she knew from letters, her sister Dolly had already gone with her children.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_470">470</target>
<p role="noindent">But her affection for Varenka did not wane. As she said good-bye, Kitty begged her to come to them in Russia.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I'll come when you get married," said Varenka. "I shall never marry."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, then, I shall never come."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, then, I shall be married simply for that. Mind now, remember your promise," said Kitty.</p>
<p role="noindent">The doctor's prediction was fulfilled. Kitty returned home to Russia cured. She was not so gay and thoughtless as before, but she was serene. Her Moscow troubles had become a memory to her.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_471">471</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter1">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>Part Three</title>
<title>CHAPTER <label>I</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch Koznishev wanted a rest from mental work, and instead of going abroad as he usually did, he came towards the end of May to stay in the country with his brother. In his judgment the best sort of life was a country life. He had come now to enjoy such a life at his brother’s. Konstantin Levin was very glad to have him, especially as he did not expect his brother Nikolay that summer. But in spite of his affection and respect for Sergey Ivanovitch, Konstantin Levin was uncomfortable with his brother in the country. It made him uncomfortable, and it positively annoyed him to see his brother’s attitude to the country. To Konstantin Levin the country was the background of life, that is of pleasures, endeavors, labor. To Sergey Ivanovitch the country meant on one hand rest from work, on the other a valuable antidote to the corrupt influences of town, which he took with satisfaction and a sense of its utility. To Konstantin Levin the country was good first because it afforded a field for labor, of the usefulness of which there could be no doubt. To Sergey Ivanovitch the country was particularly good, because there it was possible and fitting to do nothing. Moreover, Sergey Ivanovitch’s attitude to the peasants rather piqued Konstantin. Sergey Ivanovitch used to say that he knew and liked the peasantry, and he often talked to the peasants, which he knew how to do without affectation or condescension, and from every such <target target-type="page" id="page_472">472</target>conversation he would deduce general conclusions in favor of the peasantry and in confirmation of his knowing them. Konstantin Levin did not like such an attitude to the peasants. To Konstantin the peasant was simply the chief partner in their common labor, and in spite of all the respect and the love, almost like that of kinship, he had for the peasant—sucked in probably, as he said himself, with the milk of his peasant nurse—still as a fellow-worker with him, while sometimes enthusiastic over the vigor, gentleness, and justice of these men, he was very often, when their common labors called for other qualities, exasperated with the peasant for his carelessness, lack of method, drunkenness, and lying. If he had been asked whether he liked or didn’t like the peasants, Konstantin Levin would have been absolutely at a loss what to reply. He liked and did not like the peasants, just as he liked and did not like men in general. Of course, being a good-hearted man, he liked men rather than he disliked them, and so too with the peasants. But like or dislike "the people" as something apart he could not, not only because he lived with "the people," and all his interests were bound up with theirs, but also because he regarded himself as a part of "the people," did not see any special qualities or failings distinguishing himself and "the people," and could not contrast himself with them. Moreover, although he had lived so long in the closest relations with the peasants, as farmer and arbitrator, and what was more, as <target target-type="page" id="page_473">473</target>adviser (the peasants trusted him, and for thirty miles round they would come to ask his advice), he had no definite views of "the people," and would have been as much at a loss to answer the question whether he knew "the people" as the question whether he liked them. For him to say he knew the peasantry would have been the same as to say he knew men. He was continually watching and getting to know people of all sorts, and among them peasants, whom he regarded as good and interesting people, and he was continually observing new points in them, altering his former views of them and forming new ones. With Sergey Ivanovitch it was quite the contrary. Just as he liked and praised a country life in comparison with the life he did not like, so too he liked the peasantry in contradistinction to the class of men he did not like, and so too he knew the peasantry as something distinct from and opposed to men generally. In his methodical brain there were distinctly formulated certain aspects of peasant life, deduced partly from that life itself, but chiefly from contrast with other modes of life. He never changed his opinion of the peasantry and his sympathetic attitude towards them.</p>
<p role="noindent">In the discussions that arose between the brothers on their views of the peasantry, Sergey Ivanovitch always got the better of his brother, precisely because Sergey Ivanovitch had definite ideas about the peasant—his character, his qualities, and his tastes. Konstantin Levin had no definite and unalterable idea on <target target-type="page" id="page_474">474</target>the subject, and so in their arguments Konstantin was readily convicted of contradicting himself.</p>
<p role="noindent">In Sergey Ivanovitch’s eyes his younger brother was a capital fellow, with his heart in the right place (as he expressed it in French), but with a mind which, though fairly quick, was too much influenced by the impressions of the moment, and consequently filled with contradictions. With all the condescension of an elder brother he sometimes explained to him the true import of things, but he derived little satisfaction from arguing with him because he got the better of him too easily.</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin regarded his brother as a man of immense intellect and culture, as generous in the highest sense of the word, and possessed of a special faculty for working for the public good. But in the depths of his heart, the older he became, and the more intimately he knew his brother, the more and more frequently the thought struck him that this faculty of working for the public good, of which he felt himself utterly devoid, was possibly not so much a quality as a lack of something—not a lack of good, honest, noble desires and tastes, but a lack of vital force, of what is called heart, of that impulse which drives a man to choose someone out of the innumerable paths of life, and to care only for that one. The better he knew his brother, the more he noticed that Sergey Ivanovitch, and many other people who worked for the public <target target-type="page" id="page_475">475</target>welfare, were not led by an impulse of the heart to care for the public good, but reasoned from intellectual considerations that it was a right thing to take interest in public affairs, and consequently took interest in them. Levin was confirmed in this generalization by observing that his brother did not take questions affecting the public welfare or the question of the immortality of the soul a bit more to heart than he did chess problems, or the ingenious construction of a new machine.</p>
<p role="noindent">Besides this, Konstantin Levin was not at his ease with his brother, because in summer in the country Levin was continually busy with work on the land, and the long summer day was not long enough for him to get through all he had to do, while Sergey Ivanovitch was taking a holiday. But though he was taking a holiday now, that is to say, he was doing no writing, he was so used to intellectual activity that he liked to put into concise and eloquent shape the ideas that occurred to him, and liked to have someone to listen to him. His most usual and natural listener was his brother. And so in spite of the friendliness and directness of their relations, Konstantin felt an awkwardness in leaving him alone. Sergey Ivanovitch liked to stretch himself on the grass in the sun, and to lie so, basking and chatting lazily.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You wouldn’t believe," he would say to his brother, "what a pleasure this rural laziness is to me. Not an idea in one’s brain, as empty as a drum!"</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_476">476</target>
<p role="noindent">But Konstantin Levin found it dull sitting and listening to him, especially when he knew that while he was away they would be carting dung onto the fields not ploughed ready for it, and heaping it all up anyhow; and would not screw the shares in the ploughs, but would let them come off and then say that the new ploughs were a silly invention, and there was nothing like the old Andreevna plough, and so on.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Come, you’ve done enough trudging about in the heat," Sergey Ivanovitch would say to him.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, I must just run round to the counting-house for a minute," Levin would answer, and he would run off to the fields.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_477">477</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter2">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>II</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Early in June it happened that Agafea Mihalovna, the old nurse and housekeeper, in carrying to the cellar a jar of mushrooms she had just pickled, slipped, fell, and sprained her wrist. The district doctor, a talkative young medical student, who had just finished his studies, came to see her. He examined the wrist, said it was not broken, was delighted at a chance of talking to the celebrated Sergey Ivanovitch Koznishev, and to show his advanced views of things told him all the scandal of the district, complaining of the poor state into which the district council had fallen. Sergey Ivanovitch listened attentively, asked him questions, and, roused by a new listener, he talked fluently, uttered a few keen and weighty observations, respectfully appreciated by the young doctor, and was soon in that eager frame of mind his brother knew so well, which always, with him, followed a brilliant and eager conversation. After the departure of the doctor, he wanted to go with a fishing rod to the river. Sergey Ivanovitch was fond of angling, and was, it seemed, proud of being able to care for such a stupid occupation.</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin, whose presence was needed in the plough land and meadows, had come to take his brother in the trap</p>
<p role="noindent">It was that time of the year, the turning-point of summer, when the crops of the present year are a certainty, when one begins to think of the sowing for next year, and the mowing is at hand; <target target-type="page" id="page_478">478</target>when the rye is all in ear, though its ears are still light, not yet full, and it waves in gray-green billows in the wind; when the green oats, with tufts of yellow grass scattered here and there among it, droop irregularly over the late-sown fields; when the early buckwheat is already out and hiding the ground; when the fallow lands, trodden hard as stone by the cattle, are half ploughed over, with paths left untouched by the plough; when from the dry dung-heaps carted onto the fields there comes at sunset a smell of manure mixed with meadow-sweet, and on the low-lying lands the riverside meadows are a thick sea of grass waiting for the mowing, with blackened heaps of the stalks of sorrel among it.</p>
<p role="noindent">It was the time when there comes a brief pause in the toil of the fields before the beginning of the labors of harvest—every year recurring, every year straining every nerve of the peasants. The crop was a splendid one, and bright, hot summer days had set in with short, dewy nights.</p>
<p role="noindent">The brothers had to drive through the woods to reach the meadows. Sergey</p>
<p role="noindent">Ivanovitch was all the while admiring the beauty of the woods, which were a tangled mass of leaves, pointing out to his brother now an old lime tree on the point of flowering, dark on the shady side, and brightly spotted with yellow stipules, now the young shoots of this year’s saplings brilliant with emerald.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_479">479</target>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin did not like talking and hearing about the beauty of nature. Words for him took away the beauty of what he saw. He assented to what his brother said, but he could not help beginning to think of other things. When they came out of the woods, all his attention was engrossed by the view of the fallow land on the upland, in parts yellow with grass, in parts trampled and checkered with furrows, in parts dotted with ridges of dung, and in parts even ploughed. A string of carts was moving across it. Levin counted the carts, and was pleased that all that were wanted had been brought, and at the sight of the meadows his thoughts passed to the mowing. He always felt something special moving him to the quick at the hay-making. On reaching the meadow Levin stopped the horse.</p>
<p role="noindent">The morning dew was still lying on the thick undergrowth of the grass, and that he might not get his feet wet, Sergey Ivanovitch asked his brother to drive him in the trap up to the willow tree from which the carp was caught. Sorry as Konstantin Levin was to crush down his mowing grass, he drove him into the meadow. The high grass softly turned about the wheels and the horse’s legs, leaving its seeds clinging to the wet axles and spokes of the wheels. His brother seated himself under a bush, arranging his tackle, while Levin led the horse away, fastened him up, and walked into the vast gray-green sea of grass unstirred by the wind. The silky grass with its ripe seeds came almost to his waist in the dampest spots.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_480">480</target>
<p role="noindent">Crossing the meadow, Konstantin Levin came out onto the road, and met an old man with a swollen eye, carrying a skep on his shoulder.</p>
<p role="noindent">"What? taken a stray swarm, Fomitch?" he asked.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, indeed, Konstantin Dmitrich! All we can do to keep our own! This is the second swarm that has flown away.... Luckily the lads caught them. They were ploughing your field. They unyoked the horses and galloped after them."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, what do you say, Fomitch—start mowing or wait a bit?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Eh, well. Our way's to wait till St. Peter's Day. But you always mow sooner. Well, to be sure, please God, the hay's good. There'll be plenty for the beasts."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What do you think about the weather?" "That's in God's hands. Maybe it will be fine." Levin went up to his brother.</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch had caught nothing, but he was not bored, and seemed in the most cheerful frame of mind. Levin saw that, stimulated by his conversation with the doctor, he wanted to talk. Levin, on the other hand, would have liked to get home as soon as possible to give orders about getting together the mowers for next day, and to set at rest his doubts about the mowing, which greatly absorbed him.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, let's be going," he said.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_481">481</target>
<p role="noindent">"Why be in such a hurry? Let’s stay a little. But how wet you are! Even though one catches nothing, it’s nice. That’s the best thing about every part of sport, that one has to do with nature. How exquisite this steely water is!" said Sergey Ivanovitch. "These riverside banks always remind me of the riddle— do you know it? ‘The grass says to the water: we quiver and we quiver.’"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I don’t know the riddle," answered Levin wearily.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_482">482</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter3">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>III</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">"Do you know, I’ve been thinking about you," said Sergey Ivanovitch. "It’s beyond everything what’s being done in the district, according to what this doctor tells me. He’s a very intelligent fellow. And as I’ve told you before, I tell you again: it’s not right for you not to go to the meetings, and altogether to keep out of the district business. If decent people won’t go into it, of course it’s bound to go all wrong. We pay the money, and it all goes in salaries, and there are no schools, nor district nurses, nor midwives, nor drugstores— nothing."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, I did try, you know," Levin said slowly and unwillingly. "I can’t! and so there’s no help for it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"But why can’t you? I must own I can’t make it out. Indifference, incapacity—I won’t admit; surely it’s not simply laziness?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"None of those things. I’ve tried, and I see I can do nothing," said Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">He had hardly grasped what his brother was saying. Looking towards the plough land across the river, he made out something black, but he could not distinguish whether it was a horse or the bailiff on horseback</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_483">483</target>
<p role="noindent">"Why is it you can do nothing? You made an attempt and didn’t succeed, as you think, and you give in. How can you have so little self-respect?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Self-respect!" said Levin, stung to the quick by his brother’s words; "I don’t understand. If they’d told me at college that other people understood the integral calculus, and I didn’t, then pride would have come in. But in this case one wants first to be convinced that one has certain qualifications for this sort of business, and especially that all this business is of great importance."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What! do you mean to say it’s not of importance?" said Sergey Ivanovitch, stung to the quick too at his brother’s considering anything of no importance that interested him, and still more at his obviously paying little attention to what he was saying.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I don’t think it important; it does not take hold of me, I can’t help it," answered Levin, making out that what he saw was the bailiff, and that the bailiff seemed to be letting the peasants go off the ploughed land. They were turning the plough over. "Can they have finished ploughing?" he wondered.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Come, really though," said the elder brother, with a frown on his handsome, clever face, "there’s a limit to everything. It’s very well to be original and genuine, and to dislike everything conventional—I know all about that; but really, what you’re saying either has no meaning, or it has a very wrong meaning.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_483">483</target>
<p role="noindent">How can you think it a matter of no importance whether the peasant, whom you love as you assert..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I never did assert it," thought Konstantin Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"... dies without help? The ignorant peasant-women starve the children, and the people stagnate in darkness, and are helpless in the hands of every village clerk, while you have at your disposal a means of helping them, and don't help them because to your mind it's of no importance."</p>
<p role="noindent">And Sergey Ivanovitch put before him the alternative: either you are so undeveloped that you can't see all that you can do, or you won't sacrifice your ease, your vanity, or whatever it is, to do it.</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin felt that there was no course open to him but to submit, or to confess to a lack of zeal for the public good. And this mortified him and hurt his feelings.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It's both," he said resolutely: "I don't see that it was possible..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What! was it impossible, if the money were properly laid out, to provide medical aid?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Impossible, as it seems to me.... For the three thousand square miles of our district, what with our thaws, and the storms, and the work in the fields, I don't see how it is possible to provide medical aid all over. And besides, I don't believe in medicine."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, well, that’s unfair ... I can quote to you thousands of instances But <target target-type="page" id="page_485">485</target>the schools, anyway."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Why have schools?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"What do you mean? Can there be two opinions of the advantage of education? If it's a good thing for you, it's a good thing for everyone."</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin felt himself morally pinned against a wall, and so he got hot, and unconsciously blurted out the chief cause of his indifference to public business.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Perhaps it may all be very good; but why should I worry myself about establishing dispensaries which I shall never make use of, and schools to which I shall never send my children, to which even the peasants don't want to send their children, and to which I've no very firm faith that they ought to send them?" said he.</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch was for a minute surprised at this unexpected view of the subject; but he promptly made a new plan of attack. He was silent for a little, drew out a hook, threw it in again, and turned to his brother smiling.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Come, now.... In the first place, the dispensary is needed. We ourselves sent for the district doctor for Agafea Mihalovna."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, well, but I fancy her wrist will never be straight again."</p>
<p role="noindent">"That remains to be proved.... Next, the peasant who can read and write is as a workman of more use and value to you."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_486">486</target>
<p role="noindent">"No, you can ask anyone you like," Konstantin Levin answered with decision, "the man that can read and write is much inferior as a workman. And mending the highroads is an impossibility; and as soon as they put up bridges they're stolen."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Still, that's not the point," said Sergey Ivanovitch, frowning. He disliked contradiction, and still more, arguments that were continually skipping from one thing to another, introducing new and disconnected points, so that there was no knowing to which to reply. "Do you admit that education is a benefit for the people?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, I admit it," said Levin without thinking, and he was conscious immediately that he had said what he did not think. He felt that if he admitted that, it would be proved that he had been talking meaningless rubbish. How it would be proved he could not tell, but he knew that this would inevitably be logically proved to him, and he awaited the proofs.</p>
<p role="noindent">The argument turned out to be far simpler than he had expected.</p>
<p role="noindent">"If you admit that it is a benefit," said Sergey Ivanovitch, "then, as an honest man, you cannot help caring about it and sympathizing with the movement, and so wishing to work for it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"But I still do not admit this movement to be just," said Konstantin Levin, reddening a little.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_487">487</target>
<p role="noindent">"What! But you said just now..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"That’s to say, I don’t admit it’s being either good or possible." </p>
<p role="noindent">"That you can’t tell without making the trial."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, supposing that’s so," said Levin, though he did not suppose so at all, "supposing that is so, still I don’t see, all the same, what I’m to worry myself about it for."</p>
<p role="noindent">"How so?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; since we are talking, explain it to me from the philosophical point of view," said Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I can’t see where philosophy comes in," said Sergey Ivanovitch, in a tone, Levin fancied, as though he did not admit his brother’s right to talk about philosophy. And that irritated Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’ll tell you, then," he said with heat, "I imagine the mainspring of all our actions is, after all, self-interest. Now in the local institutions I, as a nobleman, see nothing that could conduce to my prosperity, and the roads are not better and could not be better; my horses carry me well enough over bad ones. Doctors and dispensaries are no use to me. An arbitrator of disputes is no use to me. I never appeal to him, and never shall appeal to him. The schools are no good to me, but positively harmful, as I told you. For me the district institutions simply mean the liability to pay fourpence halfpenny for every three acres, to drive into the town, sleep with bugs, and listen to all sorts of idiocy and loathsomeness, and self-interest offers me no inducement."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_488">488</target>
<p role="noindent">"Excuse me," Sergey Ivanovitch interposed with a smile, "selfinterest did not induce us to work for the emancipation of the serfs, but we did work for it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"No!" Konstantin Levin broke in with still greater heat; "the emancipation of the serfs was a different matter. There selfinterest did come in. One longed to throw off that yoke that crushed us, all decent people among us. But to be a town councilor and discuss how many dustmen are needed, and how chimneys shall be constructed in the town in which I don’t live— to serve on a jury and try a peasant who’s stolen a flitch of bacon, and listen for six hours at a stretch to all sorts of jabber from the counsel for the defense and the prosecution, and the president cross-examining my old half-witted Alioshka, ‘Do you admit, prisoner in the dock, the fact of the removal of the bacon?’ ‘Eh?’"</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin had warmed to his subject, and began mimicking the president and the half-witted Alioshka: it seemed to him that it was all to the point.</p>
<p role="noindent">But Sergey Ivanovitch shrugged his shoulders. "Well, what do you mean to say, then?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I simply mean to say that those rights that touch me ... my interest, I shall always defend to the best of my ability; that when they made raids on us students, and the police read our <target target-type="page" id="page_489">489</target>letters, I was ready to defend those rights to the utmost, to defend my rights to education and freedom. I can understand compulsory military service, which affects my children, my brothers, and myself, I am ready to deliberate on what concerns me; but deliberating on how to spend forty thousand roubles of district council money, or judging the half- witted Alioshka—I don’t understand, and I can’t do it."</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin Levin spoke as though the floodgates of his speech had burst open. Sergey Ivanovitch smiled.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But tomorrow it’ll be your turn to be tried; would it have suited your tastes better to be tried in the old criminal tribunal?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’m not going to be tried. I shan’t murder anybody, and I’ve no need of it. Well, I tell you what," he went on, flying off again to a subject quite beside the point, "our district self-government and all the rest of it—it’s just like the birch branches we stick in the ground on Trinity Day, for instance, to look like a copse which has grown up of itself in Europe, and I can’t gush over these birch branches and believe in them."</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch merely shrugged his shoulders, as though to express his wonder how the birch branches had come into their argument at that point, though he did really understand at once what his brother meant.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Excuse me, but you know one really can’t argue in that way," he observed.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_490">490</target>
<p role="noindent">But Konstantin Levin wanted to justify himself for the failing, of which he was conscious, of lack of zeal for the public welfare, and he went on.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I imagine," he said, "that no sort of activity is likely to be lasting if it is not founded on self-interest, that’s a universal principle, a philosophical principle," he said, repeating the word "philosophical" with determination, as though wishing to show that he had as much right as any one else to talk of philosophy.</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch smiled. "He too has a philosophy of his own at the service of his natural tendencies," he thought.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Come, you’d better let philosophy alone," he said. "The chief problem of the philosophy of all ages consists just in finding the indispensable connection which exists between individual and social interests. But that’s not to the point; what is to the point is a correction I must make in your comparison. The birches are not simply stuck in, but some are sown and some are planted, and one must deal carefully with them. It’s only those peoples that have an intuitive sense of what’s of importance and significance in their institutions, and know how to value them, that have a future before them—it’s only those peoples that one can truly call historical."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_491">491</target>
<p role="noindent">And Sergey Ivanovitch carried the subject into the regions of philosophical history where Konstantin Levin could not follow him, and showed him all the incorrectness of his view.</p>
<p role="noindent">"As for your dislike of it, excuse my saying so, that’s simply our Russian sloth and old serf-owner’s ways, and I’m convinced that in you it’s a temporary error and will pass."</p>
<p role="noindent">Konstantin was silent. He felt himself vanquished on all sides, but he felt at the same time that what he wanted to say was unintelligible to his brother. Only he could not make up his mind whether it was unintelligible because he was not capable of expressing his meaning clearly, or because his brother would not or could not understand him. But he did not pursue the speculation, and without replying, he fell to musing on a quite different and personal matter.</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch wound up the last line, untied the horse, and they drove off.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_492">492</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter4">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>IV</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The personal matter that absorbed Levin during his conversation with his brother was this. Once in a previous year he had gone to look at the mowing, and being made very angry by the bailiff he had recourse to his favorite means for regaining his temper,—he took a scythe from a peasant and began mowing.</p>
<p role="noindent">He liked the work so much that he had several times tried his hand at mowing since. He had cut the whole of the meadow in front of his house, and this year ever since the early spring he had cherished a plan for mowing for whole days together with the peasants. Ever since his brother’s arrival, he had been in doubt whether to mow or not. He was loath to leave his brother alone all day long, and he was afraid his brother would laugh at him about it. But as he drove into the meadow, and recalled the sensations of mowing, he came near deciding that he would go mowing. After the irritating discussion with his brother, he pondered over this intention again.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I must have physical exercise, or my temper’ll certainly be ruined," he thought, and he determined he would go mowing, however awkward he might feel about it with his brother or the peasants.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_493">493</target>
<p role="noindent">Towards evening Konstantin Levin went to his counting house, gave directions as to the work to be done, and sent about the village to summon the mowers for the morrow, to cut the hay in Kalinov meadow, the largest and best of his grass lands.</p>
<p role="noindent">"And send my scythe, please, to Tit, for him to set it, and bring it round tomorrow. I shall maybe do some mowing myself too," he said, trying not to be embarrassed.</p>
<p role="noindent">The bailiff smiled and said: "Yes, sir."</p>
<p role="noindent">At tea the same evening Levin said to his brother:</p>
<p role="noindent">"I fancy the fine weather will last. Tomorrow I shall start mowing." "I’m so fond of that form of field labor," said Sergey Ivanovitch.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’m awfully fond of it. I sometimes mow myself with the peasants, and tomorrow I want to try mowing the whole day."</p>
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch lifted his head, and looked with interest at his brother. "How do you mean? Just like one of the peasants, all day long?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, it’s very pleasant," said Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It’s splendid as exercise, only you’ll hardly be able to stand it," said Sergey Ivanovitch, without a shade of irony</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’ve tried it. It’s hard work at first, but you get into it. I dare say I shall manage to keep it up..."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_494">494</target>
<p role="noindent">"Really! what an idea! But tell me, how do the peasants look at it? I suppose they laugh in their sleeves at their master’s being such a queer fish?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, I don’t think so; but it’s so delightful, and at the same time such hard work, that one has no time to think about it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"But how will you do about dining with them? To send you a bottle of Lafitte and roast turkey out there would be a little awkward."</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, I’ll simply come home at the time of their noonday rest."</p>
<p role="noindent">Next morning Konstantin Levin got up earlier than usual, but he was detained giving directions on the farm, and when he reached the mowing grass the mowers were already at their second row</p>
<p role="noindent">From the uplands he could get a view of the shaded cut part of the meadow below, with its grayish ridges of cut grass, and the black heaps of coats, taken off by the mowers at the place from which they had started cutting.</p>
<p role="noindent">Gradually, as he rode towards the meadow, the peasants came into sight, some in coats, some in their shirts mowing, one behind another in a long string, swinging their scythes differently. He counted forty-two of them.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_495">495</target>
<p role="noindent">They were mowing slowly over the uneven, low-lying parts of the meadow, where there had been an old dam. Levin recognized some of his own men. Here was old Yermil in a very long white smock, bending forward to swing a scythe; there was a young fellow, Vaska, who had been a coachman of Levin’s, taking every row with a wide sweep. Here, too, was Tit, Levin’s preceptor in the art of mowing, a thin little peasant. He was in front of all, and cut his wide row without bending, as though playing with the scythe.</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin got off his mare, and fastening her up by the roadside went to meet Tit, who took a second scythe out of a bush and gave it to him.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It’s ready, sir; it’s like a razor, cuts of itself," said Tit, taking off his cap with a smile and giving him the scythe.</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin took the scythe, and began trying it. As they finished their rows, the mowers, hot and good-humored, came out into the road one after another, and, laughing a little, greeted the master. They all stared at him, but no one made any remark, till a tall old man, with a wrinkled, beardless face, wearing a short sheepskin jacket, came out into the road and accosted him.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Look’ee now, master, once take hold of the rope there’s no letting it go!" he said, and Levin heard smothered laughter among the mowers.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’ll try not to let it go," he said, taking his stand behind Tit, and waiting for the time to begin.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_496">496</target>
<p role="noindent">"Mind’ee," repeated the old man.</p>
<p role="noindent">Tit made room, and Levin started behind him. The grass was short close to the road, and Levin, who had not done any mowing for a long while, and was disconcerted by the eyes fastened upon him, cut badly for the first moments, though he swung his scythe vigorously. Behind him he heard voices:</p>
<p role="noindent">"It’s not set right; handle’s too high; see how he has to stoop to it," said one.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Press more on the heel," said another.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Never mind, he’ll get on all right," the old man resumed.</p>
<p role="noindent">"He’s made a start.... You swing it too wide, you’ll tire yourself out The master, sure, does his best for himself! But see the grass missed out! For such work us fellows would catch it!"</p>
<p role="noindent">The grass became softer, and Levin, listening without answering, followed Tit, trying to do the best he could. They moved a hundred paces. Tit kept moving on, without stopping, not showing the slightest weariness, but Levin was already beginning to be afraid he would not be able to keep it up: he was so tired.</p>
<p role="noindent">He felt as he swung his scythe that he was at the very end of his strength, and was making up his mind to ask Tit to stop. But at that very moment Tit stopped of his own accord, and stooping <target target-type="page" id="page_497">497</target>
down picked up some grass, rubbed his scythe, and began whetting it. Levin straightened himself, and drawing a deep breath looked round. Behind him came a peasant, and he too was evidently tired, for he stopped at once without waiting to mow up to Levin, and began whetting his scythe. Tit sharpened his scythe and Levin’s, and they went on. The next time it was just the same. Tit moved on with sweep after sweep of his scythe, not stopping nor showing signs of weariness. Levin followed him, trying not to get left behind, and he found it harder and harder: the moment came when he felt he had no strength left, but at that very moment Tit stopped and whetted the scythes.</p>
<p role="noindent">So they mowed the first row. And this long row seemed particularly hard work to Levin; but when the end was reached and Tit, shouldering his scythe, began with deliberate stride returning on the tracks left by his heels in the cut grass, and Levin walked back in the same way over the space he had cut, in spite of the sweat that ran in streams over his face and fell in drops down his nose, and drenched his back as though he had been soaked in water, he felt very happy. What delighted him particularly was that now he knew he would be able to hold out.</p>
<p role="noindent">His pleasure was only disturbed by his row not being well cut. "I will swing less with my arm and more with my whole body," he thought, comparing Tit’s row, which looked as if it had been cut with a line, with his own unevenly and irregularly lying grass.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_498">498</target>
<p role="noindent">The first row, as Levin noticed, Tit had mowed specially quickly, probably wishing to put his master to the test, and the row happened to be a long one. The next rows were easier, but still Levin had to strain every nerve not to drop behind the peasants.</p>
<p role="noindent">He thought of nothing, wished for nothing, but not to be left behind the peasants, and to do his work as well as possible. He heard nothing but the swish of scythes, and saw before him Tit’s upright figure mowing away, the crescent-shaped curve of the cut grass, the grass and flower heads slowly and rhythmically falling before the blade of his scythe, and ahead of him the end of the row, where would come the rest.</p>
<p role="noindent">Suddenly, in the midst of his toil, without understanding what it was or whence it came, he felt a pleasant sensation of chill on his hot, moist shoulders. He glanced at the sky in the interval for whetting the scythes. A heavy, lowering storm cloud had blown up, and big raindrops were falling. Some of the peasants went to their coats and put them on; others—just like Levin himself— merely shrugged their shoulders, enjoying the pleasant coolness of it.</p>
<p role="noindent">Another row, and yet another row, followed—long rows and short rows, with good grass and with poor grass. Levin lost all sense of time, and could not have told whether it was late or early now. A change began to come over his work, which gave <target target-type="page" id="page_499">499</target>him immense satisfaction. In the midst of his toil there were moments during which he forgot what he was doing, and it came all easy to him, and at those same moments his row was almost as smooth and well cut as Tit’s. But so soon as he recollected what he was doing, and began trying to do better, he was at once conscious of all the difficulty of his task, and the row was badly mown.</p>
<p role="noindent">On finishing yet another row he would have gone back to the top of the meadow again to begin the next, but Tit stopped, and going up to the old man said something in a low voice to him. They both looked at the sun. "What are they talking about, and why doesn’t he go back?" thought Levin, not guessing that the peasants had been mowing no less than four hours without stopping, and it was time for their lunch.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Lunch, sir," said the old man.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Is it really time? That’s right; lunch, then."</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin gave his scythe to Tit, and together with the peasants, who were crossing the long stretch of mown grass, slightly sprinkled with rain, to get their bread from the heap of coats, he went towards his house. Only then he suddenly awoke to the fact that he had been wrong about the weather and the rain was drenching his hay.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The hay will be spoiled," he said.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Not a bit of it, sir; mow in the rain, and you’ll rake in fineweather!" said the old man.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_500">500</target>
<p role="noindent">Levin untied his horse and rode home to his coffee. Sergey Ivanovitch was only just getting up. When he had drunk his coffee, Levin rode back again to the mowing before Sergey Ivanovitch had had time to dress and come down to the dining room.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_501">501</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter5">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>Part Three</title>
<title>CHAPTER <label>V</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">After lunch Levin was not in the same place in the string of mowers as before, but stood between the old man who had accosted him jocosely, and now invited him to be his neighbor, and a young peasant, who had only been married in the autumn, and who was mowing this summer for the first time.</p> 
<p role="noindent">The old man, holding himself erect, moved in front, with his feet turned out, taking long, regular strides, and with a precise and regular action which seemed to cost him no more effort than swinging one's arms in walking, as though it were in play, he laid down the high, even row of grass. It was as though it were not he but the sharp scythe of itself swishing through the juicy grass.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Behind Levin came the lad Mishka. His pretty, boyish face, with a twist of fresh grass bound round his hair, was all working with effort; but whenever anyone looked at him he smiled. He would clearly have died sooner than own it was hard work for him.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin kept between them. In the very heat of the day the mowing did not seem such hard work to him. The perspiration with which he was drenched cooled him, while the sun, that burned his back, his head, and his arms, bare to the elbow, gave a vigor and dogged energy to his labor; and more and more often now came those moments of unconsciousness, when it was possible not to think what one was doing. The scythe cut of<target target-type="page" id="page_502">502</target>itself. These were happy moments. Still more delightful were the moments when they reached the stream where the rows ended, and the old man rubbed his scythe with the wet, thick grass, rinsed its blade in the fresh water of the stream, ladled out a little in a tin dipper, and offered Levin a drink.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"What do you say to my home-brew, eh? Good, eh?" said he, winking.</p> 
<p role="noindent">And truly Levin had never drunk any liquor so good as this warm water with green bits floating in it, and a taste of rust from the tin dipper. And immediately after this came the delicious, slow saunter, with his hand on the scythe, during which he could wipe away the streaming sweat, take deep breaths of air, and look about at the long string of mowers and at what was happening around in the forest and the country.</p> 
<p role="noindent">The longer Levin mowed, the oftener he felt the moments of unconsciousness in which it seemed not his hands that swung the scythe, but the scythe mowing of itself, a body full of life and consciousness of its own, and as though by magic, without thinking of it, the work turned out regular and well-finished of itself. These were the most blissful moments.</p> 
<p role="noindent">It was only hard work when he had to break off the motion, which had become unconscious, and to think; when he had to mow round a hillock or a<target target-type="page" id="page_503">503</target>tuft of sorrel. The old man did this easily. When a hillock came he changed his action, and at one time with the heel, and at another with the tip of his scythe, clipped the hillock round both sides with short strokes. And while he did this he kept looking about and watching what came into his view: at one moment he picked a wild berry and ate it or offered it to Levin, then he flung away a twig with the blade of the scythe, then he looked at a quail's nest, from which the bird flew just under the scythe, or caught a snake that crossed his path, and lifting it on the scythe as though on a fork showed it to Levin and threw it away.</p> 
<p role="noindent">For both Levin and the young peasant behind him, such changes of position were difficult. Both of them, repeating over and over again the same strained movement, were in a perfect frenzy of toil, and were incapable of shifting their position and at the same time watching what was before them.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin did not notice how time was passing. If he had been asked how long he had been working he would have said half an hour—and it was getting on for dinner time. As they were walking back over the cut grass, the old man called Levin's attention to the little girls and boys who were coming from different directions, hardly visible through the long grass, and along the road towards the mowers, carrying sacks of bread dragging at their little hands and pitchers of the sour rye-beer, with cloths wrapped round them.<target target-type="page" id="page_504">504</target></p> 
<p role="noindent">"Look'ee, the little emmets crawling!" he said, pointing to them, and he shaded his eyes with his hand to look at the sun. They mowed two more rows; the old man stopped.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Come, master, dinner time!" he said briskly. And on reaching the stream the mowers moved off across the lines of cut grass towards their pile of coats, where the children who had brought their dinners were sitting waiting for them. The peasants gathered into groups—those further away under a cart, those nearer under a willow bush.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin sat down by them; he felt disinclined to go away.</p> 
<p role="noindent">All constraint with the master had disappeared long ago. The peasants got ready for dinner. Some washed, the young lads bathed in the stream, others made a place comfortable for a rest, untied their sacks of bread, and uncovered the pitchers of rye-beer. The old man crumbled up some bread in a cup, stirred it with the handle of a spoon, poured water on it from the dipper, broke up some more bread, and having seasoned it with salt, he turned to the east to say his prayer.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Come, master, taste my sop," said he, kneeling down before the cup.</p> 
<p role="noindent">The sop was so good that Levin gave up the idea of going home. He dined with the old man, and talked to him about his family affairs, taking the keenest<target target-type="page" id="page_505">505</target>interest in them, and told him about his own affairs and all the circumstances that could be of interest to the old man. He felt much nearer to him than to his brother, and could not help smiling at the affection he felt for this man. When the old man got up again, said his prayer, and lay down under a bush, putting some grass under his head for a pillow, Levin did the same, and in spite of the clinging flies that were so persistent in the sunshine, and the midges that tickled his hot face and body, he fell asleep at once and only waked when the sun had passed to the other side of the bush and reached him. The old man had been awake a long while, and was sitting up whetting the scythes of the younger lads.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin looked about him and hardly recognized the place, everything was so changed. The immense stretch of meadow had been mown and was sparkling with a peculiar fresh brilliance, with its lines of already sweet-smelling grass in the slanting rays of the evening sun. And the bushes about the river had been cut down, and the river itself, not visible before, now gleaming like steel in its bends, and the moving, ascending, peasants, and the sharp wall of grass of the unmown part of the meadow, and the hawks hovering over the stripped meadow—all was perfectly new. Raising himself, Levin began considering how much had been cut and how much more could still be done that day.</p> 
<p role="noindent">The work done was exceptionally much for forty-two men. They had cut the whole of the big meadow, which had, in the years of<target target-type="page" id="page_506">506</target>serf labor, taken thirty scythes two days to mow. Only the corners remained to do, where the rows were short. But Levin felt a longing to get as much mowing done that day as possible, and was vexed with the sun sinking so quickly in the sky. He felt no weariness; all he wanted was to get his work done more and more quickly and as much done as possible.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Could you cut Mashkin Upland too?—what do you think?" he said to the old man.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"As God wills, the sun's not high. A little vodka for the lads?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">At the afternoon rest, when they were sitting down again, and those who smoked had lighted their pipes, the old man told the men that "Mashkin Upland's to be cut—there'll be some vodka."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Why not cut it? Come on, Tit! We'll look sharp! We can eat at night. Come on!" cried voices, and eating up their bread, the mowers went back to work.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Come, lads, keep it up!" said Tit, and ran on ahead almost at a trot.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Get along, get along!" said the old man, hurrying after him and easily overtaking him, "I'll mow you down, look out!"</p> 
<p role="noindent">And young and old mowed away, as though they were racing with one another. But however fast they worked, they did not spoil the grass, and the rows were laid just as neatly and exactly. The little piece left uncut in the corner was mown in five<target target-type="page" id="page_507">507</target>minutes. The last of the mowers were just ending their rows while the foremost snatched up their coats onto their shoulders, and crossed the road towards Mashkin Upland.</p> 
<p role="noindent">The sun was already sinking into the trees when they went with their jingling dippers into the wooded ravine of Mashkin Upland. The grass was up to their waists in the middle of the hollow, soft, tender, and feathery, spotted here and there among the trees with wild heart's-ease.</p> 
<p role="noindent">After a brief consultation—whether to take the rows lengthwise or diagonally—Prohor Yermilin, also a renowned mower, a huge, black-haired peasant, went on ahead. He went up to the top, turned back again and started mowing, and they all proceeded to form in line behind him, going downhill through the hollow and uphill right up to the edge of the forest. The sun sank behind the forest. The dew was falling by now; the mowers were in the sun only on the hillside, but below, where a mist was rising, and on the opposite side, they mowed into the fresh, dewy shade. The work went rapidly. The grass cut with a juicy sound, and was at once laid in high, fragrant rows. The mowers from all sides, brought closer together in the short row, kept urging one another on to the sound of jingling dippers and clanging scythes, and the hiss of the whetstones sharpening them, and good-humored shouts.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin still kept between the young peasant and the old man. The old man, who had put on his short sheepskin jacket, was just as good-humored, jocose, and free in his movements. Among the<target target-type="page" id="page_508">508</target>trees they were continually cutting with their scythes the so-called "birch mushrooms," swollen fat in the succulent grass. But the old man bent down every time he came across a mushroom, picked it up and put it in his bosom. "Another present for my old woman," he said as he did so.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Easy as it was to mow the wet, soft grass, it was hard work going up and down the steep sides of the ravine. But this did not trouble the old man. Swinging his scythe just as ever, and moving his feet in their big, plaited shoes with firm, little steps, he climbed slowly up the steep place, and though his breeches hanging out below his smock, and his whole frame trembled with effort, he did not miss one blade of grass or one mushroom on his way, and kept making jokes with the peasants and Levin. Levin walked after him and often thought he must fall, as he climbed with a scythe up a steep cliff where it would have been hard work to clamber without anything. But he climbed up and did what he had to do. He felt as though some external force were moving him.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_509">509</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter6">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>VI</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Mashkin Upland was mown, the last row finished, the peasants had put on their coats and were gaily trudging home. Levin got on his horse and, parting regretfully from the peasants, rode homewards. On the hillside he looked back; he could not see them in the mist that had risen from the valley; he could only hear rough, good-humored voices, laughter, and the sound of clanking scythes.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch had long ago finished dinner, and was drinking iced lemon and water in his own room, looking through the reviews and papers which he had only just received by post, when Levin rushed into the room, talking merrily, with his wet and matted hair sticking to his forehead, and his back and chest grimed and moist.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"We mowed the whole meadow! Oh, it is nice, delicious! And how have you been getting on?" said Levin, completely forgetting the disagreeable conversation of the previous day.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Mercy! what do you look like!" said Sergey Ivanovitch, for the first moment looking round with some dissatisfaction. "And the door, do shut the door!" he cried. "You must have let in a dozen at least."</p> 
<p role="noindent">Sergey Ivanovitch could not endure flies, and in his own room he never opened the window except at night, and carefully kept the door shut.<target target-type="page" id="page_510">510</target></p> 
<p role="noindent">"Not one, on my honor. But if I have, I'll catch them. You wouldn't believe what a pleasure it is! How have you spent the day?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Very well. But have you really been mowing the whole day? I expect you're as hungry as a wolf. Kouzma has got everything ready for you."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"No, I don't feel hungry even. I had something to eat there. But I'll go and wash."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Yes, go along, go along, and I'll come to you directly," said Sergey Ivanovitch, shaking his head as he looked at his brother. "Go along, make haste," he added smiling, and gathering up his books, he prepared to go too. He, too, felt suddenly good-humored and disinclined to leave his brother's side. "But what did you do while it was raining?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Rain? Why, there was scarcely a drop. I'll come directly. So you had a nice day too? That's first-rate." And Levin went off to change his clothes.</p> 
<p role="noindent">Five minutes later the brothers met in the dining room. Although it seemed to Levin that he was not hungry, and he sat down to dinner simply so as not to<target target-type="page" id="page_511">511</target>hurt Kouzma's feelings, yet when he began to eat the dinner struck him as extraordinarily good. Sergey Ivanovitch watched him with a smile.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Oh, by the way, there's a letter for you," said he. "Kouzma, bring it down, please. And mind you shut the doors."</p> 
<p role="noindent">The letter was from Oblonsky. Levin read it aloud. Oblonsky wrote to him from Petersburg: "I have had a letter from Dolly; she's at Ergushovo, and everything seems going wrong there. Do ride over and see her, please; help her with advice; you know all about it. She will be so glad to see you. She's quite alone, poor thing. My mother-in-law and all of them are still abroad."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"That's capital! I will certainly ride over to her," said Levin. "Or we'll go together. She's such a splendid woman, isn't she?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"They're not far from here, then?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Twenty-five miles. Or perhaps it is thirty. But a capital road. Capital, we'll drive over."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"I shall be delighted," said Sergey Ivanovitch, still smiling. The sight of his younger brother's appearance had immediately put him in a good humor.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Well, you have an appetite!" he said, looking at his dark-red, sunburnt face and neck bent over the plate.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Splendid! You can't imagine what an effectual remedy it is for every sort of foolishness. I want to enrich medicine with a new word: Arbeitskur."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Well, but you don't need it, I should fancy." "No, but for all sorts of nervous invalids."<target target-type="page" id="page_512">512</target></p> 
<p role="noindent">"Yes, it ought to be tried. I had meant to come to the mowing to look at you, but it was so unbearably hot that I got no further than the forest. I sat there a little, and went on by the forest to the village, met your old nurse, and sounded her as to the peasants' view of you. As far as I can make out, they don't approve of this. She said: 'It's not a gentleman's work.' Altogether, I fancy that in the people's ideas there are very clear and definite notions of certain, as they call it, 'gentlemanly' lines of action. And they don't sanction the gentry's moving outside bounds clearly laid down in their ideas."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Maybe so; but anyway it's a pleasure such as I have never known in my life. And there's no harm in it, you know. Is there?" answered Levin. "I can't help it if they don't like it. Though I do believe it's all right. Eh?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Altogether," pursued Sergey Ivanovitch, "you're satisfied with your day?" "Quite satisfied. We cut the whole meadow. And such a splendid old man I<target target-type="page" id="page_513">513</target>made friends with there! You can't fancy how delightful he was!"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Well, so you're content with your day. And so am I. First, I solved two chess problems, and one a very pretty one—a pawn opening. I'll show it you. And then—I thought over our conversation yesterday."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Eh! our conversation yesterday?" said Levin, blissfully dropping his eyelids and drawing deep breaths after finishing his dinner, and absolutely incapable of recalling what their conversation yesterday was about.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"I think you are partly right. Our difference of opinion amounts to this, that you make the mainspring self-interest, while I suppose that interest in the common weal is bound to exist in every man of a certain degree of advancement. Possibly you are right too, that action founded on material interest would be more desirable. You are altogether, as the French say, too primesautière a nature; you must have intense, energetic action, or nothing."</p> 
<p role="noindent">Levin listened to his brother and did not understand a single word, and did not want to understand. He was only afraid his brother might ask him some question which would make it evident he had not heard.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"So that's what I think it is, my dear boy," said Sergey Ivanovitch, touching him on the shoulder.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Yes, of course. But, do you know? I won't stand up for my view," answered Levin, with a guilty, childlike smile. "Whatever was it I was disputing about?" he wondered. "Of course, I'm right, and he's right, and it's all first-rate. Only I must go round to the counting house and see to things." He got up, stretching and smiling. Sergey Ivanovitch smiled too.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"If you want to go out, let's go together," he said, disinclined to be parted from his brother, who seemed positively breathing<target target-type="page" id="page_514">514</target>out freshness and energy. "Come, we'll go to the counting house, if you have to go there."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Oh, heavens!" shouted Levin, so loudly that Sergey Ivanovitch was quite frightened.</p> 
<p role="noindent">"What, what is the matter?"</p> 
<p role="noindent">"How's Agafea Mihalovna's hand?" said Levin, slapping himself on the head. "I'd positively forgotten her even."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"It's much better."</p> 
<p role="noindent">"Well, anyway I'll run down to her. Before you've time to get your hat on, I'll be back."</p> 
<p role="noindent">And he ran downstairs, clattering with his heels like a spring-rattle.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_515">515</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter7">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>VII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Stephan Arkadyevitch had gone to Petersburg to perform the most natural and essential official duty—so familiar to everyone in the government service, though incomprehensible to outsiders—that duty, but for which one could hardly be in government service, of reminding the ministry of his existence— and having, for the due performance of this rite, taken all the available cash from home, was gaily and agreeably spending his days at the races and in the summer villas. Meanwhile Dolly and the children had moved into the country, to cut down expenses as much as possible. She had gone to Ergushovo, the estate that had been her dowry, and the one where in spring the forest had been sold. It was nearly forty miles from Levin’s Pokrovskoe. The big, old house at Ergushovo had been pulled down long ago, and the old prince had had the lodge done up and built on to. Twenty years before, when Dolly was a child, the lodge had been roomy and comfortable, though, like all lodges, it stood sideways to the entrance avenue, and faced the south.But by now this lodge was old and dilapidated. When Stepan Arkadyevitch had gone down in the spring to sell the forest, Dolly had begged him to look over the house and order what repairs might be needed. Stepan Arkadyevitch, like all unfaithful husbands indeed, was very solicitous for his wife’s comfort, and he had himself looked over the house, and given instructions about everything that he considered necessary. What he <target target-type="page" id="page_516">516</target>considered necessary was to cover all the furniture with cretonne, to put up curtains, to weed the garden, to make a little bridge on the pond, and to plant flowers. But he forgot many other essential matters, the want of which greatly distressed Darya Alexandrovna later on.</p>
<p role="noindent">In spite of Stepan Arkadyevitch’s efforts to be an attentive father and husband, he never could keep in his mind that he had a wife and children. He had bachelor tastes, and it was in accordance with them that he shaped his life. On his return to Moscow he informed his wife with pride that everything was ready, that the house would be a little paradise, and that he advised her most certainly to go. His wife’s staying away in the country was very agreeable to Stepan Arkadyevitch from every point of view: it did the children good, it decreased expenses, and it left him more at liberty. Darya Alexandrovna regarded staying in the country for the summer as essential for the children, especially for the little girl, who had not succeeded in regaining her strength after the scarlatina, and also as a means of escaping the petty humiliations, the little bills owing to the wood-merchant, the fishmonger, the shoemaker, which made her miserable. Besides this, she was pleased to go away to the country because she was dreaming of getting her sister Kitty to stay with her there. Kitty was to be back from abroad in the middle of the summer, and bathing had been prescribed for her.</p>
<p role="noindent">Kitty wrote that no prospect was so <target target-type="page" id="page_517">517</target>alluring as to spend the summer with Dolly at Ergushovo, full of childish associations for both of them.</p>
<p role="noindent">The first days of her existence in the country were very hard for Dolly. She used to stay in the country as a child, and the impression she had retained of it was that the country was a refuge from all the unpleasantness of the town, that life there, though not luxurious—Dolly could easily make up her mind to that —was cheap and comfortable; that there was plenty of everything, everything was cheap, everything could be got, and children were happy. But now coming to the country as the head of a family, she perceived that it was all utterly unlike what she had fancied.</p>
<p role="noindent">The day after their arrival there was a heavy fall of rain, and in the night the water came through in the corridor and in the nursery, so that the beds had to be carried into the drawing room. There was no kitchen maid to be found; of the nine cows, it appeared from the words of the cowherd-woman that some were about to calve, others had just calved, others were old, and others again hard-uddered; there was not butter nor milk enough even for the children. There were no eggs. They could get no fowls; old, purplish, stringy cocks were all they had for roasting and boiling. Impossible to get women to scrub the floors—all were potato-hoeing. Driving was out of the question, because one of the horses was restive, and bolted in the shafts. There was no place where they could bathe; the whole of the <target target-type="page" id="page_518">518</target>river-bank was trampled by the cattle and open to the road; even walks were impossible, for the cattle strayed into the garden through a gap in the hedge, and there was one terrible bull, who bellowed, and therefore might be expected to gore somebody. There were no proper cupboards for their clothes; what cupboards there were either would not close at all, or burst open whenever anyone passed by them. There were no pots and pans; there was no copper in the washhouse, nor even an ironing- board in the maids’ room.</p>
<p role="noindent">Finding instead of peace and rest all these, from her point of view, fearful calamities, Darya Alexandrovna was at first in despair. She exerted herself to the utmost, felt the hopelessness of the position, and was every instant suppressing the tears that started into her eyes. The bailiff, a retired quartermaster, whom Stepan Arkadyevitch had taken a fancy to and had appointed bailiff on account of his handsome and respectful appearance as a hall-porter, showed no sympathy for Darya Alexandrovna’s woes. He said respectfully, "nothing can be done, the peasants are such a wretched lot," and did nothing to help her.</p>
<p role="noindent">The position seemed hopeless. But in the Oblonskys’ household, as in all families indeed, there was one inconspicuous but most valuable and useful person, Marya Philimonovna. She soothed her mistress, assured her that everything would come round (it was her expression, and Matvey had <target target-type="page" id="page_519">519</target>borrowed it from her), and without fuss or hurry proceeded to set to work herself. She had immediately made friends with the bailiff’s wife, and on the very first day she drank tea with her and the bailiff under the acacias, and reviewed all the circumstances of the position. Very soon Marya Philimonovna had established her club, so to say, under the acacias, and there it was, in this club, consisting of the bailiff’s wife, the village elder, and the counting house clerk, that the difficulties of existence were gradually smoothed away, and in a week’s time everything actually had come round. The roof was mended, a kitchen maid was found—a crony of the village elder’s—hens were bought, the cows began giving milk, the garden hedge was stopped up with stakes, the carpenter made a mangle, hooks were put in the cupboards, and they ceased to burst open spontaneously, and an ironing-board covered with army cloth was placed across from the arm of a chair to the chest of drawers, and there was a smell of flatirons in the maids’ room.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Just see, now, and you were quite in despair," said Marya Philimonovna, pointing to the ironing-board. They even rigged up a bathing-shed of straw hurdles. Lily began to bathe, and Darya Alexandrovna began to realize, if only in part, her expectations, if not of a peaceful, at least of a comfortable, life in the country. Peaceful with six children Darya Alexandrovna could not be. One would fall ill, another might easily become so, a third would be without something necessary, a fourth would show symptoms of a bad disposition, and so on. Rare indeed <target target-type="page" id="page_520">520</target>were the brief periods of peace. But these cares and anxieties were for Darya Alexandrovna the sole happiness possible. Had it not been for them, she would have been left alone to brood over her husband who did not love her. And besides, hard though it was for the mother to bear the dread of illness, the illnesses themselves, and the grief of seeing signs of evil propensities in her children—the children themselves were even now repaying her in small joys for her sufferings. Those joys were so small that they passed unnoticed, like gold in sand, and at bad moments she could see nothing but the pain, nothing but sand; but there were good moments too when she saw nothing but the joy, nothing but gold.</p>
<p role="noindent">Now in the solitude of the country, she began to be more and more frequently aware of those joys. Often, looking at them, she would make every possible effort to persuade herself that she was mistaken, that she as a mother was partial to her children. All the same, she could not help saying to herself that she had charming children, all six of them in different ways, but a set of children such as is not often to be met with, and she was happy in them, and proud of them.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_521">521</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter8">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>VIII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Towards the end of May, when everything had been more or less satisfactorily arranged, she received her husband’s answer to her complaints of the disorganized state of things in the country. He wrote begging her forgiveness for not having thought of everything before, and promised to come down at the first chance. This chance did not present itself, and till the beginning of June Darya Alexandrovna stayed alone in the country.</p>
<p role="noindent">On the Sunday in St. Peter’s week Darya Alexandrovna drove to mass for all her children to take the sacrament. Darya Alexandrovna in her intimate, philosophical talks with her sister, her mother, and her friends very often astonished them by the freedom of her views in regard to religion. She had a strange religion of transmigration of souls all her own, in which she had firm faith, troubling herself little about the dogmas of the Church. But in her family she was strict in carrying out all that was required by the Church—and not merely in order to set an example, but with all her heart in it. The fact that the children had not been at the sacrament for nearly a year worried her extremely, and with the full approval and sympathy of Marya Philimonovna she decided that this should take place now in the summer.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_522">522</target>
<p role="noindent">For several days before, Darya Alexandrovna was busily deliberating on how to dress all the children. Frocks were made or altered and washed, seams and flounces were let out, buttons were sewn on, and ribbons got ready. One dress, Tanya’s, which the English governess had undertaken, cost Darya Alexandrovna much loss of temper. The English governess in altering it had made the seams in the wrong place, had taken up the sleeves too much, and altogether spoilt the dress. It was so narrow on Tanya’s shoulders that it was quite painful to look at her. But Marya Philimonovna had the happy thought of putting in gussets, and adding a little shoulder-cape.</p>
<p role="noindent">The dress was set right, but there was nearly a quarrel with the English governess. On the morning, however, all was happily arranged, and towards ten o’clock—the time at which they had asked the priest to wait for them for the mass—the children in their new dresses, with beaming faces, stood on the step before the carriage waiting for their mother.</p>
<p role="noindent">To the carriage, instead of the restive Raven, they had harnessed, thanks to the representations of Marya Philimonovna, the bailiff’s horse, Brownie, and Darya Alexandrovna, delayed by anxiety over her own attire, came out and got in, dressed in a white muslin gown.</p>
<p role="noindent">Darya Alexandrovna had done her hair, and dressed with care and excitement. In the old days she had dressed for her own sake to look pretty and be admired. Later on, as she got older, dress became more and more distasteful to her. She saw that <target target-type="page" id="page_523">523</target>she was losing her good looks. But now she began to feel pleasure and interest in dress again. Now she did not dress for her own sake, not for the sake of her own beauty, but simply that as the mother of those exquisite creatures she might not spoil the general effect. And looking at herself for the last time in the looking-glass she was satisfied with herself. She looked nice. Not nice as she would have wished to look nice in old days at a ball, but nice for the object which she now had in view.</p>
<p role="noindent">In the church there was no one but the peasants, the servants and their women-folk. But Darya Alexandrovna saw, or fancied she saw, the sensation produced by her children and her. The children were not only beautiful to look at in their smart little dresses, but they were charming in the way they behaved.</p>
<p role="noindent">Aliosha, it is true, did not stand quite correctly; he kept turning round, trying to look at his little jacket from behind; but all the same he was wonderfully sweet. Tanya behaved like a grownup person, and looked after the little ones. And the smallest, Lily, was bewitching in her naïve astonishment at everything, and it was difficult not to smile when, after taking the sacrament, she said in English, "Please, some more."</p>
<p role="noindent">On the way home the children felt that something solemn had happened, and were very sedate.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_524">524</target>
<p role="noindent">Everything went happily at home too; but at lunch Grisha began whistling, and, what was worse, was disobedient to the English governess, and was forbidden to have any tart. Darya Alexandrovna would not have let things go so far on such a day had she been present; but she had to support the English governess’s authority, and she upheld her decision that Grisha should have no tart. This rather spoiled the general good humor.</p>
<p role="noindent">Grisha cried, declaring that Nikolinka had whistled too, and he was not punished, and that he wasn’t crying for the tart—he didn’t care—but at being unjustly treated. This was really too tragic, and Darya Alexandrovna made up her mind to persuade the English governess to forgive Grisha, and she went to speak to her. But on the way, as she passed the drawing room, she beheld a scene, filling her heart with such pleasure that the tears came into her eyes, and she forgave the delinquent herself.</p>
<p role="noindent">The culprit was sitting at the window in the corner of the drawing room; beside him was standing Tanya with a plate. On the pretext of wanting to give some dinner to her dolls, she had asked the governess’s permission to take her share of tart to the nursery, and had taken it instead to her brother. While still weeping over the injustice of his punishment, he was eating the tart, and kept saying through his sobs, "Eat yourself; let’s eat it together ... together."</p>
<p role="noindent">Tanya had at first been under the influence of her pity for Grisha, then of a sense of her noble action, and tears were <target target-type="page" id="page_525">525</target>standing in her eyes too; but she did not refuse, and ate her share.</p>
<p role="noindent">On catching sight of their mother they were dismayed, but, looking into her face, they saw they were not doing wrong. They burst out laughing, and, with their mouths full of tart, they began wiping their smiling lips with their hands, and smearing their radiant faces all over with tears and jam.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Mercy! Your new white frock! Tanya! Grisha!" said their mother, trying to save the frock, but with tears in her eyes, smiling a blissful, rapturous smile.</p>
<p role="noindent">The new frocks were taken off, and orders were given for the little girls to have their blouses put on, and the boys their old jackets, and the wagonette to be harnessed; with Brownie, to the bailiff’s annoyance, again in the shafts, to drive out for mushroom picking and bathing. A roar of delighted shrieks arose in the nursery, and never ceased till they had set off for the bathing-place.</p>
<p role="noindent">They gathered a whole basketful of mushrooms; even Lily found a birch mushroom. It had always happened before that Miss Hoole found them and pointed them out to her; but this time she found a big one quite of herself, and there was a general scream of delight, "Lily has found a mushroom!"</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_526">526</target>
<p role="noindent">Then they reached the river, put the horses under the birch trees, and went to the bathing-place. The coachman, Terenty, fastened the horses, who kept whisking away the flies, to a tree, and, treading down the grass, lay down in the shade of a birch and smoked his shag, while the never-ceasing shrieks of delight of the children floated across to him from the bathing-place.</p>
<p role="noindent">Though it was hard work to look after all the children and restrain their wild pranks, though it was difficult too to keep in one’s head and not mix up all the stockings, little breeches, and shoes for the different legs, and to undo and to do up again all the tapes and buttons, Darya Alexandrovna, who had always liked bathing herself, and believed it to be very good for the children, enjoyed nothing so much as bathing with all the children. To go over all those fat little legs, pulling on their stockings, to take in her arms and dip those little naked bodies, and to hear their screams of delight and alarm, to see the breathless faces with wide-open, scared, and happy eyes of all her splashing cherubs, was a great pleasure to her.</p>
<p role="noindent">When half the children had been dressed, some peasant women in holiday dress, out picking herbs, came up to the bathing-shed and stopped shyly. Marya Philimonovna called one of them and handed her a sheet and a shirt that had dropped into the water for her to dry them, and Darya Alexandrovna began to talk to the women. At first they laughed behind their hands and did not understand her questions, but soon they grew bolder and began <target target-type="page" id="page_527">527</target>to talk, winning Darya Alexandrovna’s heart at once by the genuine admiration of the children that they showed.</p>
<p role="noindent">"My, what a beauty! as white as sugar," said one, admiring Tanitchka, and shaking her head; "but thin..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, she has been ill."</p>
<p role="noindent">"And so they’ve been bathing you too," said another to the baby.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; he’s only three months old," answered Darya Alexandrovna with pride.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You don’t say so!"</p>
<p role="noindent">"And have you any children?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’ve had four; I’ve two living—a boy and a girl. I weaned her last carnival."</p>
<p role="noindent">"How old is she?" "Why, two years old."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Why did you nurse her so long?" "It’s our custom; for three fasts..."</p>
<p role="noindent">And the conversation became most interesting to Darya Alexandrovna. What sort of time did she have? What was the matter with the boy? Where was her husband? Did it often happen?</p>
<p role="noindent">Darya Alexandrovna felt disinclined to leave the peasant women, so <target target-type="page" id="page_529">529</target>interesting to her was their conversation, so completely identical were all their interests. What pleased her most of all was that she saw clearly what all the women admired more than anything was her having so many children, and such fine ones. The peasant women even made Darya Alexandrovna laugh, and offended the English governess, because she was the cause of the laughter she did not understand. One of the younger women kept staring at the Englishwoman, who was dressing after all the rest, and when she put on her third petticoat she could not refrain from the remark, "My, she keeps putting on and putting on, and she’ll never have done!" she said, and they all went off into roars.</p>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter19">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XIX</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">On the drive home, as Darya Alexandrovna, with all her children round her, their heads still wet from their bath, and a kerchief tied over her own head, was getting near the house, the coachman said, "There’s some gentleman coming: the master of Pokrovskoe, I do believe."</p>
<p role="noindent">Darya Alexandrovna peeped out in front, and was delighted when she recognized in the gray hat and gray coat the familiar figure of Levin walking to meet them. She was glad to see him at any time, but at this moment she was specially glad he should see her in all her glory.</p>
<p role="noindent">No one was better able to appreciate her grandeur than Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">Seeing her, he found himself face to face with one of the pictures of his daydream of family life.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You’re like a hen with your chickens, Darya Alexandrovna."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah, how glad I am to see you!" she said, holding out her hand to him. "Glad to see me, but you didn’t let me know. My brother’s staying with me. I got a note from Stiva that you were here."</p>
<p role="noindent">"From Stiva?" Darya Alexandrovna asked with surprise.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_530">530</target>
<p role="noindent">"Yes; he writes that you are here, and that he thinks you might allow me to be of use to you," said Levin, and as he said it he became suddenly embarrassed, and, stopping abruptly, he walked on in silence by the wagonette, snapping off the buds of the lime trees and nibbling them. He was embarrassed through a sense that Darya Alexandrovna would be annoyed by receiving from an outsider help that should by rights have come from her own husband. Darya Alexandrovna certainly did not like this little way of Stepan Arkadyevitch’s of foisting his domestic duties on others. And she was at once aware that Levin was aware of this. It was just for this fineness of perception, for this delicacy, that Darya Alexandrovna liked Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I know, of course," said Levin, "that that simply means that you would like to see me, and I’m exceedingly glad. Though I can fancy that, used to town housekeeping as you are, you must feel in the wilds here, and if there’s anything wanted, I’m altogether at your disposal."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, no!" said Dolly. "At first things were rather uncomfortable, but now we’ve settled everything capitally—thanks to my old nurse," she said, indicating Marya Philimonovna, who, seeing that they were speaking of her, smiled brightly and cordially to Levin. She knew him, and knew that he would be a good match for her young lady, and was very keen to see the matter settled.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Won’t you get in, sir, we’ll make room this side!" she said to him.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_531">531</target>
<p role="noindent">"No, I’ll walk. Children, who’d like to race the horses with me?"</p>
<p role="noindent">The children knew Levin very little, and could not remember when they had seen him, but they experienced in regard to him none of that strange feeling of shyness and hostility which children so often experience towards hypocritical, grown-up people, and for which they are so often and miserably punished.</p>
<p role="noindent">Hypocrisy in anything whatever may deceive the cleverest and most penetrating man, but the least wide-awake of children recognizes it, and is revolted by it, however ingeniously it may be disguised.</p>
<p role="noindent">Whatever faults Levin had, there was not a trace of hypocrisy in him, and so the children showed him the same friendliness that they saw in their mother’s face. On his invitation, the two elder ones at once jumped out to him and ran with him as simply as they would have done with their nurse or Miss Hoole or their mother. Lily, too, began begging to go to him, and her mother handed her to him; he sat her on his shoulder and ran along with her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Don’t be afraid, don’t be afraid, Darya Alexandrovna!" he said, smiling good-humoredly to the mother; "there’s no chance of my hurting or dropping her."</p>
<p role="noindent">And, looking at his strong, agile, assiduously careful and needlessly wary movements, the mother felt her mind at rest, and smiled gaily and approvingly as she watched him.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_532">532</target>
<p role="noindent">Here, in the country, with children, and with Darya Alexandrovna, with whom he was in sympathy, Levin was in a mood not infrequent with him, of childlike light-heartedness that she particularly liked in him. As he ran with the children, he taught them gymnastic feats, set Miss Hoole laughing with his queer English accent, and talked to Darya Alexandrovna of his pursuits in the country.</p>
<p role="noindent">After dinner, Darya Alexandrovna, sitting alone with him on the balcony, began to speak of Kitty.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You know, Kitty’s coming here, and is going to spend the summer with me."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Really," he said, flushing, and at once, to change the conversation, he said: "Then I’ll send you two cows, shall I? If you insist on a bill you shall pay me five roubles a month; but it’s really too bad of you."</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, thank you. We can manage very well now."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, well, then, I’ll have a look at your cows, and if you’ll allow me, I’ll give directions about their food. Everything depends on their food."</p>
<p role="noindent">And Levin, to turn the conversation, explained to Darya Alexandrovna the theory of cow-keeping, based on the principle that the cow is simply a machine for the transformation of food into milk, and so on.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_533">533</target>
<p role="noindent">He talked of this, and passionately longed to hear more of Kitty, and, at the same time, was afraid of hearing it. He dreaded the breaking up of the inward peace he had gained with such effort.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, but still all this has to be looked after, and who is there to look after it?" Darya Alexandrovna responded, without interest.</p>
<p role="noindent">She had by now got her household matters so satisfactorily arranged, thanks to Marya Philimonovna, that she was disinclined to make any change in them; besides, she had no faith in Levin’s knowledge of farming. General principles, as to the cow being a machine for the production of milk, she looked on with suspicion. It seemed to her that such principles could only be a hindrance in farm management. It all seemed to her a far simpler matter: all that was needed, as Marya Philimonovna had explained, was to give Brindle and Whitebreast more food and drink, and not to let the cook carry all the kitchen slops to the laundry maid’s cow. That was clear. But general propositions as to feeding on meal and on grass were doubtful and obscure. And, what was most important, she wanted to talk about Kitty.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_534">534</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter20">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XX</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">"Kitty writes to me that there’s nothing she longs for so much as quiet and solitude," Dolly said after the silence that had followed.</p>
<p role="noindent">"And how is she—better?" Levin asked in agitation.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Thank God, she’s quite well again. I never believed her lungs were affected."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, I’m very glad!" said Levin, and Dolly fancied she saw something touching, helpless, in his face as he said this and looked silently into her face.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Let me ask you, Konstantin Dmitrievitch," said Darya Alexandrovna, smiling her kindly and rather mocking smile, "why is it you are angry with Kitty?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I? I’m not angry with her," said Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, you are angry. Why was it you did not come to see us nor them when you were in Moscow?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Darya Alexandrovna," he said, blushing up to the roots of his hair, "I wonder really that with your kind heart you don’t feel this. How it is you feel no pity for me, if nothing else, when you know..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What do I know?"</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_535">535</target>
<p role="noindent">"You know I made an offer and that I was refused," said Levin, and all the tenderness he had been feeling for Kitty a minute before was replaced by a feeling of anger for the slight he had suffered.</p>
<p role="noindent">"What makes you suppose I know?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Because everybody knows it..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"That’s just where you are mistaken; I did not know it, though I had guessed it was so."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, now you know it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"All I knew was that something had happened that made her dreadfully miserable, and that she begged me never to speak of it. And if she would not tell me, she would certainly not speak of it to anyone else. But what did pass between you? Tell me."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I have told you." "When was it?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"When I was at their house the last time."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Do you know that," said Darya Alexandrovna, "I am awfully, awfully sorry for her. You suffer only from pride "</p>
<p role="noindent">"Perhaps so," said Levin, "but "</p>
<p role="noindent">She interrupted him.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But she, poor girl I am awfully, awfully sorry for her. Now I see it all."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_536">536</target>
<p role="noindent">"Well, Darya Alexandrovna, you must excuse me," he said, getting up. "Good-bye, Darya Alexandrovna, till we meet again."</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, wait a minute," she said, clutching him by the sleeve. "Wait a minute, sit down."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Please, please, don’t let us talk of this," he said, sitting down, and at the same time feeling rise up and stir within his heart a hope he had believed to be buried.</p>
<p role="noindent">"If I did not like you," she said, and tears came into her eyes; "if I did not know you, as I do know you "</p>
<p role="noindent">The feeling that had seemed dead revived more and more, rose up and took possession of Levin’s heart.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, I understand it all now," said Darya Alexandrovna. "You can’t understand it; for you men, who are free and make your own choice, it’s always clear whom you love. But a girl’s in a position of suspense, with all a woman’s or maiden’s modesty, a girl who sees you men from afar, who takes everything on trust,—a girl may have, and often has, such a feeling that she cannot tell what to say."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, if the heart does not speak "</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, the heart does speak; but just consider: you men have views about a girl, you come to the house, you make friends, you criticize, you wait to see if you have found what you love, and then, when you are sure you love her, you make an offer "</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_537">537</target>
<p role="noindent">"Well, that’s not quite it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Anyway you make an offer, when your love is ripe or when the balance has completely turned between the two you are choosing from. But a girl is not asked. She is expected to make her choice, and yet she cannot choose, she can only answer ‘yes’ or ‘no.’"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, to choose between me and Vronsky," thought Levin, and the dead thing that had come to life within him died again, and only weighed on his heart and set it aching.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Darya Alexandrovna," he said, "that’s how one chooses a new dress or some purchase or other, not love. The choice has been made, and so much the better And there can be no repeating it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah, pride, pride!" said Darya Alexandrovna, as though despising him for the baseness of this feeling in comparison with that other feeling which only women know. "At the time when you made Kitty an offer she was just in a position in which she could not answer. She was in doubt. Doubt between you and Vronsky. Him she was seeing every day, and you she had not seen for a long while. Supposing she had been older ... I, for instance, in her place could have felt no doubt. I always disliked him, and so it has turned out."</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin recalled Kitty’s answer. She had said: "No, that cannot be ". <target target-type="page" id="page_538">538</target>"Darya Alexandrovna," he said dryly, "I appreciate your confidence in me; I believe you are making a mistake. But whether I am right or wrong, that pride you so despise makes any thought of Katerina Alexandrovna out of the question for me,—you understand, utterly out of the question."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I will only say one thing more: you know that I am speaking of my sister, whom I love as I love my own children. I don’t say she cared for you, all I meant to say is that her refusal at that moment proves nothing."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I don’t know!" said Levin, jumping up. "If you only knew how you are hurting me. It’s just as if a child of yours were dead, and they were to say to you: He would have been like this and like that, and he might have lived, and how happy you would have been in him. But he’s dead, dead, dead! "</p>
<p role="noindent">"How absurd you are!" said Darya Alexandrovna, looking with mournful tenderness at Levin’s excitement. "Yes, I see it all more and more clearly," she went on musingly. "So you won’t come to see us, then, when Kitty’s here?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, I shan’t come. Of course I won’t avoid meeting Katerina Alexandrovna, but as far as I can, I will try to save her the annoyance of my presence."</p>
<p role="noindent">"You are very, very absurd," repeated Darya Alexandrovna, looking with tenderness into his face. "Very well then, let it be as <target target-type="page" id="page_539">539</target>though we had not spoken of this. What have you come for, Tanya?" she said in French to the little girl who had come in.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Where’s my spade, mamma?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I speak French, and you must too."</p>
<p role="noindent">The little girl tried to say it in French, but could not remember the French for spade; the mother prompted her, and then told her in French where to look for the spade. And this made a disagreeable impression on Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">Everything in Darya Alexandrovna’s house and children struck him now as by no means so charming as a little while before.</p>
<p role="noindent">"And what does she talk French with the children for?" he thought; "how unnatural and false it is! And the children feel it so: Learning French and unlearning sincerity," he thought to himself, unaware that Darya Alexandrovna had thought all that over twenty times already, and yet, even at the cost of some loss of sincerity, believed it necessary to teach her children French in that way.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But why are you going? Do stay a little."</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin stayed to tea; but his good-humor had vanished, and he felt ill at ease.</p>
<p role="noindent">After tea he went out into the hall to order his horses to be put in, and, when he came back, he found Darya Alexandrovna greatly disturbed, with a troubled face, and tears in her eyes. While Levin had been outside, an incident had occurred which <target target-type="page" id="page_540">540</target>had utterly shattered all the happiness she had been feeling that day, and her pride in her children. Grisha and Tanya had been fighting over a ball. Darya Alexandrovna, hearing a scream in the nursery, ran in and saw a terrible sight. Tanya was pulling Grisha’s hair, while he, with a face hideous with rage, was beating her with his fists wherever he could get at her.</p>
<p role="noindent">Something snapped in Darya Alexandrovna’s heart when she saw this. It was as if darkness had swooped down upon her life; she felt that these children of hers, that she was so proud of, were not merely most ordinary, but positively bad, ill-bred children, with coarse, brutal propensities—wicked children.</p>
<p role="noindent">She could not talk or think of anything else, and she could not speak to Levin of her misery.</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin saw she was unhappy and tried to comfort her, saying that it showed nothing bad, that all children fight; but, even as he said it, he was thinking in his heart: "No, I won’t be artificial and talk French with my children; but my children won’t be like that. All one has to do is not spoil children, not to distort their nature, and they’ll be delightful. No, my children won’t be like that."</p>
<p role="noindent">He said good-bye and drove away, and she did not try to keep him.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_541">541</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter11">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XI</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">In the middle of July the elder of the village on Levin’s sister’s estate, about fifteen miles from Pokrovskoe, came to Levin to report on how things were going there and on the hay. The chief source of income on his sister’s estate was from the riverside meadows. In former years the hay had been bought by the peasants for twenty roubles the three acres. When Levin took over the management of the estate, he thought on examining the grasslands that they were worth more, and he fixed the price at twenty-five roubles the three acres. The peasants would not give that price, and, as Levin suspected, kept off other purchasers. Then Levin had driven over himself, and arranged to have the grass cut, partly by hired labor, partly at a payment of a certain proportion of the crop. His own peasants put every hindrance they could in the way of this new arrangement, but it was carried out, and the first year the meadows had yielded a profit almost double. The previous year—which was the third year—the peasants had maintained the same opposition to the arrangement, and the hay had been cut on the same system. This year the peasants were doing all the mowing for a third of the hay crop, and the village elder had come now to announce that the hay had been cut, and that, fearing rain, they had invited the counting-house clerk over, had divided the crop in his presence, and had raked together eleven stacks as the owner’s share. From the vague answers to his question how <target target-type="page" id="page_542">542</target>much hay had been cut on the principal meadow, from the hurry of the village elder who had made the division, not asking leave, from the whole tone of the peasant, Levin perceived that there was something wrong in the division of the hay, and made up his mind to drive over himself to look into the matter.</p>
<p role="noindent">Arriving for dinner at the village, and leaving his horse at the cottage of an old friend of his, the husband of his brother’s wet- nurse, Levin went to see the old man in his bee-house, wanting to find out from him the truth about the hay. Parmenitch, a talkative, comely old man, gave Levin a very warm welcome, showed him all he was doing, told him everything about his bees and the swarms of that year; but gave vague and unwilling answers to Levin’s inquiries about the mowing. This confirmed Levin still more in his suspicions.</p>
<p role="noindent">He went to the hay fields and examined the stacks. The haystacks could not possibly contain fifty wagon-loads each, and to convict the peasants Levin ordered the wagons that had carried the hay to be brought up directly, to lift one stack, and carry it into the barn. There turned out to be only thirty-two loads in the stack. In spite of the village elder’s assertions about the compressibility of hay, and its having settled down in the stacks, and his swearing that everything had been done in the fear of God, Levin stuck to his point that the hay had been divided without his orders, and that, therefore, he would not accept that hay as fifty loads to a stack. After a prolonged <target target-type="page" id="page_543">543</target>dispute the matter was decided by the peasants taking these eleven stacks, reckoning them as fifty loads each. The arguments and the division of the haycocks lasted the whole afternoon. When the last of the hay had been divided, Levin, intrusting the superintendence of the rest to the counting-house clerk, sat down on a haycock marked off by a stake of willow, and looked admiringly at the meadow swarming with peasants.</p>
<p role="noindent">In front of him, in the bend of the river beyond the marsh, moved a bright- colored line of peasant women, and the scattered hay was being rapidly formed into gray winding rows over the pale green stubble. After the women came the men with pitchforks, and from the gray rows there were growing up broad, high, soft haycocks. To the left, carts were rumbling over the meadow that had been already cleared, and one after another the haycocks vanished, flung up in huge forkfuls, and in their place there were rising heavy cartloads of fragrant hay hanging over the horses’ hind-quarters.</p>
<p role="noindent">"What weather for haying! What hay it’ll be!" said an old man, squatting down beside Levin. "It’s tea, not hay! It’s like scattering grain to the ducks, the way they pick it up!" he added, pointing to the growing haycocks. "Since dinnertime they’ve carried a good half of it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"The last load, eh?" he shouted to a young peasant, who drove by, standing in the front of an empty cart, shaking the cord reins.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_544">544</target>
<p role="noindent">"The last, dad!" the lad shouted back, pulling in the horse, and, smiling, he looked round at a bright, rosy-checked peasant girl who sat in the cart smiling too, and drove on.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Who’s that? Your son?" asked Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">"My baby," said the old man with a tender smile. "What a fine fellow!"</p>
<p role="noindent">"The lad’s all right." "Married already?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, it’s two years last St. Philip’s day."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Any children?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Children indeed! Why, for over a year he was innocent as a babe himself, and bashful too," answered the old man. "Well, the hay! It’s as fragrant as tea!" he repeated, wishing to change the subject.</p>
<p role="noindent">Levin looked more attentively at Ivan Parmenov and his wife. They were loading a haycock onto the cart not far from him. Ivan Parmenov was standing on the cart, taking, laying in place, and stamping down the huge bundles of hay, which his pretty young wife deftly handed up to him, at first in armfuls, and then on the pitchfork. The young wife worked easily, merrily, and dexterously. The close-packed hay did not once break away off her fork. First she gathered it together, stuck the fork into it, then with a rapid, supple movement leaned the whole weight of her body on it, and at once with a bend of her back under <target target-type="page" id="page_545">545</target>the red belt she drew herself up, and arching her full bosom under the white smock, with a smart turn swung the fork in her arms, and flung the bundle of hay high onto the cart. Ivan, obviously doing his best to save her every minute of unnecessary labor, made haste, opening his arms to clutch the bundle and lay it in the cart. As she raked together what was left of the hay, the young wife shook off the bits of hay that had fallen on her neck, and straightening the red kerchief that had dropped forward over her white brow, not browned like her face by the sun, she crept under the cart to tie up the load. Ivan directed her how to fasten the cord to the cross-piece, and at something she said he laughed aloud. In the expressions of both faces was to be seen vigorous, young, freshly awakened love.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_546">546</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter12">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The load was tied on. Ivan jumped down and took the quiet, sleek horse by the bridle. The young wife flung the rake up on the load, and with a bold step, swinging her arms, she went to join the women, who were forming a ring for the haymakers’ dance. Ivan drove off to the road and fell into line with the other loaded carts. The peasant women, with their rakes on their shoulders, gay with bright flowers, and chattering with ringing, merry voices, walked behind the hay cart. One wild untrained female voice broke into a song, and sang it alone through a verse, and then the same verse was taken up and repeated by half a hundred strong healthy voices, of all sorts, coarse and fine, singing in unison.</p>
<p role="noindent">The women, all singing, began to come close to Levin, and he felt as though a storm were swooping down upon him with a thunder of merriment. The storm swooped down, enveloped him and the haycock on which he was lying, and the other haycocks, and the wagon-loads, and the whole meadow and distant fields all seemed to be shaking and singing to the measures of this wild merry song with its shouts and whistles and clapping. Levin felt envious of this health and mirthfulness; he longed to take part in the expression of this joy of life. But he could do nothing, and had to lie and look on and <target target-type="page" id="page_547">547</target>listen. When the peasants, with their singing, had vanished out of sight and hearing, a weary feeling of despondency at his own isolation, his physical inactivity, his alienation from this world, came over Levin.</p>
<p role="noindent">Some of the very peasants who had been most active in wrangling with him over the hay, some whom he had treated with contumely, and who had tried to cheat him, those very peasants had greeted him goodhumoredly, and evidently had not, were incapable of having any feeling of rancor against him, any regret, any recollection even of having tried to deceive him.</p>
<p role="noindent">All that was drowned in a sea of merry common labor. God gave the day, God gave the strength. And the day and the strength were consecrated to labor, and that labor was its own reward. For whom the labor? What would be its fruits? These were idle considerations—beside the point.</p>
<p role="noindent">Often Levin had admired this life, often he had a sense of envy of the men who led this life; but today for the first time, especially under the influence of what he had seen in the attitude of Ivan Parmenov to his young wife, the idea presented itself definitely to his mind that it was in his power to exchange the dreary, artificial, idle, and individualistic life he was leading for this laborious, pure, and socially delightful life.</p>
<p role="noindent">The old man who had been sitting beside him had long ago gone home; the people had all separated. Those who lived near had gone home, while those who came from far were gathered into a group for supper, and to spend the night in the meadow.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_548">548</target>
<p role="noindent">Levin, unobserved by the peasants, still lay on the haycock, and still looked on and listened and mused. The peasants who remained for the night in the meadow scarcely slept all the short summer night. At first there was the sound of merry talk and laughing all together over the supper, then singing again and laughter.</p>
<p role="noindent">All the long day of toil had left no trace in them but lightness of heart. Before the early dawn all was hushed. Nothing was to be heard but the night sounds of the frogs that never ceased in the marsh, and the horses snorting in the mist that rose over the meadow before the morning. Rousing himself, Levin got up from the haycock, and looking at the stars, he saw that the night was over.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Well, what am I going to do? How am I to set about it?" he said to himself, trying to express to himself all the thoughts and feelings he had passed through in that brief night. All the thoughts and feelings he had passed through fell into three separate trains of thought. One was the renunciation of his old life, of his utterly useless education. This renunciation gave him satisfaction, and was easy and simple. Another series of thoughts and mental images related to the life he longed to live now. The simplicity, the purity, the sanity of this life he felt clearly, and he was convinced he would find in it the content, the peace, and the dignity, of the lack of which he <target target-type="page" id="page_549">549</target>was so miserably conscious. But a third series of ideas turned upon the question how to effect this transition from the old life to the new. And there nothing took clear shape for him. "Have a wife? Have work and the necessity of work? Leave Pokrovskoe? Buy land? Become a member of a peasant community? Marry a peasant girl? How am I to set about it?" he asked himself again, and could not find an answer. "I haven’t slept all night, though, and I can’t think it out clearly," he said to himself. "I’ll work it out later. One thing’s certain, this night has decided my fate. All my old dreams of home life were absurd, not the real thing," he told himself. "It’s all ever so much simpler and better..."</p>
<p role="noindent">"How beautiful!" he thought, looking at the strange, as it were, mother-of- pearl shell of white fleecy cloudlets resting right over his head in the middle of the sky. "How exquisite it all is in this exquisite night! And when was there time for that cloud-shell to form? Just now I looked at the sky, and there was nothing in it—only two white streaks. Yes, and so imperceptibly too my views of life changed!"</p>
<p role="noindent">He went out of the meadow and walked along the highroad towards the village. A slight wind arose, and the sky looked gray and sullen. The gloomy moment had come that usually precedes the dawn, the full triumph of light over darkness.</p>
<p role="noindent">Shrinking from the cold, Levin walked rapidly, looking at the ground. "What’s that? Someone coming," he thought, catching the tinkle of bells, and lifting his head. Forty paces from him a carriage with four horses harnessed abreast was driving <target target-type="page" id="page_550">550</target>towards him along the grassy road on which he was walking. The shaft-horses were tilted against the shafts by the ruts, but the dexterous driver sitting on the box held the shaft over the ruts, so that the wheels ran on the smooth part of the road.</p>
<p role="noindent">This was all Levin noticed, and without wondering who it could be, he gazed absently at the coach.</p>
<p role="noindent">In the coach was an old lady dozing in one corner, and at the window, evidently only just awake, sat a young girl holding in both hands the ribbons of a white cap. With a face full of light and thought, full of a subtle, complex inner life, that was remote from Levin, she was gazing beyond him at the glow of the sunrise.</p>
<p role="noindent">At the very instant when this apparition was vanishing, the truthful eyes glanced at him. She recognized him, and her face lighted up with wondering delight.</p>
<p role="noindent">He could not be mistaken. There were no other eyes like those in the world. There was only one creature in the world that could concentrate for him all the brightness and meaning of life. It was she. It was Kitty. He understood that she was driving to Ergushovo from the railway station. And everything that had been stirring Levin during that sleepless night, all the resolutions he had made, all vanished at once. He recalled with horror his dreams of marrying a peasant girl. There only, in the carriage <target target-type="page" id="page_551">551</target>that had crossed over to the other side of the road, and was rapidly disappearing, there only could he find the solution of the riddle of his life, which had weighed so agonizingly upon him of late.</p>
<p role="noindent">She did not look out again. The sound of the carriage-springs was no longer audible, the bells could scarcely be heard. The barking of dogs showed the carriage had reached the village, and all that was left was the empty fields all round, the village in front, and he himself isolated and apart from it all, wandering lonely along the deserted highroad.</p>
<p role="noindent">He glanced at the sky, expecting to find there the cloud shell he had been admiring and taking as the symbol of the ideas and feelings of that night. There was nothing in the sky in the least like a shell. There, in the remote heights above, a mysterious change had been accomplished. There was no trace of shell, and there was stretched over fully half the sky an even cover of tiny and ever tinier cloudlets. The sky had grown blue and bright; and with the same softness, but with the same remoteness, it met his questioning gaze.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No," he said to himself, "however good that life of simplicity and toil may be, I cannot go back to it. I love her."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_552">552</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter13">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XIII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">None but those who were most intimate with Alexey Alexandrovitch knew that, while on the surface the coldest and most reasonable of men, he had one weakness quite opposed to the general trend of his character. Alexey Alexandrovitch could not hear or see a child or woman crying without being moved. The sight of tears threw him into a state of nervous agitation, and he utterly lost all power of reflection. The chief secretary of his department and his private secretary were aware of this, and used to warn women who came with petitions on no account to give way to tears, if they did not want to ruin their chances. "He will get angry, and will not listen to you," they used to say.</p>
<p role="noindent">And as a fact, in such cases the emotional disturbance set up in Alexey Alexandrovitch by the sight of tears found expression in hasty anger. "I can do nothing. Kindly leave the room!" he would commonly cry in such cases.</p>
<p role="noindent">When returning from the races Anna had informed him of her relations with Vronsky, and immediately afterwards had burst into tears, hiding her face in her hands, Alexey Alexandrovitch, for all the fury aroused in him against her, was aware at the same time of a rush of that emotional disturbance always produced in him by tears. Conscious of it, and conscious that <target target-type="page" id="page_523">523</target>any expression of his feelings at that minute would be out of keeping with the position, he tried to suppress every manifestation of life in himself, and so neither stirred nor looked at her. This was what had caused that strange expression of deathlike rigidity in his face which had so impressed Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">When they reached the house he helped her to get out of the carriage, and making an effort to master himself, took leave of her with his usual urbanity, and uttered that phrase that bound him to nothing; he said that tomorrow he would let her know his decision.</p>
<p role="noindent">His wife’s words, confirming his worst suspicions, had sent a cruel pang to the heart of Alexey Alexandrovitch. That pang was intensified by the strange feeling of physical pity for her set up by her tears. But when he was all alone in the carriage Alexey Alexandrovitch, to his surprise and delight, felt complete relief both from this pity and from the doubts and agonies of jealousy.</p>
<p role="noindent">He experienced the sensations of a man who has had a tooth out after suffering long from toothache. After a fearful agony and a sense of something huge, bigger than the head itself, being torn out of his jaw, the sufferer, hardly able to believe in his own good luck, feels all at once that what has so long poisoned his existence and enchained his attention, exists no longer, and that he can live and think again, and take interest in other things besides his tooth. This feeling Alexey Alexandrovitch was experiencing. The agony had been strange and <target target-type="page" id="page_554">554</target>terrible, but now it was over; he felt that he could live again and think of something other than his wife.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No honor, no heart, no religion; a corrupt woman. I always knew it and always saw it, though I tried to deceive myself to spare her," he said to himself. And it actually seemed to him that he always had seen it: he recalled incidents of their past life, in which he had never seen anything wrong before —now these incidents proved clearly that she had always been a corrupt woman. "I made a mistake in linking my life to hers; but there was nothing wrong in my mistake, and so I cannot be unhappy. It’s not I that am to blame," he told himself, "but she.</p>
<p role="noindent">But I have nothing to do with her. She does not exist for me..."</p>
<p role="noindent">Everything relating to her and her son, towards whom his sentiments were as much changed as towards her, ceased to interest him. The only thing that interested him now was the question of in what way he could best, with most propriety and comfort for himself, and thus with most justice, extricate himself from the mud with which she had spattered him in her fall, and then proceed along his path of active, honorable, and useful existence.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I cannot be made unhappy by the fact that a contemptible woman has committed a crime. I have only to find the best way out of the difficult position in which she has placed me. And I shall find it," he said to himself, frowning more and more. "I’m <target target-type="page" id="page_555">555</target>not the first nor the last." And to say nothing of historical instances dating from the "Fair Helen" of Menelaus, recently revived in the memory of all, a whole list of contemporary examples of husbands with unfaithful wives in the highest society rose before Alexey Alexandrovitch’s imagination. "Daryalov, Poltavsky, Prince Karibanov, Count Paskudin, Dram.... Yes, even Dram, such an honest, capable fellow ... Semyonov, Tchagin, Sigonin," Alexey Alexandrovitch remembered. "Admitting that a certain quite irrational ridicule falls to the lot of these men, yet I never saw anything but a misfortune in it, and always felt sympathy for it," Alexey Alexandrovitch said to himself, though indeed this was not the fact, and he had never felt sympathy for misfortunes of that kind, but the more frequently he had heard of instances of unfaithful wives betraying their husbands, the more highly he had thought of himself. "It is a misfortune which may befall anyone. And this misfortune has befallen me. The only thing to be done is to make the best of the position."</p>
<p role="noindent">And he began passing in review the methods of proceeding of men who had been in the same position that he was in.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Daryalov fought a duel "</p>
<p role="noindent">The duel had particularly fascinated the thoughts of Alexey Alexandrovitch in his youth, just because he was physically a coward, and was himself well aware of the fact. Alexey Alexandrovitch could not without horror contemplate the idea of a pistol aimed at himself, and had never made use of any <target target-type="page" id="page_556">556</target>weapon in his life. This horror had in his youth set him pondering on dueling, and picturing himself in a position in which he would have to expose his life to danger. Having attained success and an established position in the world, he had long ago forgotten this feeling; but the habitual bent of feeling reasserted itself, and dread of his own cowardice proved even now so strong that Alexey Alexandrovitch spent a long while thinking over the question of dueling in all its aspects, and hugging the idea of a duel, though he was fully aware beforehand that he would never under any circumstances fight one.</p>
<p role="noindent">"There’s no doubt our society is still so barbarous (it’s not the same in England) that very many"—and among these were those whose opinion Alexey Alexandrovitch particularly valued— "look favorably on the duel; but what result is attained by it? Suppose I call him out," Alexey Alexandrovitch went on to himself, and vividly picturing the night he would spend after the challenge, and the pistol aimed at him, he shuddered, and knew that he never would do it—"suppose I call him out. Suppose I am taught," he went on musing, "to shoot; I press the trigger," he said to himself, closing his eyes, "and it turns out I have killed him," Alexey Alexandrovitch said to himself, and he shook his head as though to dispel such silly ideas. "What sense is there in murdering a man in order to define one’s relation to a guilty wife and son? I should still just as much have to decide what I ought to do with her. But what is more probable and what <target target-type="page" id="page_557">557</target>would doubtless occur—I should be killed or wounded. I, the innocent person, should be the victim—killed or wounded. It’s even more senseless. But apart from that, a challenge to fight would be an act hardly honest on my side. Don’t I know perfectly well that my friends would never allow me to fight a duel—would never allow the life of a statesman, needed by Russia, to be exposed to danger? Knowing perfectly well beforehand that the matter would never come to real danger, it would amount to my simply trying to gain a certain sham reputation by such a challenge. That would be dishonest, that would be false, that would be deceiving myself and others. A duel is quite irrational, and no one expects it of me. My aim is simply to safeguard my reputation, which is essential for the uninterrupted pursuit of my public duties." Official duties, which had always been of great consequence in Alexey Alexandrovitch’s eyes, seemed of special importance to his mind at this moment. Considering and rejecting the duel, Alexey Alexandrovitch turned to divorce—another solution selected by several of the husbands he remembered. Passing in mental review all the instances he knew of divorces (there were plenty of them in the very highest society with which he was very familiar), Alexey Alexandrovitch could not find a single example in which the object of divorce was that which he had in view. In all these instances the husband had practically ceded or sold his unfaithful wife, and the very party which, being in fault, had not the right to contract a fresh marriage, had formed counterfeit, pseudo-matrimonial ties with a self-styled husband. In his own <target target-type="page" id="page_558">558</target>case, Alexey Alexandrovitch saw that a legal divorce, that is to say, one in which only the guilty wife would be repudiated, was impossible of attainment. He saw that the complex conditions of the life they led made the coarse proofs of his wife’s guilt, required by the law, out of the question; he saw that a certain refinement in that life would not admit of such proofs being brought forward, even if he had them, and that to bring forward such proofs would damage him in the public estimation more than it would her.</p>
<p role="noindent">An attempt at divorce could lead to nothing but a public scandal, which would be a perfect godsend to his enemies for calumny and attacks on his high position in society. His chief object, to define the position with the least amount of disturbance possible, would not be attained by divorce either. Moreover, in the event of divorce, or even of an attempt to obtain a divorce, it was obvious that the wife broke off all relations with the husband and threw in her lot with the lover. And in spite of the complete, as he supposed, contempt and indifference he now felt for his wife, at the bottom of his heart Alexey Alexandrovitch still had one feeling left in regard to her—a disinclination to see her free to throw in her lot with Vronsky, so that her crime would be to her advantage. The mere notion of this so exasperated Alexey Alexandrovitch, that directly it rose to his mind he groaned with inward agony, and got up and changed his place in the <target target-type="page" id="page_559">559</target>carriage, and for a long while after, he sat with scowling brows, wrapping his numbed and bony legs in the fleecy rug.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Apart from formal divorce, One might still do like Karibanov, Paskudin, and that good fellow Dram—that is, separate from one’s wife," he went on thinking, when he had regained his composure. But this step too presented the same drawback of public scandal as a divorce, and what was more, a separation, quite as much as a regular divorce, flung his wife into the arms of Vronsky. "No, it’s out of the question, out of the question!" he said again, twisting his rug about him again. "I cannot be unhappy, but neither she nor he ought to be happy."</p>
<p role="noindent">The feeling of jealousy, which had tortured him during the period of uncertainty, had passed away at the instant when the tooth had been with agony extracted by his wife’s words. But that feeling had been replaced by another, the desire, not merely that she should not be triumphant, but that she should get due punishment for her crime. He did not acknowledge this feeling, but at the bottom of his heart he longed for her to suffer for having destroyed his peace of mind—his honor. And going once again over the conditions inseparable from a duel, a divorce, a separation, and once again rejecting them, Alexey Alexandrovitch felt convinced that there was only one solution, —to keep her with him, concealing what had happened from the world, and using every measure in his power to break off the intrigue, and still more— though this he did not admit to himself—to punish her. "I must inform her of my conclusion, that thinking <target target-type="page" id="page_560">560</target>over the terrible position in which she has placed her family, all other solutions will be worse for both sides than an external status quo, and that such I agree to retain, on the strict condition of obedience on her part to my wishes, that is to say, cessation of all intercourse with her lover." When this decision had been finally adopted, another weighty consideration occurred to Alexey Alexandrovitch in support of it. "By such a course only shall I be acting in accordance with the dictates of religion," he told himself. "In adopting this course, I am not casting off a guilty wife, but giving her a chance of amendment; and, indeed, difficult as the task will be to me, I shall devote part of my energies to her reformation and salvation."</p>
<p role="noindent">Though Alexey Alexandrovitch was perfectly aware that he could not exert any moral influence over his wife, that such an attempt at reformation could lead to nothing but falsity; though in passing through these difficult moments he had not once thought of seeking guidance in religion, yet now, when his conclusion corresponded, as it seemed to him, with the requirements of religion, this religious sanction to his decision gave him complete satisfaction, and to some extent restored his peace of mind. He was pleased to think that, even in such an important crisis in life, no one would be able to say that he had not acted in accordance with the principles of that religion whose banner he had always held aloft amid the general <target target-type="page" id="page_561">561</target>coolness and indifference. As he pondered over subsequent developments, Alexey Alexandrovitch did not see, indeed, why his relations with his wife should not remain practically the same as before. No doubt, she could never regain his esteem, but there was not, and there could not be, any sort of reason that his existence should be troubled, and that he should suffer because she was a bad and faithless wife. "Yes, time will pass; time, which arranges all things, and the old relations will be reestablished," Alexey Alexandrovitch told himself; "so far reestablished, that is, that I shall not be sensible of a break in the continuity of my life. She is bound to be unhappy, but I am not to blame, and so I cannot be unhappy."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_521">562</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter14">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XIV</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">As he neared Petersburg, Alexey Alexandrovitch not only adhered entirely to his decision, but was even composing in his head the letter he would write to his wife. Going into the porter’s room, Alexey Alexandrovitch glanced at the letters and papers brought from his office, and directed that they should be brought to him in his study.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The horses can be taken out and I will see no one," he said in answer to the porter, with a certain pleasure, indicative of his agreeable frame of mind, emphasizing the words, "see no one."</p>
<p role="noindent">In his study Alexey Alexandrovitch walked up and down twice, and stopped at an immense writing-table, on which six candles had already been lighted by the valet who had preceded him. He cracked his knuckles and sat down, sorting out his writing appurtenances. Putting his elbows on the table, he bent his head on one side, thought a minute, and began to write, without pausing for a second. He wrote without using any form of address to her, and wrote in French, making use of the plural "vous," which has not the same note of coldness as the corresponding Russian form.</p>
<p role="noindent">"At our last conversation, I notified you of my intention to communicate to you my decision in regard to the subject of that conversation. Having carefully considered everything, I am <target target-type="page" id="page_563">563</target>writing now with the object of fulfilling that promise. My decision is as follows. Whatever your conduct may have been, I do not consider myself justified in breaking the ties in which we are bound by a Higher Power. The family cannot be broken up by a whim, a caprice, or even by the sin of one of the partners in the marriage, and our life must go on as it has done in the past.</p>
<p role="noindent">This is essential for me, for you, and for our son. I am fully persuaded that you have repented and do repent of what has called forth the present letter, and that you will cooperate with me in eradicating the cause of our estrangement, and forgetting the past. In the contrary event, you can conjecture what awaits you and your son. All this I hope to discuss more in detail in a personal interview. As the season is drawing to a close, I would beg you to return to Petersburg as quickly as possible, not later than Tuesday. All necessary preparations shall be made for your arrival here. I beg you to note that I attach particular significance to compliance with this request.</p>
<p role="noindent">A. Karenin "P.S.—I enclose the money which may be needed for your expenses."</p>
<p role="noindent">He read the letter through and felt pleased with it, and especially that he had remembered to enclose money: there was not a harsh word, not a reproach in it, nor was there undue indulgence. Most of all, it was a golden bridge for return. Folding the letter and smoothing it with a massive ivory knife, and putting it in an envelope with the money, he rang the bell <target target-type="page" id="page_564">564</target>with the gratification it always afforded him to use the well arranged appointments of his writing- table.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Give this to the courier to be delivered to Anna Arkadyevna tomorrow at the summer villa," he said, getting up.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Certainly, your excellency; tea to be served in the study?"</p>
<p role="noindent">Alexey Alexandrovitch ordered tea to be brought to the study, and playing with the massive paper-knife, he moved to his easy chair, near which there had been placed ready for him a lamp and the French work on Egyptian hieroglyphics that he had begun. Over the easy chair there hung in a gold frame an oval portrait of Anna, a fine painting by a celebrated artist. Alexey Alexandrovitch glanced at it. The unfathomable eyes gazed ironically and insolently at him. Insufferably insolent and challenging was the effect in Alexey Alexandrovitch’s eyes of the black lace about the head, admirably touched in by the painter, the black hair and handsome white hand with one finger lifted, covered with rings. After looking at the portrait for a minute, Alexey Alexandrovitch shuddered so that his lips quivered and he uttered the sound "brrr," and turned away. He made haste to sit down in his easy chair and opened the book. He tried to read, but he could not revive the very vivid interest he had felt before in Egyptian hieroglyphics. He looked at the book and thought of something else. He thought not of his wife, but of a complication that had arisen in <target target-type="page" id="page_565">565</target>his official life, which at the time constituted the chief interest of it. He felt that he had penetrated more deeply than ever before into this intricate affair, and that he had originated a leading idea—he could say it without self-flattery—calculated to clear up the whole business, to strengthen him in his official career, to discomfit his enemies, and thereby to be of the greatest benefit to the government. Directly the servant had set the tea and left the room, Alexey Alexandrovitch got up and went to the writing- table. Moving into the middle of the table a portfolio of papers, with a scarcely perceptible smile of self-satisfaction, he took a pencil from a rack and plunged into the perusal of a complex report relating to the present complication. The complication was of this nature: Alexey Alexandrovitch’s characteristic quality as a politician, that special individual qualification that every rising functionary possesses, the qualification that with his unflagging ambition, his reserve, his honesty, and with his self- confidence had made his career, was his contempt for red tape, his cutting down of correspondence, his direct contact, wherever possible, with the living fact, and his economy. It happened that the famous Commission of the 2nd of June had set on foot an inquiry into the irrigation of lands in the Zaraisky province, which fell under Alexey Alexandrovitch’s department, and was a glaring example of fruitless expenditure and paper reforms. Alexey Alexandrovitch was aware of the truth of this. The irrigation of these lands in the Zaraisky province had been initiated by the predecessor of Alexey Alexandrovitch’s predecessor. And vast sums of money had actually been spent and were still being spent <target target-type="page" id="page_566">566</target>on this business, and utterly unproductively, and the whole business could obviously lead to nothing whatever. Alexey Alexandrovitch had perceived this at once on entering office, and would have liked to lay hands on the Board of Irrigation. But at first, when he did not yet feel secure in his position, he knew it would affect too many interests, and would be injudicious. Later on he had been engrossed in other questions, and had simply forgotten the Board of Irrigation. It went of itself, like all such boards, by the mere force of inertia. (Many people gained their livelihood by the Board of Irrigation, especially one highly conscientious and musical family: all the daughters played on stringed instruments, and Alexey Alexandrovitch knew the family and had stood godfather to one of the elder daughters.) The raising of this question by a hostile department was in Alexey Alexandrovitch’s opinion a dishonorable proceeding, seeing that in every department there were things similar and worse, which no one inquired into, for well-known reasons of official etiquette. However, now that the glove had been thrown down to him, he had boldly picked it up and demanded the appointment of a special commission to investigate and verify the working of the Board of Irrigation of the lands in the Zaraisky province. But in compensation he gave no quarter to the enemy either. He demanded the appointment of another special commission to inquire into the question of <target target-type="page" id="page_567">567</target>the Native Tribes Organization Committee. The question of the Native Tribes had been brought up incidentally in the Commission of the 2nd of June, and had been pressed forward actively by Alexey Alexandrovitch as one admitting of no delay on account of the deplorable condition of the native tribes. In the commission this question had been a ground of contention between several departments. The department hostile to Alexey Alexandrovitch proved that the condition of the native tribes was exceedingly flourishing, that the proposed reconstruction might be the ruin of their prosperity, and that if there were anything wrong, it arose mainly from the failure on the part of Alexey Alexandrovitch’s department to carry out the measures prescribed by law. Now Alexey Alexandrovitch intended to demand: First, that a new commission should be formed which should be empowered to investigate the condition of the native tribes on the spot; secondly, if it should appear that the condition of the native tribes actually was such as it appeared to be from the official documents in the hands of the committee, that another new scientific commission should be appointed to investigate the deplorable condition of the native tribes from the—(1) political, (2) administrative, (3) economic, (4) ethnographical, (5) material, and (6) religious points of view; thirdly, that evidence should be required from the rival department of the measures that had been taken during the last ten years by that department for averting the disastrous conditions in which the native tribes were now placed; and <target target-type="page" id="page_568">568</target>appeared from the evidence before the committee, from No. 17,015 and 18,038, from December 5, 1863, and June 7, 1864, acted in direct contravention of the intent of the law T... Act 18, and the note to Act 36. A flash of eagerness suffused the face of Alexey Alexandrovitch as he rapidly wrote out a synopsis of these ideas for his own benefit. Having filled a sheet of paper, he got up, rang, and sent a note to the chief secretary of his department to look up certain necessary facts for him. Getting up and walking about the room, he glanced again at the portrait, frowned, and smiled contemptuously. After reading a little more of the book on Egyptian hieroglyphics, and renewing his interest in it, Alexey Alexandrovitch went to bed at eleven o’clock, and recollecting as he lay in bed the incident with his wife, he saw it now in by no means such a gloomy light.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_569">569</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter15">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XV</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">Though Anna had obstinately and with exasperation contradicted Vronsky when he told her their position was impossible, at the bottom of her heart she regarded her own position as false and dishonorable, and she longed with her whole soul to change it. On the way home from the races she had told her husband the truth in a moment of excitement, and in spite of the agony she had suffered in doing so, she was glad of it. After her husband had left her, she told herself that she was glad, that now everything was made clear, and at least there would be no more lying and deception. It seemed to her beyond doubt that her position was now made clear forever. It might be bad, this new position, but it would be clear; there would be no indefiniteness or falsehood about it. The pain she had caused herself and her husband in uttering those words would be rewarded now by everything being made clear, she thought. That evening she saw Vronsky, but she did not tell him of what had passed between her and her husband, though, to make the position definite, it was necessary to tell him</p>
<p role="noindent">When she woke up next morning the first thing that rose to her mind was what she had said to her husband, and those words seemed to her so awful that she could not conceive now how she could have brought herself to utter those strange, coarse words, and could not imagine what would come of it. But the words were spoken, and Alexey Alexandrovitch had gone away <target target-type="page" id="page_570">570</target>without saying anything. "I saw Vronsky and did not tell him. At the very instant he was going away I would have turned him back and told him, but I changed my mind, because it was strange that I had not told him the first minute. Why was it I wanted to tell him and did not tell him?" And in answer to this question a burning blush of shame spread over her face. She knew what had kept her from it, she knew that she had been ashamed. Her position, which had seemed to her simplified the night before, suddenly struck her now as not only not simple, but as absolutely hopeless. She felt terrified at the disgrace, of which she had not ever thought before. Directly she thought of what her husband would do, the most terrible ideas came to her mind. She had a vision of being turned out of the house, of her shame being proclaimed to all the world. She asked herself where she should go when she was turned out of the house, and she could not find an answer.</p>
<p role="noindent">When she thought of Vronsky, it seemed to her that he did not love her, that he was already beginning to be tired of her, that she could not offer herself to him, and she felt bitter against him for it. It seemed to her that the words that she had spoken to her husband, and had continually repeated in her imagination, she had said to everyone, and everyone had heard them. She could not bring herself to look those of her own household in the face. She could not bring herself to call her maid, and still less go downstairs and see her son and his governess</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_571">571</target>
<p role="noindent">The maid, who had been listening at her door for a long while, came into her room of her own accord. Anna glanced inquiringly into her face, and blushed with a scared look. The maid begged her pardon for coming in, saying that she had fancied the bell rang. She brought her clothes and a note. The note was from Betsy. Betsy reminded her that Liza Merkalova and Baroness Shtoltz were coming to play croquet with her that morning with their adorers, Kaluzhsky and old Stremov. "Come, if only as a study in morals. I shall expect you," she finished.</p>
<p role="noindent">Anna read the note and heaved a deep sigh.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Nothing, I need nothing," she said to Annushka, who was rearranging the bottles and brushes on the dressing table. "You can go. I’ll dress at once and come down. I need nothing."</p>
<p role="noindent">Annushka went out, but Anna did not begin dressing, and sat in the same position, her head and hands hanging listlessly, and every now and then she shivered all over, seemed as though she would make some gesture, utter some word, and sank back into lifelessness again. She repeated continually, "My God! my God!" But neither "God" nor "my" had any meaning to her. The idea of seeking help in her difficulty in religion was as remote from her as seeking help from Alexey Alexandrovitch himself, although she had never had doubts of the faith in which she had been brought up. She knew that the support of religion was possible only upon condition of renouncing what made up for her the whole meaning of life. She was not simply miserable, she began to feel alarm at the new spiritual condition, never experienced <target target-type="page" id="page_569">569</target>before, in which she found herself. She felt as though everything were beginning to be double in her soul, just as objects sometimes appear double to over-tired eyes. She hardly knew at times what it was she feared, and what she hoped for. Whether she feared or desired what had happened, or what was going to happen, and exactly what she longed for, she could not have said.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah, what am I doing!" she said to herself, feeling a sudden thrill of pain in both sides of her head. When she came to herself, she saw that she was holding her hair in both hands, each side of her temples, and pulling it. She jumped up, and began walking about.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The coffee is ready, and mademoiselle and Seryozha are waiting," said Annushka, coming back again and finding Anna in the same position.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Seryozha? What about Seryozha?" Anna asked, with sudden eagerness, recollecting her son’s existence for the first time that morning.</p>
<p role="noindent">"He’s been naughty, I think," answered Annushka with a smile. "In what way?</p>
<p role="noindent">"Some peaches were lying on the table in the corner room. I think he slipped in and ate one of them on the sly."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_573">573</target>
<p role="noindent">The recollection of her son suddenly roused Anna from the helpless condition in which she found herself. She recalled the partly sincere, though greatly exaggerated, rôle of the mother living for her child, which she had taken up of late years, and she felt with joy that in the plight in which she found herself she had a support, quite apart from her relation to her husband or to Vronsky. This support was her son. In whatever position she might be placed, she could not lose her son. Her husband might put her to shame and turn her out, Vronsky might grow cold to her and go on living his own life apart (she thought of him again with bitterness and reproach); she could not leave her son. She had an aim in life. And she must act; act to secure this relation to her son, so that he might not be taken from her. Quickly indeed, as quickly as possible, she must take action before he was taken from her. She must take her son and go away. Here was the one thing she had to do now. She needed consolation. She must be calm, and get out of this insufferable position. The thought of immediate action binding her to her son, of going away somewhere with him, gave her this consolation.</p>
<p role="noindent">She dressed quickly, went downstairs, and with resolute steps walked into the drawing room, where she found, as usual, waiting for her, the coffee, Seryozha, and his governess. Seryozha, all in white, with his back and head bent, was standing at a table under a looking-glass, and with an expression of intense concentration which she knew well, and in <target target-type="page" id="page_574">574</target>which he resembled his father, he was doing something to the flowers he carried.</p>
<p role="noindent">The governess had a particularly severe expression. Seryozha screamed shrilly, as he often did, "Ah, mamma!" and stopped, hesitating whether to go to greet his mother and put down the flowers, or to finish making the wreath and go with the flowers. The governess, after saying good-morning, began a long and detailed account of Seryozha’s naughtiness, but Anna did not hear her; she was considering whether she would take her with her or not. "No, I won’t take her," she decided. "I’ll go alone with my child." "Yes, it’s very wrong," said Anna, and taking her son by the shoulder she looked at him, not severely, but with a timid glance that bewildered and delighted the boy, and she kissed him. "Leave him to me," she said to the astonished governess, and not letting go of her son, she sat down at the table, where coffee was set ready for her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Mamma! I ... I ... didn’t..." he said, trying to make out from her expression what was in store for him in regard to the peaches.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Seryozha," she said, as soon as the governess had left the room, "that was wrong, but you’ll never do it again, will you?... You love me?"</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_575">575</target>
<p role="noindent">She felt that the tears were coming into her eyes. "Can I help loving him?" she said to herself, looking deeply into his scared and at the same time delighted eyes. "And can he ever join his father in punishing me? Is it possible he will not feel for me?" Tears were already flowing down her face, and to hide them she got up abruptly and almost ran out on to the terrace.</p>
<p role="noindent">After the thunder showers of the last few days, cold, bright weather had set in. The air was cold in the bright sun that filtered through the freshly washed leaves.</p>
<p role="noindent">She shivered, both from the cold and from the inward horror which had clutched her with fresh force in the open air.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Run along, run along to Mariette," she said to Seryozha, who had followed her out, and she began walking up and down on the straw matting of the terrace. "Can it be that they won’t forgive me, won’t understand how it all couldn’t be helped?" she said to herself.</p>
<p role="noindent">Standing still, and looking at the tops of the aspen trees waving in the wind, with their freshly washed, brightly shining leaves in the cold sunshine, she knew that they would not forgive her, that everyone and everything would be merciless to her now as was that sky, that green. And again she felt that everything was split in two in her soul. "I mustn’t, mustn’t think," she said to herself. "I must get ready. To go where? When? Whom to take with me? Yes, to Moscow by the evening train. Annushka and Seryozha, and only the most necessary things. But first I must write to <target target-type="page" id="page_576">576</target>them both." She went quickly indoors into her boudoir, sat down at the table, and wrote to her husband:</p>
<p role="noindent">—"After what has happened, I cannot remain any longer in your house. I am going away, and taking my son with me. I don’t know the law, and so I don’t know with which of the parents the son should remain; but I take him with me because I cannot live without him. Be generous, leave him to me."</p>
<p role="noindent">Up to this point she wrote rapidly and naturally, but the appeal to his generosity, a quality she did not recognize in him, and the necessity of winding up the letter with something touching, pulled her up. "Of my fault and my remorse I cannot speak, because..."</p>
<p role="noindent">She stopped again, finding no connection in her ideas. "No," she said to herself, "there’s no need of anything," and tearing up the letter, she wrote it again, leaving out the allusion to generosity, and sealed it up</p>
<p role="noindent">Another letter had to be written to Vronsky. "I have told my husband," she wrote, and she sat a long while unable to write more. It was so coarse, so unfeminine. "And what more am I to write to him?" she said to herself. Again a flush of shame spread over her face; she recalled his composure, and a feeling of anger against him impelled her to tear the sheet with the phrase she had written into tiny bits. "No need of anything," she said to herself, and closing her blotting <target target-type="page" id="page_577">577</target>case she went upstairs, told the governess and the servants that she was going that day to Moscow, and at once set to work to pack up her things.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_578">578</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter16">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XVI</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">All the rooms of the summer villa were full of porters, gardeners, and footmen going to and fro carrying out things. Cupboards and chests were open; twice they had sent to the shop for cord; pieces of newspaper were tossing about on the floor. Two trunks, some bags and strapped-up rugs, had been carried down into the hall. The carriage and two hired cabs were waiting at the steps. Anna, forgetting her inward agitation in the work of packing, was standing at a table in her boudoir, packing her traveling bag, when Annushka called her attention to the rattle of some carriage driving up. Anna looked out of the window and saw Alexey Alexandrovitch’s courier on the steps, ringing at the front door bell.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Run and find out what it is," she said, and with a calm sense of being prepared for anything, she sat down in a low chair, folding her hands on her knees. A footman brought in a thick packet directed in Alexey Alexandrovitch’s hand.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The courier has orders to wait for an answer," he said. "Very well," she said, and as soon as he had left the room she tore open the letter with trembling fingers. A roll of unfolded notes done up in a wrapper fell out of it. She disengaged the letter and began reading it at the end. "Preparations shall be made for your arrival here ... I attach particular significance to compliance..." she read. She ran on, then back, read it all 579 through, and once more read the letter all <target target-type="page" id="page_579">579</target>through again from the beginning. When she had finished, she felt that she was cold all over, and that a fearful calamity, such as she had not expected, had burst upon her.</p>
<p role="noindent">In the morning she had regretted that she had spoken to her husband, and wished for nothing so much as that those words could be unspoken. And here this letter regarded them as unspoken, and gave her what she had wanted. But now this letter seemed to her more awful than anything she had been able to conceive.</p>
<p role="noindent">"He’s right!" she said; "of course, he’s always right; he’s a Christian, he’s generous! Yes, vile, base creature! And no one understands it except me, and no one ever will; and I can’t explain it. They say he’s so religious, so high- principled, so upright, so clever; but they don’t see what I’ve seen. They don’t know how he has crushed my life for eight years, crushed everything that was living in me—he has not once even thought that I’m a live woman who must have love. They don’t know how at every step he’s humiliated me, and been just as pleased with himself. Haven’t I striven, striven with all my strength, to find something to give meaning to my life? Haven’t I struggled to love him, to love my son when I could not love my husband? But the time came when I knew that I couldn’t cheat myself any longer, that <target target-type="page" id="page_580">580</target>I was alive, that I was not to blame, that God has made me so that I must love and live. And now what does he do? If he’d killed me, if he’d killed him, I could have borne anything, I could have forgiven anything; but, no, he How was it I didn’t guess what he would do? He’s doing just what’s characteristic of his mean character. He’ll keep himself in the right, while me, in my ruin, he’ll drive still lower to worse ruin yet "</p>
<p role="noindent">She recalled the words from the letter. "You can conjecture what awaits you and your son...." "That’s a threat to take away my child, and most likely by their stupid law he can. But I know very well why he says it. He doesn’t believe even in my love for my child, or he despises it (just as he always used to ridicule it). He despises that feeling in me, but he knows that I won’t abandon my child, that I can’t abandon my child, that there could be no life for me without my child, even with him whom I love; but that if I abandoned my child and ran away from him, I should be acting like the most infamous, basest of women. He knows that, and knows that I am incapable of doing that."</p>
<p role="noindent">She recalled another sentence in the letter. "Our life must go on as it has done in the past...." "That life was miserable enough in the old days; it has been awful of late. What will it be now? And he knows all that; he knows that I can’t repent that I breathe, that I love; he knows that it can lead to nothing but lying and <target target-type="page" id="page_578">581</target>deceit; but he wants to go on torturing me. I know him; I know that he’s at home and is happy in deceit, like a fish swimming in the water. No, I won’t give him that happiness. I’ll break through the spiderweb of lies in which he wants to catch me, come what may. Anything’s better than lying and deceit.</p>
<p role="noindent">"But how? My God! my God! Was ever a woman so miserable as I am? "</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; I will break through it, I will break through it!" she cried, jumping up and keeping back her tears. And she went to the writing table to write him another letter. But at the bottom of her heart she felt that she was not strong enough to break through anything, that she was not strong enough to get out of her old position, however false and dishonorable it might be.</p>
<p role="noindent">She sat down at the writing table, but instead of writing she clasped her hands on the table, and, laying her head on them, burst into tears, with sobs and heaving breast like a child crying. She was weeping that her dream of her position being made clear and definite had been annihilated forever. She knew beforehand that everything would go on in the old way, and far worse, indeed, than in the old way. She felt that the position in the world that she enjoyed, and that had seemed to her of so little consequence in the morning, that this position was precious to her, that she would not have the strength to exchange it for the shameful position of a woman who has <target target-type="page" id="page_582">572</target>abandoned husband and child to join her lover; that however much she might struggle, she could not be stronger than herself. She would never know freedom in love, but would remain forever a guilty wife, with the menace of detection hanging over her at every instant; deceiving her husband for the sake of a shameful connection with a man living apart and away from her, whose life she could never share. She knew that this was how it would be, and at the same time it was so awful that she could not even conceive what it would end in. And she cried without restraint, as children cry when they are punished.</p>
<p role="noindent">The sound of the footman’s steps forced her to rouse herself, and, hiding her face from him, she pretended to be writing.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The courier asks if there’s an answer," the footman announced. </p>
<p role="noindent">"An answer? Yes," said Anna. "Let him wait. I’ll ring."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What can I write?" she thought. "What can I decide upon alone? What do I know? What do I want? What is there I care for?" Again she felt that her soul was beginning to be split in two. She was terrified again at this feeling, and clutched at the first pretext for doing something which might divert her thoughts from herself. "I ought to see Alexey" (so she called Vronsky in her thoughts); "no one but he can tell me what I ought to do. I’ll go to Betsy’s, perhaps I shall see him there," she said to herself, completely forgetting that when she had told him the day before that she was not going to Princess Tverskaya’s, he had said that in that case he should not go either. She went up to the table, wrote to her husband, "I have <target target-type="page" id="page_583">583</target>received your letter.—A."; and, ringing the bell, gave it to the footman.</p>
<p role="noindent">"We are not going," she said to Annushka, as she came in. "Not going at all?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; don’t unpack till tomorrow, and let the carriage wait. I’m going to the princess’s."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Which dress am I to get ready?"</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_584">584</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter17">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XVII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">The croquet party to which the Princess Tverskaya had invited Anna was to consist of two ladies and their adorers. These two ladies were the chief representatives of a select new Petersburg circle, nicknamed, in imitation of some imitation, les sept merveilles du monde. These ladies belonged to a circle which, though of the highest society, was utterly hostile to that in which Anna moved. Moreover, Stremov, one of the most influential people in Petersburg, and the elderly admirer of Liza Merkalova, was Alexey Alexandrovitch’s enemy in the political world. From all these considerations Anna had not meant to go, and the hints in Princess Tverskaya’s note referred to her refusal. But now Anna was eager to go, in the hope of seeing Vronsky.</p>
<p role="noindent">Anna arrived at Princess Tverskaya’s earlier than the other guests.</p>
<p role="noindent">At the same moment as she entered, Vronsky’s footman, with side- whiskers combed out like a Kammerjunker, went in too. He stopped at the door, and, taking off his cap, let her pass. Anna recognized him, and only then recalled that Vronsky had told her the day before that he would not come. Most likely he was sending a note to say so.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_585">585</target>
<p role="noindent">As she took off her outer garment in the hall, she heard the footman, pronouncing his "r’s" even like a Kammerjunker, say, "From the count for the princess," and hand the note.</p>
<p role="noindent">She longed to question him as to where his master was. She longed to turn back and send him a letter to come and see her, or to go herself to see him. But neither the first nor the second nor the third course was possible. Already she heard bells ringing to announce her arrival ahead of her, and Princess Tverskaya’s footman was standing at the open door waiting for her to go forward into the inner rooms.</p>
<p role="noindent">"The princess is in the garden; they will inform her immediately. Would you be pleased to walk into the garden?" announced another footman in another room</p>
<p role="noindent">The position of uncertainty, of indecision, was still the same as at home— worse, in fact, since it was impossible to take any step, impossible to see Vronsky, and she had to remain here among outsiders, in company so uncongenial to her present mood. But she was wearing a dress that she knew suited her. She was not alone; all around was that luxurious setting of idleness that she was used to, and she felt less wretched than at home. She was not forced to think what she was to do. Everything would be done of itself. On meeting Betsy coming towards her in a white gown that struck her by its elegance, Anna smiled at her just as she always did. Princess Tverskaya was <target target-type="page" id="page_586">586</target>walking with Tushkevitch and a young lady, a relation, who, to the great joy of her parents in the provinces, was spending the summer with the fashionable princess.</p>
<p role="noindent">There was probably something unusual about Anna, for Betsy noticed it at once.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I slept badly," answered Anna, looking intently at the footman who came to meet them, and, as she supposed, brought Vronsky’s note</p>
<p role="noindent">"How glad I am you’ve come!" said Betsy. "I’m tired, and was just longing to have some tea before they come. You might go"—she turned to Tushkevitch —"with Masha, and try the croquet ground over there where they’ve been cutting it. We shall have time to talk a little over tea; we’ll have a cozy chat, eh?" she said in English to Anna, with a smile, pressing the hand with which she held a parasol.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, especially as I can’t stay very long with you. I’m forced to go on to old Madame Vrede. I’ve been promising to go for a century," said Anna, to whom lying, alien as it was to her nature, had become not merely simple and natural in society, but a positive source of satisfaction. Why she said this, which she had not thought of a second before, she could not have explained. She had said it simply from the reflection that as Vronsky would not be here, she had better secure her own freedom, and try to see him somehow. But why she had spoken of old Madame <target target-type="page" id="page_587">587</target>Vrede, whom she had to go and see, as she had to see many other people, she could not have explained; and yet, as it afterwards turned out, had she contrived the most cunning devices to meet Vronsky, she could have thought of nothing better.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No. I’m not going to let you go for anything," answered Betsy, looking intently into Anna’s face. "Really, if I were not fond of you, I should feel offended. One would think you were afraid my society would compromise you. Tea in the little dining room, please," she said, half closing her eyes, as she always did when addressing the footman.</p>
<p role="noindent">Taking the note from him, she read it.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Alexey’s playing us false," she said in French; "he writes that he can’t come," she added in a tone as simple and natural as though it could never enter her head that Vronsky could mean anything more to Anna than a game of croquet. Anna knew that Betsy knew everything, but, hearing how she spoke of Vronsky before her, she almost felt persuaded for a minute that she knew nothing.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah!" said Anna indifferently, as though not greatly interested in the matter, and she went on smiling: "How can you or your friends compromise anyone?"</p>
<p role="noindent">This playing with words, this hiding of a secret, had a great fascination for Anna, as, indeed, it has for all women. And it was <target target-type="page" id="page_588">588</target>not the necessity of concealment, not the aim with which the concealment was contrived, but the process of concealment itself which attracted her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I can’t be more Catholic than the Pope," she said. "Stremov and Liza Merkalova, why, they’re the cream of the cream of society. Besides, they’re received everywhere, and I"—she laid special stress on the I—"have never been strict and intolerant. It’s simply that I haven’t the time."</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; you don’t care, perhaps, to meet Stremov? Let him and Alexey Alexandrovitch tilt at each other in the committee—that’s no affair of ours. But in the world, he’s the most amiable man I know, and a devoted croquet player. You shall see. And, in spite of his absurd position as Liza’s lovesick swain at his age, you ought to see how he carries off the absurd position. He’s very nice. Sappho Shtoltz you don’t know? Oh, that’s a new type, quite new."</p>
<p role="noindent">Betsy said all this, and, at the same time, from her goodhumored, shrewd glance, Anna felt that she partly guessed her plight, and was hatching something for her benefit. They were in the little boudoir. "I must write to Alexey though," and Betsy sat down to the table, scribbled a few lines, and put the note in an envelope.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’m telling him to come to dinner. I’ve one lady extra to dinner with me, and no man to take her in. Look what I’ve said, will that persuade him? Excuse me, I must leave you for a minute. <target target-type="page" id="page_589">589</target>Would you seal it up, please, and send it off?" she said from the door; "I have to give some directions."</p>
<p role="noindent">Without a moment’s thought, Anna sat down to the table with Betsy’s letter, and, without reading it, wrote below: "It’s essential for me to see you. Come to the Vrede garden. I shall be there at six o’clock." She sealed it up, and, Betsy coming back, in her presence handed the note to be taken.</p>
<p role="noindent">At tea, which was brought them on a little tea-table in the cool little drawing room, the cozy chat promised by Princess Tverskaya before the arrival of her visitors really did come off between the two women. They criticized the people they were expecting, and the conversation fell upon Liza Merkalova.</p>
<p role="noindent">"She’s very sweet, and I always liked her," said Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You ought to like her. She raves about you. Yesterday she came up to me after the races and was in despair at not finding you. She says you’re a real heroine of romance, and that if she were a man she would do all sorts of mad things for your sake. Stremov says she does that as it is."</p>
<p role="noindent">"But do tell me, please, I never could make it out," said Anna, after being silent for some time, speaking in a tone that showed she was not asking an idle question, but that what she was asking was of more importance to her than it should have been; "do tell me, <target target-type="page" id="page_590">590</target>please, what are her relations with Prince Kaluzhsky, Mishka, as he’s called? I’ve met them so little. What does it mean?"</p>
<p role="noindent">Betsy smiled with her eyes, and looked intently at Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It’s a new manner," she said. "They’ve all adopted that manner. They’ve flung their caps over the windmills. But there are ways and ways of flinging them."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes, but what are her relations precisely with Kaluzhsky?"</p>
<p role="noindent">Betsy broke into unexpectedly mirthful and irrepressible laughter, a thing which rarely happened with her.</p>
<p role="noindent">"You’re encroaching on Princess Myakaya’s special domain now. That’s the question of an enfant terrible," and Betsy obviously tried to restrain herself, but could not, and went off into peals of that infectious laughter that people laugh who do not laugh often. "You’d better ask them," she brought out, between tears of laughter.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No; you laugh," said Anna, laughing too in spite of herself, "but I never could understand it. I can’t understand the husband’s rôle in it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"The husband? Liza Merkalova’s husband carries her shawl, and is always ready to be of use. But anything more than that in reality, no one cares to inquire. You know in decent society one doesn’t talk or think even of certain details of the toilet. That’s how it is with this."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_591">591</target>
<p role="noindent">"Will you be at Madame Rolandak’s fête?" asked Anna, to change the conversation</p>
<p role="noindent">"I don’t think so," answered Betsy, and, without looking at her friend, she began filling the little transparent cups with fragrant tea. Putting a cup before Anna, she took out a cigarette, and, fitting it into a silver holder, she lighted it.</p>
<p role="noindent">"It’s like this, you see: I’m in a fortunate position," she began, quite serious now, as she took up her cup. "I understand you, and I understand Liza. Liza now is one of those naïve natures that, like children, don’t know what’s good and what’s bad. Anyway, she didn’t comprehend it when she was very young. And now she’s aware that the lack of comprehension suits her. Now, perhaps, she doesn’t know on purpose," said Betsy, with a subtle smile. "But, anyway, it suits her. The very same thing, don’t you see, may be looked at tragically, and turned into a misery, or it may be looked at simply and even humorously. Possibly you are inclined to look at things too tragically."</p>
<p role="noindent">"How I should like to know other people just as I know myself!" said Anna, seriously and dreamily. "Am I worse than other people, or better? I think I’m worse."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Enfant terrible, enfant terrible!" repeated Betsy. "But here they are."</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_592">592</target>
</body>
</book-part>
<book-part book-part-type="Chapter" id="chapter18">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<title>CHAPTER <label>XVIII</label></title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>
<p role="noindent">They heard the sound of steps and a man’s voice, then a woman’s voice and laughter, and immediately thereafter there walked in the expected guests: Sappho Shtoltz, and a young man beaming with excess of health, the so-called Vaska. It was evident that ample supplies of beefsteak, truffles, and Burgundy never failed to reach him at the fitting hour. Vaska bowed to the two ladies, and glanced at them, but only for one second. He walked after Sappho into the drawing-room, and followed her about as though he were chained to her, keeping his sparkling eyes fixed on her as though he wanted to eat her. Sappho Shtoltz was a blonde beauty with black eyes. She walked with smart little steps in high-heeled shoes, and shook hands with the ladies vigorously like a man.</p>
<p role="noindent">Anna had never met this new star of fashion, and was struck by her beauty, the exaggerated extreme to which her dress was carried, and the boldness of her manners. On her head there was such a superstructure of soft, golden hair —her own and false mixed—that her head was equal in size to the elegantly rounded bust, of which so much was exposed in front. The impulsive abruptness of her movements was such that at every step the lines of her knees and the upper part of her legs were distinctly marked under her dress, and the question involuntarily rose to the mind where in the undulating, <target target-type="page" id="page_593">593</target>piled-up mountain of material at the back the real body of the woman, so small and slender, so naked in front, and so hidden behind and below, really came to an end.</p>
<p role="noindent">Betsy made haste to introduce her to Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Only fancy, we all but ran over two soldiers," she began telling them at once, using her eyes, smiling and twitching away her tail, which she flung back at one stroke all on one side. "I drove here with Vaska.... Ah, to be sure, you don’t know each other." And mentioning his surname she introduced the young man, and reddening a little, broke into a ringing laugh at her mistake— that is, at her having called him Vaska to a stranger. Vaska bowed once more to Anna, but he said nothing to her. He addressed Sappho: "You’ve lost your bet. We got here first. Pay up," said he, smiling.</p>
<p role="noindent">Sappho laughed still more festively.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Not just now," said she.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, all right, I’ll have it later."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Very well, very well. Oh, yes." She turned suddenly to Princess Betsy: "I am a nice person ... I positively forgot it ... I’ve brought you a visitor. And here he comes." The unexpected young visitor, whom Sappho had invited, and whom she had forgotten, was, however, a personage of such consequence that, in spite of his youth, both the ladies rose on his entrance.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_594">594</target>
<p role="noindent">He was a new admirer of Sappho’s. He now dogged her footsteps, like Vaska.</p>
<p role="noindent">Soon after Prince Kaluzhsky arrived, and Liza Merkalova with Stremov. Liza Merkalova was a thin brunette, with an Oriental, languid type of face, and —as everyone used to say—exquisite enigmatic eyes. The tone of her dark dress (Anna immediately observed and appreciated the fact) was in perfect harmony with her style of beauty. Liza was as soft and enervated as Sappho was smart and abrupt.</p>
<p role="noindent">But to Anna’s taste Liza was far more attractive. Betsy had said to Anna that she had adopted the pose of an innocent child, but when Anna saw her, she felt that this was not the truth. She really was both innocent and corrupt, but a sweet and passive woman. It is true that her tone was the same as Sappho’s; that like Sappho, she had two men, one young and one old, tacked onto her, and devouring her with their eyes. But there was something in her higher than what surrounded her. There was in her the glow of the real diamond among glass imitations. This glow shone out in her exquisite, truly enigmatic eyes. The weary, and at the same time passionate, glance of those eyes, encircled by dark rings, impressed one by its perfect sincerity. Everyone looking into those eyes fancied he knew her wholly, and knowing her, could not but love her. At the sight of Anna, her whole face lighted up at once with a smile of delight.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_595">595</target>
<p role="noindent">"Ah, how glad I am to see you!" she said, going up to her. "Yesterday at the races all I wanted was to get to you, but you’d gone away. I did so want to see you, yesterday especially. Wasn’t it awful?" she said, looking at Anna with eyes that seemed to lay bare all her soul.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Yes; I had no idea it would be so thrilling," said Anna, blushing. The company got up at this moment to go into the garden.</p>
<p role="noindent">"I’m not going," said Liza, smiling and settling herself close to Anna. "You won’t go either, will you? Who wants to play croquet?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"Oh, I like it," said Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">"There, how do you manage never to be bored by things? It’s delightful to look at you. You’re alive, but I’m bored."</p>
<p role="noindent">"How can you be bored? Why, you live in the liveliest set in Petersburg," said Anna.</p>
<p role="noindent">"Possibly the people who are not of our set are even more bored; but we—I certainly—are not happy, but awfully, awfully bored."</p>
<p role="noindent">Sappho smoking a cigarette went off into the garden with the two young men. Betsy and Stremov remained at the tea-table.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_596">596</target>
<p role="noindent">"What, bored!" said Betsy. "Sappho says they did enjoy themselves tremendously at your house last night."</p>
<p role="noindent">"Ah, how dreary it all was!" said Liza Merkalova. "We all drove back to my place after the races. And always the same people, always the same. Always the same thing. We lounged about on sofas all the evening. What is there to enjoy in that? No; do tell me how you manage never to be bored?" she said, addressing Anna again. "One has but to look at you and one sees, here’s a woman who may be happy or unhappy, but isn’t bored. Tell me how you do it?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"I do nothing," answered Anna, blushing at these searching questions. "That’s the best way," Stremov put in. Stremov was a man of fifty, partly gray, but still vigorous-looking, very ugly, but with a characteristic and intelligent face. Liza Merkalova was his wife’s niece, and he spent all his leisure hours with her. On meeting Anna Karenina, as he was Alexey Alexandrovitch’s enemy in the government, he tried, like a shrewd man and a man of the world, to be particularly cordial with her, the wife of his enemy.</p>
<p role="noindent">"‘Nothing,’" he put in with a subtle smile, "that’s the very best way. I told you long ago," he said, turning to Liza Merkalova, "that if you don’t want to be bored, you mustn’t think you’re going to be bored. It’s just as you mustn’t be afraid of not being <target target-type="page" id="page_597">597</target>able to fall asleep, if you’re afraid of sleeplessness. That’s just what Anna Arkadyevna has just said."</p>
<p role="noindent">"I should be very glad if I had said it, for it’s not only clever but true," said Anna, smiling.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, do tell me why it is one can’t go to sleep, and one can’t help being bored?"</p>
<p role="noindent">"To sleep well one ought to work, and to enjoy oneself one ought to work too."</p>
<p role="noindent">"What am I to work for when my work is no use to anybody? And I can’t and won’t knowingly make a pretense about it."</p>
<p role="noindent">"You’re incorrigible," said Stremov, not looking at her, and he spoke again to Anna. As he rarely met Anna, he could say nothing but commonplaces to her, but he said those commonplaces as to when she was returning to Petersburg, and how fond Countess Lidia Ivanovna was of her, with an expression which suggested that he longed with his whole soul to please her and show his regard for her and even more than that.</p>
<p role="noindent">Tushkevitch came in, announcing that the party were awaiting the other players to begin croquet.</p>
<p role="noindent">"No, don’t go away, please don’t," pleaded Liza Merkalova, hearing that Anna was going. Stremov joined in her entreaties.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_598">598</target>
<p role="noindent">"It’s too violent a transition," he said, "to go from such company to old Madame Vrede. And besides, you will only give her a chance for talking scandal, while here you arouse none but such different feelings of the highest and most opposite kind," he said to her.</p>
<p role="noindent">Anna pondered for an instant in uncertainty. This shrewd man’s flattering words, the naïve, childlike affection shown her by Liza Merkalova, and all the social atmosphere she was used to,—it was all so easy, and what was in store for her was so difficult, that she was for a minute in uncertainty whether to remain, whether to put off a little longer the painful moment of explanation. But remembering what was in store for her alone at home, if she did not come to some decision, remembering that gesture—terrible even in memory—when she had clutched her hair in both hands—she said good-bye and went away.</p>
<target target-type="page" id="page_599">599</target>
</body>
</book-part>