<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//DTD CUP-BITS Book Interchange DTD v1.2//EN" "https://dtd.cambridge.org/schemas/2021/09/CUP-BITS-book1.dtd">
<book xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<book-part book-part-type="chapter" id="chap">
<book-part-meta>
<title-group>
<label>Chapter 1</label>
<title>ENGINEERING ELEGANT SYSTEMS</title>
</title-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>

<target target-type="page" id="page_99">99</target>
</body>
</book-part>
</book>
<letter id="l_1">
<to>
<name>Mr. Edward Vermylen</name>
<company>A. Zerega’s Sons, Inc.</company>
<address>28 Front St.
Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201</address>
<p>Dear Mr. Vermylen,</p>
<p role="indent">Your company has been one of our good customers for fourteen years. Naturally, we are very grateful
for your patronage and are eager to give you the speedy, efficient service you deserve. However, we regret to
say that it isn’t possible for us to do that when your trucks bring us a large shipment late in the afternoon, as
they did on November 10. Why? Because many other customers make late afternoon deliveries also. Naturally,
that causes congestion. That means your trucks are held up unavoidably at the pier and sometimes even your
freight is delayed.</p>
<p role="indent">That’s bad, but it can be avoided. If you make your deliveries at the pier in the morning when possible,
your trucks will be able to keep moving, your freight will get immediate attention, and our workers will get
home early at night to enjoy a dinner of the delicious macaroni and noodles that you manufacture.
Regardless of when your shipments arrive, we shall always cheerfully do all in our power to serve you
promptly. You are busy. Please don’t trouble to answer this note.
</p>
<regards>
<p>Yours truly,</p>
<name>J----- B-----, supt.</name>
</regards>
</letter>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>